[MUSIC]
Hi, welcome to the Haskell weekly podcast.
This show is about Haskell,
a purely functional programming language.
I'm Dustin Segers,
a software engineer here at ITProTV.
And I'm with the lead engineer here,
and he is the host for today.
>> Hey, Dustin.
It's good to be here with you in studio.
>> [LAUGH] It's good to be
here with you too, man.
>> Thanks for joining me.
My name's Taylor, as Dustin mentioned,
I am the lead developer at ITPro,
I also publish the Haskell weekly podcast.
And today we're gonna be
talking about a story
that was in one of the older
issues about Boolean Blindness.
>> Mm-hm.
>> Dustin, could you explain to
me what Boolean Blindness is?
>> So Boolean Blindness is basically,
where you are using a bool
in place of maybe, something that
could be expressed a little bit.
More or less generically?
>> So, with a bool we have,
it's either true or it's false.
>> Yes.
>> And that doesn't encode any
interesting information there.
Lots of things could be
represented as bools.
>> Correct.
>> A light switch could be a bool,
but Boolean blindness is saying that,
maybe we're better off
encoding that as Light Switch,
is a special data type that could either
be on or off instead of true or false.
Is that what you're saying?
>> Yes, pretty much, yeah.
>> So, what are the benefits of modeling
one of these things as a data type
rather than reusing bools.
>> It's more expressive.
So, let's use your light switch for
example.
On or off is better than
just saying true or false.
>> Right, cuz what does true mean?
>> Exactly.
So we could have a data type
that would be light switch,
and we could pass it in to a function.
And, it could be either on or
off versus true or false, which gives
a bit more meaning to what you have.
>> Exactly.
That's really nice when you're calling the
function because instead of saying some
function true, It'll say, some function
light switch on or light switch off.
>> Correct.
>> That dream of self-documenting code.
>> Yes, yes.
>> And addition to the code being
self-documenting when you call it,
the function, the documentation that
is generated for that function or,
if you're just reading through the code,
that's gonna be much nicer as well.
Because it's not gonna say, some function
takes five Booleans and returns something.
It'll take a light switch state and
a door state, and
all these different things that it needs.
One function that we use very frequently
in our code bases here is filter.
And filter says, give me some predicate,
some function that returns true or false.
And give me a list and
I'll give you back a smaller list
that fulfills that predicate.
But for me, every time I use filter,
I have to think, is this function
the thing that keeps things in or
the thing that keeps things out?
And I can never remember, and
the type signature doesn't really help me.
>> Right.
>> Could you tell me how Boolean
blindness might help there,
or not suffering from
Boolean blindness might help?
>> You could say, so
how much a filter this list of users
based on whether or
not they are part of a team, and
your data type if you will,
could be on team or
off team,
instead of just a regular old Boolean.
And you could use your filter to say,
I want to filter only these users who
are off the team, and then in that case,
your filter will only take the users
who are not on the team and
you can do whatever you want to there.
>> Right, so
that's a lot clearer than saying,
where team membership is true or
team membership is false,
it's self-documenting just
on the name of the value.
>> Correct.
>> But that filter function itself
is still a little confusing because,
we have to get the concept
we're interested in,
which is are they on the team or
aren't they into a Boolean?
So we have to say, some equality check
their, wouldn't it be nice if we could
have a filter where instead of the filter
function itself taking a Boolean,
it would take some other thing, like
keep this thing, or discard this thing.
>> Right, yes.
>> Instead of converting from
this user is on the team, or
this user is off the team into a Boolean,
we would convert it into a,
they should be kept as part of this filter
operation, or they should be removed.
Doesn't that clean things up a little bit?
>> Yes.
>> Would you prefer to use a function like
that, or would you prefer to keep using
the original filter that just
has bools all over the place?
>> I'd probably prefer, yeah, the one that
does not use bools all over the place.
>> Why is that?
What makes it better?
>> Well, it's more intuitive, it's more
expressive, so it's easier to understand.
The ax murderer who comes in later,
six months down the road,
and it's like, who wrote this code?
Won't come to find me.
>> It happens all the time.
[LAUGH]
>> Yes, exactly.
He'll be a bit more docile I would think,
so yeah.
>> He might put his ax away and
take out something else
instead like a feather duster.
[LAUGH]
>> Yeah, or a burger.
Yeah.
>> Burger.
[LAUGH]
>> [LAUGH]
>> As a gift for the person,
the earth is a wonderful code.
>> Yes, [LAUGH]
>> [LAUGH] That's one way we might
clean up this filter function and
avoid Boolean blindness.
There are other ways too and
this blog post mentions a few of them.
One example they give is changing
the name of the function.
Because, for me like I said the problem
I have with filter is that,
I can never remember does it filter
things in or does it filter them out?
I don't know which way it goes?
>> Mm-hm.
>> So maybe a better name would be better?
Is there some other name we could use for
filter that might be good?
>> Filtering in or
filter out would be nice.
>> [LAUGH] It's a step in
the right direction for sure.
Let's say that we did change
the name of the filter to.
Filter in but it still took a Boolean.
>> Okay.
>> Is there any, like what's the upshot of
doing it that way versus the way we were
talking about before about
using a different type.
>> So,
filter in that would take me maybe a keep.
>> Mm-hm, okay.
>> The upshot there is when you're
not confused about what's going on,
and the self documenting code dealio.
And yeah,
it's just more expressive again, and
it seems like it would
be better to upkeep,
well to help with upkeep
in the future as well, so.
>> Yeah, cuz imagine that, bringing
it back to our light switch example.
>> Mm-hm.
>> We currently have a very simple
light switch that is either on or off.
But what if we upgrade our lights and
suddenly we have dimmers.
And we want to filter out for
all the lights that are on.
Well, how do we decide if a light is on or
not, to keep it in this filter or
to rule it out?
Maybe we wanna say well,
at 50% brightness, or
once the dimmer switch hits halfway up,
then it counts as on.
And in coding that I think,
is a lot clearer,
because we would have a function
that takes a light switch state and
gives us back a, do you keep it or
do you rule it out?
Versus something that just
returns a Boolean, right?
And then you're thinking, well what
is this Boolean used for later on?
>> Right. [LAUGH] >> Yeah, and
it can be really challenging as you said,
six months down the line, when that ax
wielding psychopath looks at your code.
They're thinking, well I can sort of
understand the dis function returns true,
when the light switch if more than 50% on,
but what does that mean?
>> Right.
>> [LAUGH]
>> Yes.
>> So we've talked about two methods for
changing filter to make it
more intention-revealing.
Either, changing the type of
the function that it takes
to return some better thing, like keep or
discard instead of a Boolean.
We've also talked about renaming it.
So instead of just filter,
you have filter in or filter out.
>> Mm-hm.
>> The third option presented in
this blog post is to make the type,
return the thing that
you wanna end up with.
So instead of saying, I'm only
selecting things to keep or discard,
instead you're kind of mapping as you're
going along and producing new values.
But you're wrapping those values in maybe,
and you're only keeping the ones
that are just some value and
discarding all the ones that are nothings.
That feels to me like it's very
clear about which ones to keep.
Because obviously, if you have a nothing,
there isn't anything to keep there and
you can go ahead and throw that one out.
>> Right.
>> And when there's a jest,
you can hang on to that thing.
But, it's unfortunate I think,
that the two operations are getting balled
together, where you have mapping and like
changing the values in this collection,
at the same time as mapping over them and
filtering some of them out?
>> Yeah.
>> What do you think about that?
Is that a good trade off or is that weird?
>> So, my gut feeling says,
I don't like it, and mainly because,
it's been drilled into my
head that mutation is evil.
>> [LAUGH]
>> So it-
>> It looks a little like mutation.
>> Yeah, yeah, it does.
Even if it's not explicitly mutation,
it does feel like we're changing,
Some essential piece of this.
It seems like side effects
are happening here.
So, I know we need those, but
just initially, I don't like that much?
>> Don't like it?
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah, I don't like it either, and for
the reason you mentioned, but
also when I look at the type like so.
If we had this weird filter function that
returned a maybe instead of returning
either yes or no, or keep it or
don't keep it, or Boolean, whatever.
It's not clear from the type signature
if the thing you're interested in doing
is changing the shape of these
values in their collection.
Or removing things from the collection.
>> Right.
>> And when we have the two
separate functions, map and filter,
that does each of those
things very specifically.
It can be clear to me as
a reader that this function,
it's gonna keep all the elements in there.
They may change a little bit, and
hopefully they do otherwise we're
not doing anything interesting.
>> Right.
>> Or, when if I see a filter I can think
okay, this isn't gonna change any of them.
It's only gonna remove some of them.
>> And I like having that assurance
because, when I'm trying to step through
code and think of all the states it could
be in, it's very useful for me to say.
Well, I know this operation is gonna keep
all the elements that I'm dealing with or
this one is not gonna change them.
>> Right, yes.
>> That makes debugging maintenance a lot
easier, so that's one of the reasons why I
don't like the other method of
doing this filter functions.
>> Gotcha,
yep I have to concur with those.
>> Taking it a step further,
another suggestion this blog post has for
a way to implement the same thing in yet
another way.
It seems like there is an endless
number of ways to implement this really
simple function.
>> Yes.
>> What they suggest is,
instead of returning a maybe,
so either you have something,
or you don't.
You could return a list that says,
either you have nothing or you have
exactly one thing, or you have two or
three or thousand or infinity of them.
Which is starting to look to me
not at all like a filter operation,
>> Right
>> And I'm having a hard time
thinking of a filter where, like, okay,
I want to filter out light
switches that are on or off.
But, every time I look at a light switch,
I produce two light switches.
>> Yeah, yeah.
>> That doesn't make any sense.
>> [LAUGH] They're multiplying.
>> [LAUGH] I just wanted to find
all the light switches are on and
now I have twice as many
light switches in here.
[LAUGH]
>> If only I could do that with money
that'd be nice.
>> [LAUGH]
>> I think that's coming in the next
version of Haskell.
[LAUGH]
>> Nice, print money, yes.
>> Okay so, I think we've covered a lot of
interesting ways to tackle this one very
simple problem of how do we
filter things out of collections,
is there anything else you
wanted to say about this topic?
>> No not really, other than that, I feel
like we encountered this a lot in ELM.
>> Yeah.
>> And I see that we are using it, but
we're trying to avoid Boolean blindness by
implementing types that,
convey what true or
false may mean specific to that function,
so.
>> Yeah, and I'm trying to think of a
concrete example that we've had recently,
can you think of one
from our own front end?
>> It's been a bit, but
I think it is this user assigned or not?
>> Mm-hm.
>> That might have been one of them.
>> I know that we have a lot of, I think
they're called accordions in our UI.
>> Yes, yeah.
>> Where, we have three steps, but
only one step can be open at a time.
>> Mm-hm.
>> And I think,
it's kind of natural to reach for
a Boolean in that case and
say, is this one open or not?
True or false?
And I think we try to represent
that as an actual type that
says-
>> Yeah.
>> This is accordion open or
accordion closed.
>> Yeah, collapsed and
uncollapsed, I believe we did.
>> And
does that make the code easier to read?
Easier to maintain, is it,
>> Yeah, I would say definitely,
even if it's just like small things,
you get the cognitive overhead.
it's reduced just because you
don't have to think much about it.
Like I said, it's just expressive.
>> Yeah..
>> It's nice.
>> You don't have to think
that's true mean this or that.
>> Yeah,
>> And
I know I stumble all the time
when we have a value or
a function that itself is negated,
so it says like not turned on.
>> Mm-hm.
>> Or turned off.
And turned off equal true and I think
well okay, so that means that it's off,
which means, turned on would be false.
And with this specific type, you don't
have to jump through those hoops every
time you are analyzing
one of these things.
>> Right, and even the, let's say
I remember in that article he had
a function of the type signature
that had a bunch of bools.
The bools were then replaced with more
meaningful, types, you can just look
at the function and determine a lot
more just from that alone as well.
>> Exactly, do you feel like
writing functions like that, or
writing code that uses
those functions is harder
than writing the similar
versions that use Boolean's?
>> I don't feel like they're harder.
I feel like they're a lot easier to use.
>> Mm-hm.
>> So there may be a little bit of,
okay, I just need to suss out what
true and false means here,
for this particular thing.
And then name it which is one
of the hardest things to do.
But, after I get done with that, yeah,
I think it's really nice to have.
>> So you're talking about the kind of
mechanics of refactoring a function to
use a specific type rather than Boolean,
right?
>> Right, yeah, I'm sorry.
>> No that's okay, that's good insight.
I meant to ask about, just day to day
using one when you have to write a new
function and you got to use one of these
that needs a specific type, is it annoying
to have to import that type and wonder
why didn't they just use a Boolean here?
>> I think after you
realize how useful it is
to have an expressive type like this.
Yeah, I think you get over that pretty
quickly if you have any sorts of doubts or
yeah, negative feelings towards it.
>> I agree.
>> [LAUGH]
>> I've grown to dislike Boolean so much,
when I see one in the code I think
there's a type lurking here.
I need to write it down somewhere.
[LAUGH]
>> We've been talking about
Boolean Blindness, and how you can avoid
it by using more expressive types.
With me today, has been Dustin,
once of the engineers here at ITPro.
Thanks, Dustin for joining me.
>> And thank you for having me.
>> And thank you, for
listening to the Haskell weekly podcast.
This has been episode four.
If you liked our show, find out more
at our website HaskellWeekly.news.
Thanks again for listening.
I've been your host, Taylor Fausak,
and we'll see you next week.
[MUSIC]