[MUSIC]
Welcome to the Haskell Weekly Podcast.
This show is about Haskell,
a purely functional programming language.
I'm your guest, Jason Fry,
I'm a software engineer here at ITProTV.
With me as always today is your host,
Taylor Fausak,
he's the lead engineer here at ITProTV.
Thank you for joining me today, Taylor.
>> Hey Jason, thanks for hosting me.
>> So what are we getting into today?
>> Today we're gonna be getting into
a post in the most recent issue of
Haskell Weekly that talks about
using GHCID for web development.
And using it to have a quick feedback
cycle so that you're not waiting for
the compiler all day long.
>> Yeah, yeah we use GHCID here.
>> We do.
>> It's very speedy.
I would love to talk
a little more about this.
Cool so where are we starting,
what are we doing?
>> So we'll start kind of
at the dark ages, I guess.
>> Ooh.
>> Far away from GHCID to talk about how
bad it is and then as we kind of
improve things, we'll get closer and
closer to GHCID and
the beauty that it gives you.
>> Okay.
So when do the dark ages start?
>> [LAUGH]
>> A few years ago?
>> Time-wise I'm not sure but
tool wise they start with
just GHC the compiler itself.
This blog post talks
about web development.
And if you're producing
a website with Haskell,
you may run GHC which will
produce an executable for you and
then you'll run the executable
to make your website.
That's in comparison to something like
Ruby where it's just a script and
running the script produces a website,
there's no intermediate compilation step.
>> Okay, so that intermediate compilation
step that makes the process for web
development a lot slower cuz you have to
re-render it in your browser and all that.
>> Right, you have to compile it and
then either generate your files or
start a new web server or whatever,
and then go look in your browser for
the changes, pretty slow.
>> Okay, yeah, that is pretty slow.
So what is the next step from that?
What happens next?
>> The next step and this is the one that
we were most familiar with here at ITPro
in recent memory is using some type
of file watcher to do that thing for
you, in our case we were using Stack.
There are many tools that do this
Stack is the most convenient for
us because it does a lot of other things.
But Stack has an option dash dash file
watch to say when any of the files in
your project change go ahead and
rebuild the whole thing,
so that handles the compilation
side of things.
It also has an extra option called
exec that says once the build has
finished do this other thing.
So you can say watch all the files,
rebuild it when any of them change and
then once that build has succeeded,
rerun the site generator or the server or
whatever it is.
>> Okay, I actually use that Stack Build
whenever I'm writing a script to
do something to interact with the database
to fix some customer data or something.
So I always use Stack Build fast,
why would I ever not, I'm not sure?
And by-
>> And to be clear,
fast means build it quickly, not
the thing you're producing will be fast.
In fact, the thing that you're producing
will be really slow because what fast does
is turn off optimizations.
>> It says, I don't actually need the code
you're generating to be fast I just wanna
know if it type checks or whatever.
>> Okay, I always was curious about that.
I knew that it was compiling it
faster but, okay, that makes sense.
It turns off the optimization so it really
is more geared towards fast feedback
cycle, writing the code but
not production stuff?
>> Yeah.
>> Okay, that makes sense.
>> That's exactly right.
>> So we'll do the fast flag,
as well as the file watch flag but
it doesn't actually pick up on my changes.
I still have to go over to the terminal
and press Enter to redo that.
Is that always happened like that?
>> Not always.
I think that's a side effect of
our local development environment
where we use Docker and we're running
Stack inside of Docker on Mac OS.
And there's a bug in how Mac OS
implements these file notifications and
Stack doesn't pick up on the change
even though it should probably should.
>> That's right so
really quite separate from GHCID-
>> Yes.
>> And Stack and all that?
>> I think I know where you're
going with that though,
because with GHCID it
does pick up the changes.
>> Mm-hm.
>> And
there's no secret sauce difference
between those two things.
It's just that GHCID is using a newer
version of some library behind the scenes
that works around this bug and the version
of Stack that we're on and in fact,
I think the next version to be released
will have that same version but
the one we're on doesn't have it.
>> Ooh to be released, do we have
an insight as when that will be Taylor?
[LAUGH]
>> No,
no idea the Stack release
process is a mystery to me.
[LAUGH]
>> Yes, I'm sure it is to everyone.
So that's where we are with GHC, Stack,
file watch but and you can use exec to
run something arbitrary,
like start your server again or something.
But that's still kind of
a slow feedback loop,
especially compared to JavaScript,
as I commented last week.
>> Yeah.
>> It's so fast,
that it doesn't have to compile anything.
>> [LAUGH]
>> It's just so quick.
So what comes next?
>> Well, it's funny you mention
not compiling anything,
because that's really the only
way to speed things up here.
One of the slowest parts of the Stack file
watch feedback loop is that it
has to link your executable and
rebuild it and get all these things
lined up that just take a while.
There's another way of doing this
feedback loop before we get to
GHCID which is using GHCI directly.
And instead of rerunning GHC and
then rerunning your executable
you can have a ripple prompt up
with your whole project loaded.
And then when you make a change,
you go over to the ripple and you type,
colon reload or just colon r and then
hit Enter and it'll rebuild everything.
So it has a manual step involved,
but since it's in GHCI,
it's going to be a lot faster.
The I in GHCI stands for
interactive or interpreted, and
that means that it's not exactly
compiling things behind the scenes and
it also isn't doing any optimizations.
So you're getting that quick compilation
speed that the dash dash fast flag gives
you and you're not wasting any time
actually producing an executable and
linking it and all that stuff.
>> So, I have so many questions-
>> [LAUGH]
>> But we're gonna get into some nuts and
bolts of that and so
I will punt on that for another time.
So yeah, we actually began to flirt
with that workflow, I don't know,
a year ago or something.
It was just too much of a burden.
>> [LAUGH]
>> To type colon r.
>> To press, yeah colon r,
who's got the time?
[LAUGH]
>> Who's got the time?
And, I'm maybe a particularly
lazy developer so
I want my feedback loop, I mean,
to be in the past if I can get it just-
>> [LAUGH]
>> Faster than instant.
So I kept complaining and
kept complaining.
>> [LAUGH]
>> And heard about this GHCID thing and so
what happens next in
the iteration of this stuff?
>> So the last hopefully or maybe not last
the iteration we're on right now is GHCID.
And the way I like to think of GHCID
is it takes that workflow I just
described of having GHCI open it and
pressing colon r whenever something
changes, and automates it.
And-
>> Brilliant.
>> [LAUGH]
>> Yeah, brilliant.
[LAUGH]
>> Million dollar idea.
At its core,
that's basically what it's doing.
It's using a file watcher
like the Stack Build did but
instead of creating an executable,
it's running everything in GHCI.
And it'll pick up your change,
it'll reload everything, and
then it'll show you the errors if
there were any, and if there weren't,
it'll run whatever you tell it to run.
>> Mm-hm.
It's really cool, we really enjoy it here.
There's not my understanding of the editor
integrations that are available they don't
really show you the errors in the code,
it's still in a side panel or something.
>> Mm-hm.
>> Are there maybe editors I'm not aware
of that are doing this better or
is that just the limitation of GHCID or?
>> There are probably editors that do
it better, I am not aware of any or
I haven't explored this enough.
For me I feel comfortable enough and
productive enough having
basically my editor up and
the terminal up at the same time and
just kind of looking between them.
I definitely would prefer, a red
squiggly underline in the editor, but
it hasn't been worth it yet for
me to figure out how to get that lined up.
Yeah, I know that you have some experience
setting that up with Haskell IDE
engine, right?
>> Yeah, I was just gonna say
I've tried to make that work,
because that kind of is the ideal
situation where you have nearly
instant feedback as you're
typing almost it's that quick.
But the problem is there's some memory
leak in the GHC version that it uses or
something and so
after about a half hour or an hour or
two your entire computer crashes.
>> [LAUGH]
>> It's not always but it's bad.
>> It doesn't sound good.
>> No it's not good.
So, can't really use HIE that well,
one of our coworkers has a script that
will just kill HIE every time it hits-
>> [LAUGH]
>> 2 gigs of memory usage or more-
>> Problem solved.
>> [LAUGH] Memory leak solved.
But it noticeably slows down the machine,
noticeably slows down the editor.
I'm running Vim with a very
lightweight vimrc, and
that was still crashing at least
once a day [LAUGH] because of HIE,
I commented out that, and only that,
no crashes in the last week.
>> Hard to get more
lightweight than that set up.
>> Right.
So HIE has great promise, I can't wait for
it to get stable in that sense, but
like you, I've just kind of gotten used
to having GHCID up, I have my editor up,
I save, I see the issues,
I go fix them, hopefully I go fix them.
>> [LAUGH]
>> For some reason that feels awkward but
I've been doing it for enough months
now that I'm kind of used to it.
>> Right.
>> It's not what I want.
>> You're desensitized to it?
>> Yeah, I'm desensitized to it.
I want the feedback loop
to be as quick as possible.
We have all our stuff containerized
in the Docker stuff we use Mac OS so
it's got that issue with file
watch doesn't do it properly.
But even if it did
the feedback loop was still-
>> It's still slow.
>> Multiple minutes-
>> Yeah.
>> At one point before you
started rejiggering things.
>> Yeah,
I think we're much better these days but
it's still a lot slower to use
the Stack Build than the GHCl.
>> Yeah and at this point GHCID,
it's really quick,
it's pretty easy to set up like
containerizing it wasn't very difficult or
just running it on the metal
is very straightforward.
So we've only been using GHCID for
six months-
>> Something like that.
>> Eight months maybe.
>> It hasn't been long.
>> Why having we been doing
it from [LAUGH] the get go?
>> That's a great question.
I don't know why we didn't
use it from the outset.
I think that I ran into some
problems getting it set up.
They weren't insurmountable,
obviously, we're using it now.
But the way our project was structured,
we had one kind of top level project
that had lots of smaller packages in it.
And it was hard to get GHCID to run
all of those packages simultaneously.
And part of that is our fault
because we had multiple or
within each package we had
module names that were repeated.
So package a had module x and
package b also had module x and
they defined different things.
And with GHCID it has to be able to
pull everything into scope at once.
So it says, well,
you had module x over here and
module x over there I don't know
which one you want I'm gonna crash.
>> I remember this yes.
[LAUGH] So we had to restructure our app
essentially, our code base to use GHCID.
>> More or less yeah.
>> So don't do it that way.
>> [LAUGH] Start with GHCID.
>> Yeah start with GHCID and
it'll go a lot faster.
So, what are some of
the neat features of GHCID?
>> I'm glad you asked, I was gonna loop
back to bring up something about HIE.
You said that you want the feedback
cycle to be as short as possible and
with HIE I think that's
as good as it can get.
>> Yeah.
>> It's integrated tightly with the editor
and it gives you very quick feedback
about the code you're writing.
However often you want feedback
beyond just syntax errors or
type errors or stuff like that.
You wanna run your test suite,
or you wanna launch a server and
poke around in your browser,
or you wanna run an executable
against a test file you have locally.
You can't exactly do that with HIE.
>> Right.
>> Because its whole purpose is to
integrate with your editor and your editor
hopefully isn't doing those things.
>> [LAUGH]
>> I don't know yours might be
with VScode.
>> I knew that was gonna be a shot
at VScode-
>> [LAUGH]
>> I knew it.
>> Should've been a shot of Emacs.
>> Yeah, there you go.
>> [LAUGH]
>> I can run VScode in Emacs.
>> There you go.
Probably the other way around too.
>> Yeah.
>> I bring that up because one of
the nice things about GHCID is that you
can run arbitrary things
after your code builds.
And since it is essentially just a GHCI
ripple, you can type whatever you could
type into the ripple into your command
line options for GHCID and have them run.
So in our case,
we often run like do our build and
then run our web server,
or run our test suite.
And you'll get your actual test suite
output right there as fast as possible
once your build has completed.
>> Yeah that's really nice for us because
at this point you have set it up so
that it compiles and then if it
compiles it runs the test suite.
>> Mm-hm.
>> And
it's really nice because sometimes you
don't want to run the whole test suite
when you know you're in
the middle of something.
You don't really need it to run,
it's just sort of running silently in
the background, you have the information
you need it compiles or not.
>> Mm-hm.
>> That's what you need right now.
>> Yeah.
>> And
then you make sure you run the test suite
multiple times throughout you while you're
developing but just not every single save,
you don't need that.
>> Mm-hm.
>> So
by having it silently run in
the background at the end I find that so
valuable.
I don't have to worry about it,
if I don't care about it in the moment,
it's really helpful.
>> Another nice thing that GHCID does, in
relation to test suites, is that if your
test suite is running, and then you make
another change in your editor and save it,
it'll stop that run of your test suite,
and rebuild it, and rerun it.
So you don't have to sit there,
like you do with the Stack Build, and
wait for the tests to succeed or
fail in order to start another build for
the change you just made.
>> Yeah, that´s nice.
So, you mentioned you can run some
arbitrary something with the exec command.
Is that what it is, you use exec command?
>> Or
I think in GHC idea it's called test.
>> Yes.
>> Which is a little
confusing-
>> Yes.
>> Because you can run non-tests.
>> Yes, it's a test flag but
you can target whatever you want.
>> Yeah.
>> Which when
you showed me this a little while ago,
confused me as it should.
>> [LAUGH]
>> But it was really helpful because I was
writing a script and I had it set up so
that when I ran it it gave me meaningful
output, and then I just needed to change
the innards to change the output.
So you said well you can you use
the test flag, target this script and
every single time you save it will run
that and show you the output instead of,
saving, seeing if it compiles, and
then manually running the script.
>> Right, how I made it.
>> My gosh, I just saved five seconds.
Thank you so much.
>> [LAUGH]
>> But really, it was really a little bit,
I mean, really cool for
me because it makes the feedback
loop just that much faster.
>> Mm-hm.
>> And once I finally realized
the test flag meant whatever.
[LAUGH] Yeah,
you can use a target whatever.
>> Yeah, it's confusing because it says
test and you can use it for test and you
probably should but really what it means
is run this after the build succeeds.
>> Right, so that is really helpful.
So there's a lot of things that
we've done to speed up our feedback
loop going from GHC,
flirted with GHCI a little bit then GHCID,
we got it containerized,
we're trying to make HIE work for us.
I think we got that containerized at one
point or we nearly did test suite running,
restructured our app [LAUGH] to
make GHCID work better for us.
But I would say it's all worth
it because at this point,
our workflow as long as we're using
GHCID is very quick, very easy.
>> Mm-hm.
>> We don't have to worry about the issue
in Mac OS Docker where it doesn't actually
pick up the file changes correctly,
we don't have to worry about Stack.
As fast as it is, I mean really,
it is not slow but
really when you think of what you'll get.
>> It's on the order of a couple seconds
which can kind of kill your momentum if
you're looking for that fast feedback.
>> Yes, yes and that's something you were
saying earlier about how GHCID is so fast,
you just throw away save,
you don't really care, right?
>> Mm-hm.
>> So how does that affect
your development cycle or
how ever you do it?
>> The way that I used to develop with
Stack Build would be I would try to make
the code as perfect as I knew how,
and then hit Save, and
have the compiler check me and then if
I messed something up I'd go fix it.
And with GHCID I feel like my workflow
has changed to where I write something
that I know is gonna fail, and I get GHCID
to tell me exactly what's wrong with it,
and I make these real
small incremental steps.
>> Yeah.
>> One bit at a time, all the way through.
>> Yeah, not literally one B-Y-T-E.
>> [LAUGH]
>> Not writing one character.
When I can get into that flow, and go at
that clip, where I'm writing one line,
saving, one line saving,
that is so much faster for me.
>> Agreed.
>> That's because GHCID, I mean,
it feels like it's a less than
a second for it to recompile.
And we have like 600-
>> Yeah our app is not small.
>> It's not tiny, it's probably not huge,
I don't know what huge is in this regards,
but it feels large.
>> Mm-hm.
>> And it takes minutes for
the Docker container to come up,
build everything, do everything.
Once you have that up and going, running
GHCID in that container, it's so quick.
>> It's a game-changer.
>> Yeah, it really is, it really has
improved my personal dev practice.
I think the whole team, I mean,
I know the whole team likes it, but
I don't know how much has
revolutionized what they do.
>> [LAUGH]
>> But I know it's really improved mine,
and everybody's very happy with it.
>> Thanks for
being on the show with me today, Jason.
>> My pleasure, thank you.
>> And thank you for
listening to the Haskell Weekly Podcast.
This has been episode six.
If you liked our show, find out more
at our website, haskellweekly.news.
Thanks again for listening.
I've been your host, Taylor Fausak.
We'll see you again next week.
>> Bye everybody!
[MUSIC]