[MUSIC]
Hi, and
welcome to the Haskell weekly podcast.
This show is about Haskell,
a purely functional programming language.
He's your host, Taylor Fausak.
>> Hello.
>> And he's the lead engineer at ITProTV.
With him today is me, Jason Fry.
I'm one of the engineers here like a pro
as well, thanks for me joining you today.
>> Thanks for joining me Jayson and
for introducing yourself.
>> Yeah, we think it's fun for
the host not to introduce himself, so
what are we talking about today?
>> Well, I know that last week you were
asking me a little about the languages
that we use everyday here at ITPro and
kind of why we chose them.
For context the languages that we use
on the back end is mostly Haskell, and
on the front end is mostly Elm.
And there's a lot of choices, especially
on the front end of which language you
want to use and
you were wondering why do we use Elm?
>> Yeah, I've heard you talk about
PureScript, talk about it well and
I am interested in learning
more about PureScript.
So I guess the question I asked you was,
if we were to make this decision
again today knowing what we know and
experience we've gained over
the last year and a half.
How would the decision change?
Would we use PureScript on the front and
backend for simplicity's sake?
Would we still use Haskell and Elm?
Would we use Haskell and PureScript or
just go back to JavaScript.
>> [LAUGH] I'm pretty sure we
wouldn't go back to JavaScript.
Everybody seems to like working with
Haskell and Elm around here, so
I don't wanna subject them to
the horrors of JavaScript.
>> It's true, it's true.
>> If we made the decision again today,
I think we would end up with the same
choices, Haskell on the back-end and
Elm on the front-end.
But I wasn't here when we made
the decision in the first place.
So I'm not entirely sure if we
were still using JavaScript and
we had to reintroduce some new languages.
Would these ones gain traction or
would we end up using something else like
TypeScript on the front end and
go on the back end?
I don't know.
Obviously I like Haskell, so
I would really campaign for
that one on the back end.
But on the front end, I feel like there's
not a way to use Haskell on the front end
or at least not a way that I would want
to subject everybody on the team to.
I know that there are tools like GHCJS,
which let you compile Haskell into
JavaScript and use it on the front end,
but they seem to be not
quite production ready.
I'm a little hesitant to say that, because
I know that people are using them for
real and using them in production.
I am not ready to make that leap.
>> So what is not quite there for
GHCJS in your opinion?
Because I know very little about it but
I thought it's been around for
a little while and
it theoretically should be usable, but
you're like, no, we won't do that.
So what is lacking there in your opinion?
Yeah, before I get into what's lacking,
I just wanna do a brief recap or
a summary of what ghcjs is.
As the name implies, it is like GHC,
except it emits JavaScript rather
than static binaries or binaries.
And that's a nice thing
because you can use the exact
same code on the back end and the front
end and it'll work in both places.
One of the project goals for GHCJS is
to be able to compile all of hackage
that the Haskell package repository,
and have it just work on JavaScript.
That's in comparison to things like
Haste which are a subset of Haskell
that you have to specifically target.
So it is kind of like Haskell and
you can reuse a lot of the same stuff, but
not everything.
So I mentioned that because that's
kind of the upshot of GHCJS.
And if that sounds interesting
to anybody listening to this,
then I encourage you to go check it out.
But for me, one of the reasons that
I'm not excited about using GHCJS
in production, is that, well,
it comes down to do two things for me.
One is that it produces
very large build artifacts.
So the amount of JavaScript that it
produces is very high and the reason for
that is that it has to emulate the entire
GHC run time system in JavaScript.
All of the laziness, all of the multi
threaded abilities that GHC has,
it has to pretend to be
able to do those things or
actually do those things, in JavaScript,
which doesn't support them by default.
That means that a really small
application, the classic example of
something that prints hello world,
ends up being very large in GHCJS.
Versus if you wrote it
in plain JavaScript,
it's literally one line of code.
>> Okay, that makes sense.
My understanding though,
is that Elm produces a lot of
lines of code in JavaScript.
So when you're comparing these,
is it just a lot more with GHCJS even
though Elm is kind of a lot itself?
>> It is.
I wish I had some specific numbers to
point to, but
my kind of gut level understanding is that
GHCJS will produce JavaScript on
the order of like 1-10 megabytes.
Whereas ELM I think typically is under
one megabyte pretty comfortably.
>> Yeah, wow, that is a lot, okay.
>> [LAUGH]
>> And the number in my head for
Elm is for a small app you're
talking about kilobytes.
>> Yeah.
>> So that is a pretty big difference.
Okay, that makes sense.
>> And to touch on that for a second,
one of the reasons that Elm produces
a somewhat large JavaScript bundle is
that it has its own run time to handle
all the message passing and serializing
to and from JSON and all that stuff.
But it tries really hard to match the
semantics of JavaScript whenever possible,
so it's strict and it's single threaded.
So it doesn't have to deal with
multi threading or laziness or
anything like that.
So its run time can be a lot smaller.
>> So a little more about GHCJS,
is there anything else that's
sort of lacking there?
Or is that just sort of,
that's basically it?
>> That's the main one for me, but
kinda writing on the coattails of that is
that performance can be
a problem with GHCJS.
The GHC runtime,
the one that you get by default
just compiling a normal Haskell program,
has been tuned pretty well over the years.
Haskell is a surprisingly old language and
GHC is a surprisingly mature compiler.
And the stuff that you produce out
of it will perform really well.
You don't have to worry like, this is
tight loop is not gonna perform well.
You can, if you're interested in it,
really optimize the performance of stuff,
but it's a discussion for another time.
With GAHCJS it is largely
the work of one person and
it's seems to me I don't know
if this is true or not, but
it seems to be a more of a hobby
type project for that person.
It's not the thing they're
working on full-time.
So they don't have as many opportunities
to get these optimizations in there to
make the program that it produces really,
really fast.
However, even if they did have the time
to do that, it still has the problem of
basically running the Haskell
run time inside of JavaScript.
So you've got a price to pay just for
doing that.
So that performance makes me
kind of shy away from it.
Again, I wish I had some
specific numbers for
how Elm performs versus GHCJS
versus vanilla JavaScript.
And it's also my understanding that GHCJS
has improve quite a bit recently and
gotten a lot faster.
But I think it's still slower
than all of its contemporaries.
>> Okay, so let's compare those two then.
If the comparison is no
longer with Haskell,
like we're just always using
Haskell on the back end.
Then on the front end PeerScript versus
Elm pros cons, we went with Elm.
We really like Elm, but I do sometimes
wonder, because I'm just curious about
PeerScript if we were just going to
make the decision differently a year and
a half ago.
But you answered that what would we do
today we probably still use Haskell
and Elm.
So lets just compare them, PureScript
is pretty great you talk highly of it.
Sure, I really like using Purescript.
I used it kind of recreationally for
a while.
>> [LAUGH]
>> I've never used Purescript in
production, but
I know plenty of people who have, so
I have confidence in it in that regard.
Backing up a bit.
You mentioned that it was around a year
and a half ago that we started using Elm.
And it was kind of the entry way for
us into Haskell.
Before that the team was largely using
JavaScript with a smattering of other
languages, like maybe Go or
Rust something to that effect, right?
>> Yeah, I don't think we were using rust.
We weren't that cool back then.
But yeah, Angular one point,
something or other and
Go and I feel like we have
a TypeScript file in there somewhere.
>> [LAUGH].
>> Elm is nice because it is very simple,
especially in comparison to Haskell.
And because of that simplicity,
it has the ability to produce very
helpful and illuminating error messages.
When you do something wrong in Haskell,
not you specifically, but
anybody on the team, often the error
message that it spits out is inscrutable.
>> Yes.
>> And I have frequently seen team members
completely stumped by an error message and
call me over, and I have to say, well,
what it's really telling you is this, and
here's how you may want to fix it.
Versus when something goes wrong in Elm
that's almost literally what the Elm
compiler tells you.
It says, hey, I saw you did this.
I was expecting this.
Here's how you might fix it.
And that's super useful when so
many other things are changing,
because Elm forces you into
this weird architecture,
weird from the perspective of an angular
developer, it's completely foreign.
And it's a strange syntax, and
it's a different compiler.
All of these things changed,
it's really nice to have that
helpful compiler there at your side.
>> Absolutely.
It's one of the things that we
really like, and with Elm 19,
it's an even friendlier compiler.
Took me out to dinner last night.
>> [LAUGH]
>> Complete gentlemen.
But for when we started Elm a year and
a half ago,
it was really helpful to get those
that sort of helpful feedback.
But we still were pretty new and
even with it being a friendly compiler,
we still were stumped much more often.
But now we have some more people in
our company that are coming in and
learning Elm.
More of our design team is starting to
learn Elm and that highlights it even more
for us, is that they have repeatedly said
my goodness this compiler is so helpful.
So that is really cool to hear them
say that and for us to be reminded.
Cuz we begin to take it for
granted and especially because we
compare it to the Haskell compiler.
Which just today had
some issue that I thought
when we compiled it was going to complain
because a parens was in the wrong spot and
it gave some really gnarly output.
I was like I don't know what you
were saying, put a parens there and
my kinda gut just tells that's what is is,
sure enough that's what it was.
>> Yeah.
>> But
if I had not already suspected I
was gonna have a parens issue I
don't know long I would've looked at
that output not knowing what to do.
>> Yeah, I often find that the GHT
compiler is more useful at telling me that
there is an error rather than
what exactly the error is.
Usually I'm like, well,
I probably know what it is already.
>> Yeah.
>> Thanks for letting me know Haskell.
>> Yeah, so we love Elm's compiler.
Purescripts' compiler just isn't quite as
friendly, it sort of as a couple tattoos,
smokes or something.
>> Not nearly as friendly.
In fact, when you compare Elm to Haskell,
and you see how much better Elam is,
I feel that when you compare
Haskell to Purescript,
you see how much better Haskell is.
>> So that bad?
Yeah, granted,
my perspective of the Purescript
compiler is woefully out of date.
I used it maybe two or
three years ago, and I I am confident that
in the meantime things have gotten better.
But it feels a lot like it technically
tells you what the problem is.
But it drowns you in a bunch of
contexts and weird variable names and
other things and weird terms.
From my point of view, I wouldn't be super
comfortable throwing a junior developer in
front of the Purescript compiler and
having confidence that they
could figure things out.
Or not a junior developer,
but our front end team.
If they were working on
a PureScript application,
I would expect to be called
over there frequently,
having to puzzle out some output
from the PureScript compiler.
>> Right, so one of the draws of
JavaScript on the front end and
back end is the simplicity.
Elm is not yet usable on the back end,
I don't believe.
Haskell, as we've discussed for us, we're
not going to use it on the front end.
So is there still value though in going
with Purescript because you can use
it on the front end and the back end?
Maybe not for
us because we can do Haskell and
we think Haskell, as good as
PureScript is, Haskell is even better.
But if Haskell wasn't an option for us for
some reason, does that make more sense
to go PureScript front and back, or
Elm front end, Purescript back end,
or something different?
>> Given the choice and
having to exclude Haskell,
I probably would choose
Purescript on the back end.
I may end up choosing
something even more niche.
Actually, I don't know that would be
more niche but something like OCaml or
ReasonML, all of which can
compile to JavaScript.
So for instance, if I had a mandate that
said you have to run Node JS on the back
end, I would say, okay,
I'll do Purescript.
>> I would say why,
why do I have this mandate.
>> Who's making these mandates.
In those situations I would choose
something like Purescript or
OCaml or ReasonML over GFCJS.
There's plenty of languages
that compile to JavaScript.
I think that Purescript in a lot
of ways is better than Haskell.
It addresses a lot of the problems with
Haskell that come from it being a very old
language that has sort of ossified around
these strange original design decisions.
For instance,
not having anonymous records, so
every time you wanna
build a new data type,
you have to explicitly say these are all
the names of the fields and their types.
Versus in Purescript you can just create
one as easily as you create a tuple or
a list or whatever.
>> Nice.
Similarly, strings in Haskell are
notoriously a linked list of characters,
which is one of the worst
representations you could come up with.
>> I feel like I could come up
with a worst one, but sure.
>> Whereas in Purescript, they're
basically the same as JavaScript strings.
Which, given how ubiquitous JavaScript is,
we have to assume are at
least somewhat acceptable.
>> Yeah, yeah.
Okay, so
Purescript does the anonymous records,
which reduces a lot of boiler plate.
So if you have a user record with a name
and an age and an occupation, and
blood type or whatever, sure, and
you want a subset of that record for
some other purpose, so
you have your master record.
And then you have well here,
I just want these three fields,
but there, I want these five fields.
That's what you're talking
about with anonymous records?
>> Exactly.
As an example from our code base,
we have the fully fledged user type that
has those fields you were talking about.
Not blood type,
we don't capture that about our users.
>> Yet.
>> [LAUGH]
>> But we also have a minimal user,
which is useful when we're writing tests,
or when we want to add a new user, and
we don't have all of
their information yet.
And we don't care, we don't have their
address or their billing information,
or any of that stuff.
>> Their shirt size.
>> Their shirt size, exactly.
With Haskell we have to
explicitly make a user,
a minimal user,
a slightly more minimal user,
a slightly less minimal user, user with
a bunch of other fields tacked on.
And in Purescript you can make all
of those a little more implicitly,
a little more off the cuff.
And as we frequently experienc,
one of the hardest things in day-to-day
software engineering is naming things.
>> Yes.
>> And
when you have to make new
Explicit types of everything,
you have to make names for them.
And this sounds kind of like a petty
concern, but it's honestly hard to do.
Because if you have a user and
you have a user with two different fields,
they're both users.
So which one, you have to call
one user and one something else.
It's frustrating.
>> User prime.
>> [LAUGH]
>> User prime prime.
>> Please don't do that.
>> User prime prime prime.
>> [LAUGH]
>> We don't allow primes here.
>> No primes.
Yeah, so I like that,
I can certainly hear someone who prefers
the Haskell way of doing it, though.
Because arguably,
those are different things, and
different things who have different names.
>> Very true.
>> But in the day-to-day,
it is just kind of inconvenient.
So is there anything else that comes
to mind, Purescript being better,
maybe than Haskell in some way,
or some other benefits to it?
I think that it has a lot of well
thought out type level features.
This isn't something we typically
work with in our work at ITPro.
We try to stay in the value
level as much as possible.
But Haskell is moving in this direction
where it's getting closer and
closer to having dependent types
where your type signatures and
your type computations can
depend on the values themselves.
And the classic example of this
is a list where you know how many
elements are in that list.
And so you could group, for
instance, with a map operation,
that you don't change
the number of elements.
I don't really wanna get
into dependent types.
But suffice to say that I think
Purescript has a has a lot more
niceties in the type system that,
to get them done in Haskell,
you have to turn on a bunch
of language extensions and
jump through some weird hoops and do some
things that aren't very comfortable.
So to bring it back home,
I think you original question was, if we
weren't using Haskell on the back end,
what would we be using on the back end?
>> Yeah, yeah.
Let's talk about that.
>> So ultimately I think I
would choose Purescript.
The reasons that I prefer Haskell
over Purescript right now are that it
produces executables, binary executables
which are a lot easier to deploy.
In our instance we stuff the executable
into an empty docker container,
throw it up in AWS and run it.
With Purescript we have to stuff
all of our code in the container,
along with all of its NPM dependencies and
all of the power dependencies, and no JS.
And then throw that up on AWS and it's
a much bigger container, there's a lot
more points of failure and lots of
security, well things that could go wrong.
Not to say that nothing could go
wrong with the Haskell thing, but
it's conceptually simpler to deal with.
Also Haskell has multi-threading built in.
So if I want to say, send this email off
on a separate thread, I can do that.
And it's built right in.
Versus doing that in JavaScript or
Purescript you have to handle that
with asynchronous and, sorry.
Asychrony and call backs.
So you have to say, well, do this.
But while that thing is executing,
nothing else can actually happen.
So if you have some CPU intensive stuff
that you want to do on a separate thread,
you can't, you have to rely on a much more
heavyweight abstraction like a queue.
So you publish work to the queue and
then have something else,
some entirely separate process pull
it off the queue and do that work.
So those kind of operational concerns are
what makes me lean toward Haskell versus
Purescript right now.
>> Okay, that multithreading
constraint sounds pretty significant.
Because a lot of what a back end is going
to do at some point, maybe not a lot of
what it does, but frequently you're
going to be doing something like that,
where you're wanting to handle something
asynchronously send off an email.
>> Yeah, almost all the time.
>> Yeah.
Always sending emails.
So that makes a lot of sense.
Purescript sounds great.
But if you can do, if you can use Haskell,
it sounds like you should.
>> You should.
>> Of course, that's our opinion because
that's literally what we're doing.
But I start to see that
a little bit better now.
Thank you.
>> So we're choosing Haskell on
the back end over Purescript because
Haskell just has more
tooling like asynchronicity,
whereas PureScript is
a little more complicated.
It's easier to deploy because Haskell
just has the binary that you deploy that.
Whereas PureScript,
a lot more points of failure there.
Again these things tend
to be solved problems but
there's always cracks in that so
just nicer, simpler to think about.
Simpler to handle.
So that's Haskell versus Purescript
on the back end just quickly.
On the-
>> And to jump in for just a second,
I would love to use Elm on the back end,
but it's not currently an option.
And I feel like Elm is doing very
well at targeting the front end and
its particular niche that
it wants to dominate.
I'm very happy that they're doing that.
If I could use it on the back end,
I would love to, but-
>> Really?
That's the first I've heard of this.
Elm on the back end,
Haskell on the front end.
>> [LAUGH] You heard it here first.
>> Precisely.
So, Elm over Purescript,
primarily because of the compiler.
Purescript has a lot more complexity,
a lot more robustness in some areas.
But you don't need those strictly.
They're really quite
helpful in some cases, so
maybe your use case,
you really do need those things.
But for most people of of the time,
Elm totally targets single page apps.
They are focused on that, and
they're doing it quite well.
The compiler makes it
really easy to pick up
this new paradigm of functional
programming, a new syntax.
It has, we didn't talk about this, but
something that we like a lot here at ITPro
is, it has this architecture built
right in to the language itself.
And it's nice to not have to think about
that or worry about that, it's just there.
>> Right.
>> The tooling's really good.
It's an opinionated formatter, so you
don't have formatting wars or arguments.
So, those are some of the reasons
that you mentioned and
then I just threw on top of
that of Elm over Purescript.
It's like Purescript seems really good,
but
Haskell might just be a little better than
it in a lot of cases on the back end and
Elm might be just a little better than it
In a lot of the cases in the front end.
But I just need to use it
recreational like you used to.
>> [LAUGH]
>> Is what I need to do.
>> Thanks for
being on the show with me today, Jason.
>> Thank you.
>> It was great to have you here
talking about Haskell versus Elm versus
Purescript.
A fight for the ages.
>> Versus a bunch of other things.
>> We don't talk about them too much.
[LAUGH] And thank you for
listening to the Haskell weekly podcast.
This has been episode three.
If you liked our show, find out more
at our website, haskellweekly.news.
Thanks again for listening.
I've been your host Taylor Fausak,
and we'll see you again next week.
>> Bye.
[MUSIC]