[MUSIC]
Hello, and
welcome to the Haskell weekly podcast.
I'm your host Taylor Fausak.
I'm the lead developer at ITProTV.
And with me in the studio
today is Cody Goodman.
Thanks for being with us, Cody.
>> Thanks, Taylor, I hear we're
gonna talk about some exceptions.
>> We are, before we get to that,
just a quick overview.
Haskell is a safe,
purely functional programming language
with a fast concurrent runtime.
And as Cody mentioned, we're gonna be
talking about exceptions in Haskell today.
In particular,
we're looking at this article posted by
Mark Karpov called exceptions tutorial.
It's from the yet
to be published intermediate Haskell book.
Really we're just going to jump right in.
So Cody,
why do we even bother with exceptions?
Why not have pure computations everywhere?
>> Well,
we're trying to model the real world.
The real world isn't perfect, so we
have to have some way of capturing that.
Exceptions are an imperfect but
time-tested, proven way of doing that.
We know them from other languages
that we've worked with,
other imperative languages.
But we get to Haskell,
we start learning it.
We see these different paradigms,
these different ways of
modeling the world around us.
Why can't we just stuff
exceptions into that model, and
get all the benefits as well?
And it turns out, after you try that,
you'll see that coming up with
the exception hierarchies, making models
that make sense is really difficult.
Whenever you want to add
another exception, for
instance, you have to type that out,
account for it somewhere else.
It becomes quite becomes quite laborious.
>> Yeah, and let's back up a minute and
make this concrete.
You mentioned that the real world,
unfortunately, has imperfections,
unlike our pure,
crystalline world of Haskell.
What are some of those things
that we could talk about,
just to have a concrete
example to play with?
>> If you just take integer division, for
instance, something that could go wrong
is a user passing a zero and
a divide by zero happening.
>> Yeah and then the whole app blows up,
which may be what we want, maybe not.
Let's say that somebody divides by zero,
one way that we could model
that is with an exception.
I think a lot of languages,
like Python, do that.
Haskell may even do that.
But what are some other
options we have for
how to model that other than an exception.
>> One other option,
if you've been learning Haskell or
using it much,
is the maybe or either monad.
Now in this case, the either monad
wouldn't make a lot of sense.
Because there's really only that one case
that could go wrong with integer division.
Maybe I'll listen to this later and
[LAUGH] see I was wrong here.
But-
>> [LAUGH] Yeah,
there might be lots of ways that
an integer division could go wrong.
>> [LAUGH]
>> I'm not a mathematician,
I couldn't tell you.
>> Indeed.
So using a maybe, we could model
that division by zero as a nothing.
Or if we got the result and
it wasn't a zero, just that value.
>> And since we only have one kind
of exception case to deal with here,
it's pretty easy to decide.
Yeah, we should probably use
maybe instead of either.
But if we had a lot of cases, wouldn't
we wanna use either rather than maybe?
>> Yeah, typically you'd wanna use either.
When you when you first learn about that,
say from real world Haskell or
some more updated materials,
you'll use either string some value.
And you will use that to essentially
plan out what that string value is.
But that's remarkably similar
to just using exceptions.
>> Yeah, the only difference really is
that we've captured it in the type and
we can work with it as a value.
Either string something isn't super
useful cause the only thing you can do
with that string is maybe print it out.
Or maybe poke at it if you
really wanna try to determine,
does it have zero in there somewhere?
>> Right.
>> Which isn't very satisfying.
But let's say, we had integer division
by zero, which returns a maybe.
We have some more complicated
thing that returns an either.
Isn't it kinda difficult to
smoosh those values together and
work with both of them in one context?
>> How do you mean exactly?
>> So if we have integer division
that returns a maybe integer.
And so, we have to deal with
just some value or nothing.
And then we have some other computation,
I can't think of one off the top my head.
But it returns in either,
let's say, string integer.
And we wanna,
if the maybe is a just integer, and
the either is a right integer,
add those things together.
Don't we have to do a lot of
pattern matching or something?
>> Yeah, we have to do pattern matching.
There's no good way to use any F mapping
or short-circuiting between maybes and
eithers, cause they have
a different number of parameters.
>> Yeah, and they're just different types.
Whereas, if everything was a maybe or
everything was an either, even with
the same error type, then we could
work with those values really easily.
>> Right.
>> And right, I guess a problem
there would be that that error type,
if we were using either,
would start to get really big, right?
>> Yeah, so let's say you replace that
string with your own my custom error type.
You make it a sum type.
You enumerate out all
the things that could go wrong.
Sure, with simple problems
that would not be too bad, and
it may even be the preferred
option in simple cases.
But if you have something relatively
complex or something that
gets very complex on you, even though
you thought it would be simple.
It becomes really laborious and
the value proposition isn't so
much in favor of those huge hierarchies.
>> Yeah, and you look at
the exception hierarchy even for
a language like Haskell, but
for stuff like Ruby or Python,
there's a lot of different
types of errors in there.
And stuffing all those into one error
type, I don't wanna deal with all those
exception cases all the time, cause most
of the time they're not gonna happen.
>> Right, if 90% of your case matches
that you're doing control flow
off of do the exact same thing,
and they print out the error.
What value are you getting specifically
from not using exceptions and
instead using either in
a custom error hierarchy?
>> Yeah, and furthermore,
if I had a, let's say I had
this integer division function.
And it returned either some
big error type integer.
If I wanted to handle the result of that,
really, I know, based on, let's say
the documentation or just my gut, that
the only exception it's actually going
to return is the division by zero one.
But I also have to handle file does exist
error and control c and all this other
stuff, even though I know in my heart
of hearts that it's never gonna happen.
>> Right and that's something
that just doesn't make sense.
And it's something that your
definitely not gonna have time for.
I think that might be a reason that, for
instance, programmers who don't know as
much about Haskell or the benefits if it,
will see it as not a real-world language.
They don't wanna be caught
up in all of those concerns.
But the good news is,
they don't have to be.
>> Yeah exactly,
it is a real-word language.
And it can be used the same
way as every other language,
because you can just throw an exception.
And in a way,
throwing an exception is a lot like you're
in this either some giant error case.
Except that you don't have to explicitly
handle all these cases that you know
aren't gonna happen.
You can only catch or deal with the
exceptions that your documentation says
that thing is gonna throw.
>> Right, and that's okay.
I think we should encourage that.
Because it's also an effective
way of learning Haskell is
only handling the cases that you think
you're gonna have to care about.
And then update and
encode incrementally as you go along.
There's, at first, a feeling of,
I have to learn everything up front.
>> Yeah, you don't need to
learn everything all at once.
You can learn stuff as you go.
We've been talking about integer division.
Obviously, that's a pure operation.
It doesn't need to read from a file or
talk to the network or anything like that.
But we're also talking
about throwing exceptions.
Isn't it weird that exceptions
can be thrown from pure code?
>> It does seem weird,
why does this happen?
Why can't we just depend
on those pure operations?
And the reasoning for that is because
the complications of the real world again.
Maybe our computer runs out of memory,
for instance,
while we're trying two add numbers.
>> Yeah, and what do we do there?
>> Exactly.
>> [LAUGH] So exceptions have to be
able to be thrown from pure code.
Because the real world is gonna butt
in and say, well, I know that's a pure
mathematical function you're dealing with,
but sorry, I ran out of power.
[LAUGH]
>> [LAUGH] Yeah,
maybe we got too close to the Sun.
>> [LAUGH]
>> There was a flare or something.
>> Yeah, something big got
flipped on our hard drive.
What are we gonna do?
But if we can throw
exceptions from pure code,
wouldn't it make sense that we could
catch them from pure code, too?
>> While it would, and
that's where you get into sort of one of
the gotchas in Haskell,
at least at first, only IO is in order.
Pure code doesn't necessarily have
a guarantee of the order, for instance,
addition.
>> Yeah so, what do you mean by addition?
If I'm adding two and three,
it seems pretty clear what's gonna happen.
>> Right, but if we have two errors
that are being added together.
We have error string of one and
error string of two.
We don't necessarily know which one
of those will be evaluated first.
>> Right, so it could be we'd run that and
we'd get one printed out to
our console as the error.
Or we'd get two, and
there's just no way to know ahead
of time which one it's gonna be.
>> Exactly.
>> So since that's the case, we can
only catch errors in IO, is that right?
>> Correct.
>> That means that we can throw
errors anywhere we want, and
then at the top level of our program,
which has to be IO, right?
>> Mm-hm.
>> That's where we handle everything and
do the typical IO stuff of just
log it out and crash the program.
>> Correct, correct.
>> Thanks for being on the show, Cody.
>> It's been great to be here.
I look forward to talking to you soon.
>> To learn more information
about Haskell, go to our website,
haskellweekly.news.
From all of us here at Haskell Weekly and
ITProTV, I'm your host Taylor Fausak.
We'll see you next week.
[MUSIC]