Oh
[Music]
hello and welcome to the ask a weekly
podcast
I'm your host Cody Goodman I'm a senior
engineer and IP pro TV with me today
it's Andres voice one of the engineers
on my team thanks for joining me today
address yep thanks for having me Cody
decided to talk about some fun stuff
with you
cool this show is about Haskell a purely
functional programming language today
we're going to be talking about refined
which is a way of moving a lot of
runtime errors into the type system
there was an interesting blog post
recently and Haskell weekly that
explored using refine to solve a few
common cases of runtime errors such as
division by zero or making sure string
is uppercase things that you'd usually
have to worry about runtime andres what
were your thoughts on it the first thing
that came to mind was it's very
interesting to think of type checking at
the runtime level and one of the things
that first stood out to me was what is
the use high-level seems very useful
after diving into of it a little bit
seems like maybe some of these features
should be implemented more directly into
the compiler level or even just as part
of the actual Haskell language but we
can talk about more about that in a bit
great definitely want to talk more about
that a bit high school is actually
moving towards supporting dependent
typing I hear in the next year or so
we'll probably have something pretty
useful and workable in terms of refined
specifically though and things that we
can use today what do you think are the
the trade-offs and deciding to use
something like that is there a lot of
ceremony involved with using something
like or fun
so runtime errors are expensive but is
it more expensive to implement something
with refine I think the major point that
came to me first is how much extra
coding work do I need to actually do
to be able to use this and I think
that's probably the major downside to
using something like refine we've gotten
to a point where we are trying to fix
we're not really fixed but more solve a
problem that isn't already solved by
using type checking and runtime checking
and all of these things and the first
thing that sticks out is lots of
different conversion functions so
there's a lot of extra boilerplate
required around using refine and using
it in such a way that is helpful to the
code and that's my first take away and
there's some extra stuff in there as
well that is very nice it's just that my
first question is how much extra coding
do I have to do and it's actually a
little bit more than I'm comfortable
with okay and like you mentioned part of
the reason for that is because it's an
external library and not something
integrated with a compiler so exciting
to see if that helps reduce that
ceremony in boilerplate yeah definitely
something that I think would be better
benefited to be directly inside the
language then as a library but it would
be nice to know or at least to be able
to use it in practice to be able to see
if our is it actually a lot of work or
if it's just you know just something
that I get from the representation of it
in the blog post and the documentation
right what do you think as a first
glance what did you first think that
this was gonna do I think that their
find is really interesting I know
there's a lot of ceremony with setting
up things at first I do wonder though if
you go from the approach of rect by
construction and you eventually build up
a lot of these or find helpers if it
much gets route to ceremony once you've
integrated into your normal workflow of
programming you know instead of thinking
in terms of runtime errors if you think
in terms of using refined does this
value refine before I pass it to the
next function if you start thinking that
way and just implementing those things
as the library you can reuse I think
it could be a lot more convenient it's
harder to make that argument though
without having a fleshed out example
yeah I agree I think once this is
actually in use and we're able to see
more of how it is used then we can make
that call it's just one of my major
downsides that I that I can see just
just off the bat is the extra work
required to wrapping it and unwrapping
it better than just doing that type
checking by hand or you know is it
actually worth it right and I think that
when you look at some of the examples by
Nature they're trying to teach something
so they're gonna be a little bit
contrived you have to simplify things to
teach the concept first but it'd be good
if we had somewhere to go from there
layers on the different things that
we've learned you know maybe having
refined check at compile time that a
string is uppercase isn't valuable but
if you're verifying Social Security
numbers
maybe verifying that they are made
interest is it again
eight nine digits then that's something
that could be useful yeah I agree
however I do see verification is usually
user input variables and they're not
available at Build time so I could see
that being a major issue so like let's
say that you have a refined type of
positive number what how will the
compiler know that a user is going to
input two minus one if you don't
actually go through the entire you know
refining it and under finding in the
process which when you refine the to
minus one it's going to throw an error
or however you decide to actually
implement it and that is the same as if
you just did an if statement for example
so I'm it's it's hard to see the
difference of actually type checking in
code and type checking in the types
itself right that's a great point I
think the special sauce so to speak lies
in that it's not really about verifying
that value it is in the exhaustive nough
stucking
that we get by defining that and how it
forces programmers if you are warning or
if you are throwing an error on
exhaustive those checks it forces the
programmers to handle that case upfront
whereas you could have missed that case
in a dynamic language yeah I agree
and that's obviously where we see the
benefits of this library the question I
had was is it worth it do we want to add
all this extra complexity just to be
more safe for the developer to write
this code and the upsize I think are
still not better than the downsides okay
what do you think about the possibility
of senior engineers using refines to
write out the types and stub out
implementations and then having the rest
of the engineers implementing the
functionality for those things if most
of these types are going to be used in a
compilation manner so you know we are
mainly using haskó in a web environment
so most of our types that need type
checking are going to be user input and
I think that's where it falls short if
it is going to be used in such a way
that this type checking is going to help
in the code writing then I think that's
a good thing so refine is a great
library to make sure that your types
that are you know more dynamic than
other types such as numbers lists things
like that stay inside the range they're
supposed to be then refine is a great
library for that regardless whether it's
a senior engineer doing the structuring
or it's a junior one I I don't see a
difference in that scenario okay
did you see if it was possible in the
docs I'm scrolling through them now to
add refined values you know to have
composite refined values
you mean like doing for example one plus
one on Iran value sort of I mean like
saying that to refine this this value
needs to both be uppercase and both be
lengths of 10
mm-hmm I'm actually not sure exactly how
it's used and that's the idea behind me
looking into this library was to see
what my first thoughts first thoughts
are in just as a skimming sort of view
so what is it going to is it going to
appeal enough for me to actually sit
down and start using it I could you know
I could go in there and start writing it
and see if it feels natural if it just
feels very unnatural or just completely
different than what we're used to and um
I can't actually I can't actually answer
the question that you're asking there
bright if it were the case that you can
do that then that's a that's an extra
plus right and actually that that's a
little bit of a warning sign to me and
and something I see too common in high
school libraries is if you can't
communicate the really valuable pieces
like that so if you can't show how to
move past the trivial examples to
something more complicated but also more
useful that's a marketing problem as
well yeah I agree
I had the same thought I said I'm
probably going to have a different
mindset when I actually go in there and
and play around with it but I thought it
was more valuable to have that viewpoint
where I actually haven't used the code
I'm just going by what the author has
told me about it and so far right I'm
not a hundred percent agreed on it and I
think you know having a little more
examples that could help you understand
what the library is meant to fix and how
it fixes it would benefit the adoption
of it right I think it's really valuable
to for you to look at this from you know
the mindset of somebody who's just
thinking about looking at a school you
get by adopting Haskell for some of
these benefits they heard about or maybe
it's a Haskell user who's thinking about
putting more type safety into their code
base you know that's pretty similar to
the mindset they're going to be in in I
think you found a valuable opportunity
for anyone who's writing blog post about
refined or any documentation
and that is to you know give more
examples this is true throughout high
school documentation in general but
especially here you want to motivate not
only the simple cases but the
intermediate and the advanced yes and I
actually have a comment on that one as
well the last part of the blog post
where they show the examples of using
refine inside of a JSON type as a use
case to use refine to make sure that
your JSON parsing matches what you want
it to be that seems like what refined
was meant to do at least in my eyesight
as a server developer for rascal JSON
parsing is pretty much a lot of what we
do so we want to make sure that the
input that comes in is what we want it
to be and I think refine attempted to
use JSON or the Ehsan library to help
type these JSON values a little better
right however that seemed to me like it
was a an afterthought it was okay we
also did this they never went into what
you can do with it or what the code can
do when when you're writing it if it can
make the parsing less verbose or maybe
more concise things like that is what I
want to see when I'm reading a blog post
it was a fine line though right so what
they left is a footnote about JSON there
you would have maybe like to see them
lead with that and then expound upon
that example yeah I mean everyone's
thoughts on what refine is good for is
obviously different I just wanted to get
a little more information up front about
all the different ways you can use
refine
not just simple instance strings and
then oh by the way we also do JSON so
looking at their example for a second it
looks like they find a type called
alcohol user who has a name and an age
they have a refined type to make sure
that there's at least one character in
the string
would you have usually verified
something like that without refine that
is a good question
that would probably depend on how simple
the parsing is most likely I would write
it either directly inside the Ehsan
instance or as a as a conversion of the
type so if I had a type that was an
alcohol user name I would have a string
to alcohol user name that would type
check there and make sure all right you
know you can only convert a string to
that type if it is at least one
character otherwise you fail so this
would the difference that would get us
is a kind of a more declarative way of
listing out how to parse and validate
that JSON right and if it would also
remove them a little bit of the
boilerplate code required to do so right
yeah for building like applicative
syntax for building the data died stuff
like that yeah thanks for being on the
show with me today on dress yeah thank
you very much
it was fun doing this and something that
I actually forgot to mention in the
beginning I have just started doing
Haskell a couple of months ago so most
of this stuff is brand new to me and it
helps a lot to read about these
libraries that people want to implement
just to understand what people's
thoughts are in terms of has goals
strict type system and and where it
needs to be improved in thanks for that
very valuable input and thank you for
listening to the ask a weekly podcast if
you liked what you heard find out more
at our website haskell weekly dot news
also please rate and review us on itunes
it helps a lot thanks again for
listening
we'll see you again next week
you