hello and welcome to the Haskell weekly
podcast as you might have guessed this
show is about Haskell which is a purely
functional programming language
I'm your host Taylor fossick I'm the
lead engineer at IT Pro TV hey Taylor
I'm Cameron
I'm also an engineer here but I'm not
the lead engineer I'm just excited to be
here today I'm glad we get to do the
show again it's been a little while yeah
it has been a little while how you doing
what do we talk about today I'm doing
well and I'm really looking forward to
talking about this post it's titled
evaluation of function calls in Haskell
which you know is just sounds riveting
but very exciting for me and it's by
Laszlo Trotsky hopefully I'm pronouncing
that name right I'm almost sure I'm not
and we're pulling it from issue 168 of
Haskell weekly and I'm still
flabbergasted that we're up into the
hundreds for issue numbers that's a lot
of articles which is really cool you
know that we were able to kind of group
all this stuff together yeah I'm really
excited about that article it sounds
really really fascinating reading over
it I was like it was a little heavy cuz
it talks a lot it gets a lot
nitty-gritty and so I think we should
really start high-level a good place to
start overview right you know I could go
really high-level me like what is the
function I think we can assume everybody
knows yeah that's fair but in this
article he talks a lot about kind of the
gist of it is coming from a chapter in
Haskell programming from first
principles by Christopher Allen and
Julie I'm already naki yeah and this is
something they talk about they're kind
of talking about preventing sharing on
purpose so sharing yeah sharing yeah
that's kind of a weird concept because
it's not something we think about
usually so much so that it's a term a
lot of people probably haven't heard of
I'm sure many people are familiar with
the fact that Haskell is a lazy language
or non-strict and what that means is
that when you write a function call it
doesn't evaluate that immediately it can
wait until you actually need that thing
before it evaluates it and what sharing
means is that if you have the same thing
used in two places maybe it will only
actually be computed once and then it'll
use the result in both of those places
whereas in a strictly
you would be forced to compete at both
time because you're using it twice mmm
okay so that's a real quick introduction
of what sharing is hopefully I didn't
mess anything a new sharing is always
caring so exactly well I think were you
sharing well but this article presents a
way to not share to create a function
that isn't shareable right yeah they
have kind of two motivating examples
right they have this this lambda this
function that takes an argument and
completely ignores it and then returned
something and they use that as an
example of something that doesn't share
it you know keeps all of its toys for
itself and then they have another
example that functionally is exactly the
same like the the end result is the same
except that it allows sharing and it
does that by using the Const helper
function that's in the prelude to not
have a lambda there and that allows GHC
to analyze this a little more thoroughly
and do this sharing optimization mmm
yeah which is really cool which you know
the way they use the constant operator
it's or the function it's not an
operator using the Const function it
makes the function point free right yeah
as opposed to point full right so you're
gonna talk about point free verse point
full a little bit sure point free
programming is definitely something that
is a you know when people look at
Haskell they think about that a lot like
all these really dense expressions with
a lot of function composition and but
really what it boils down to is that
with point free programming you don't
talk about your variable urghhh excuse
me your argument names you don't
actually list them out so what we're
used to in most programming languages is
that when you write a function you have
to explicitly list all of the arguments
that you take in and in high school you
can do that and you know when you write
a lambda or a top-level function
declaration that's the common way to do
things but if your function is just a
series of other functions composed
together and it takes its argument it
can be a little annoying to say you know
f of x equals this function open
parenthesis this other function open
parenthesis this other function x
mmm-hmm and so a point free lets you
kind of rewrite that without mentioning
the ex at all and just say F equals f1
composed with F 2 composed with F 3
right which is really nice for kind of
understandability and looking at it and
seeing that it's just a pipeline of
functions right but specifically with
regards to this blog post point free is
interesting because it changes the
semantics of how it actually runs and
you know we've talked about sharing
already so it should come as no surprise
that it influences sharing right and and
yeah it's it's behind the scenes that
things are different right because if
you look at you know the lambda verse
the Kant's compositionally it doesn't
look that different mm-hmm in high
school but they kind of touch on
something called core right yeah and
core is something that hopefully or
maybe not hopefully that's the wrong way
to put it
generally speaking day to day if you're
writing Haskell code you're not going to
have reason to go look at the core that
it produces mm-hmm but you can think of
core as the first step in the
compilation pipeline and core could be
it isn't this but essentially you can
think of it as a very minimal minified
version of Haskell that doesn't have any
syntactic sugar and because of that it
ends up having a lot of lambdas and a
lot of case statements so it's not as
sweet as happy I mean it's a little sour
maybe you're bitter I'm not sure which
flavor it would be no less it's still
part of a Pascal in the compilation
process right and the reason that core
kind of comes into this discussion is
that when we talk about sharing it's not
apparent when you look at Haskell source
code if something will be shared or not
there are some kind of heuristics that
this blogpost
talks about especially at the end that
tell you when you can expect something
to be shared or not but the only way to
be sure is to look at the core and you
can tell GHC to output the core so that
you can look at it and as I said it
doesn't have any syntactic sugar so it
ends up being really verbose a lot of
the time mm-hmm which means it's not
something you typically want to be
looking at all the time you'd be like
it's like the assembly code of Haskell
in a way it's it's very direct and
straightforward but also very wordy
because of that but but I bring all this
up because the the sharing you know this
expression that does share versus one
that doesn't can become very clear in
core whereas it's not clear at all in
Haskell right because I mean but to me a
something when I was looking at this I
was like what is this and they're like
it's core and I was I was confused
because and it makes sense but
everything is a lambda and in this like
part of the argument in this you know
blog post is like this lambda is not
shareable which looking at in core makes
sense but it still more confusing
because there's so many lambda they're
everywhere
whereas in Haskell it's almost unusual
to see a lambda often it'll be a
top-level declaration or some point free
expression but yeah then when you
compile it down to cord there's lambdas
everywhere you get a lineage and that
could also be a little confusing in the
context of sharing because what they're
saying is at the Haskell level this
lambda prohibits sharing but at the core
level they both turn into lambdas so it
can be a little weird to keep those kind
of the core lambda and Haskell lambda
separate right because it looks like the
core lambda for the function that is
shareable it has record syntax for the
function you know let block and allows
you to reuse it over and over and over
again yeah just kind of neat
yeah and that actually gets it the crux
of this sharing thing because bringing
ourselves back up to the Haskell level
the point free expression the one that
uses Const that won the argument that
you pass into it is shareable because
GHC can look at that and see that it's
function application and it can look at
the argument you're passing in and
saying well you actually end up using
this twice and I don't you know Haskell
is feeling lazy so it says I'm not going
to compute this thing twice I'll just do
it once and use it in both places yeah
and then when you change that into a
lambda it can't do that analysis inside
of the lambda because every time you
call a lambda your expectation as a
programmer is that it's going to run
that function again it's not going to
pull something out
well actually this part is constant so
I'm gonna optimize it away right it's
not that smart
yeah it's fair I'm just reading through
this you know example again which I
encourage all our listeners to go check
out this article yeah and kind of see
these examples we're talking about
because it's a great post and it goes
into a lot of detail right and it's a
little hard to see like you know as I
said we're talking about like yeah it's
actually happening visualize the
functions in your mind's eye right
because we haven't even told you what
the main little function that they're
trying to make shareable is and it's
it's trace which I looked at this and I
was like Taylor what what does this do
so I know it's a little bit of a side
note but I just want to touch on like
what is Trace sure I think it's a great
aside because trace is something that
doesn't come up often but when it does
come up it's super handy the real quick
way to explain it is that trace is like
put sterlin or print or something like
that except that you don't have to be in
IO to do it you can do it from a pure
function or pure expression and it can
be a little tricky because most people
come from strict languages and in a
strict language if you say you know if
you put a log line before you return
some value you generally know about when
that's going to be pronounced because
you can sort of like trace the execution
in your head and say first it'll go here
then it'll go here Haskell is different
because it doesn't do that linear
execution that linear step so if you
throw a trace in you may actually see
the output some other place than you
expected because Haskell waited to
evaluate that thing until some other
time and then by the time that it did
that's when it prints out the trace
right what is actually needed right so
yeah I think I may have got ahead of
myself a little bit but trace is a
function that you give it a string and
some value to return and it will print
out that string when that value is
requested I guess is the best way to put
it so yeah it so it's like a pure way to
print something out evaluate evaluated
and that's why they use it in this blog
post because they want to show you when
things get evaluated and in particular
when something
evaluated twice versus only being
evaluated once and that's really hard to
show in peer code in Haskell because you
it's an effect evaluating something is
essentially in effect right
it should generally happen in I oh yeah
yeah no I think that's cool yeah yeah
they kind of spend some time talking
about the evaluation of sharing
evaluation of not sharing which was cool
to kind of like conceptualize what that
means mm-hmm because you know sometimes
you're working in a function that you
know you get this big data set to really
give back a small set of data you know
so sometimes you have a large heap that
you don't want to keep around so you
don't only want to share it and so maybe
this is a that's a moment you would want
to you know choose not to share
something yeah exactly need it when you
you know call it that one time right
it's easy to look at this and think well
shouldn't we always share things because
there's not much point in computing the
same thing twice because you know you're
gonna get the same result but as you
said if the thing you're producing is
really large and the you know the first
time you use it and the second time you
use it are very far apart in time then
you're holding on to that thing and
aiming for a long time and if it's big
and you had you do a lot of those
computations you may run out of memory
holding on to these values that you
might need later right so you might as
well just throw them away and compute
them akin when you need them
like say deuces yeah see you later data
awesome yeah so obviously we're talking
about this idea of sharing and
evaluating what that is and they spend
some time you know getting into you know
the kind of the timing and the metrics
around sharing mm-hm
in this blog post so I think that's cool
for me though I don't think it's really
worth us it's not worth it for us to
tell it that you know our listeners what
that is again go read the blog post it
gets into excruciating detail at some
points so much like how am I supposed to
talk about this in another language
uh-huh
and one thing I wanted to mention before
we get to the kind of conclusion of this
post
that one thing they don't mention in
this post is that you can do sharing
explicitly in Haskell even if you like
normally rely on the compiler to do it
for you you can always just make a new
let and say let your shared value equal
whatever you want it to be in some
expression where you use it multiple
times and then it's very clear that that
will be shared right and but if you
choose the opposite route and have that
function call in all you know let's say
four spots mm-hmm it's still going to
use the same value let's now evaluate
each time right which is different than
other languages strict languages would
evaluate yes time but if you have some
function that takes four arguments and
you want to pass in the same thing every
time and it's f of X f of X f of X f of
X in a strict language it's going to
call that four times but Haskell will
say well that's the same and you didn't
hide it behind a lambda so I'm gonna
pull that out and only do it once yeah
then we'll be like and you know I won't
use till you need it it's very lazy
which is a good thing for us I've I
didn't know that I was missing that my
life but now you can switching over to
high school and being more involved in
high school it's been really cool to
take advantage of that laziness yeah so
do you feel like you've got a good
understanding of what this blog post was
trying to say could you kind of explain
back to me what sharing means to you now
yeah in total not just in life sharing
but no I think overall sharing is and
Haskell something that increases
performance because obviously we're not
gonna have to evaluate multiple times
but it allows us to evaluate one problem
one time and use that that answer so we
can serve result whatever I want to call
it multiple times and we don't have to
worry about you know it gaining more
memory in the heap because it's just
there it's available you know and so
sometimes we may not want to do that if
we have a large set of data that we only
really want to return a few things from
you may want to not share because it you
know we don't want to get our thumb too
big who woulda thunk it but you know
it's part of the you know people can
write code you know without sharing if
they want to but I feel like Haskell
inherently
leans toward sharing yeah definitely
encourages it which is nice I think it
helps us write more efficient code
without really having to think about it
yeah right like I had no idea I was
sharing this time but well I knew but I
didn't like say oh this is what's
happening yeah yeah and I and I think
point free is something that took a
second to learn and understand but the
fact that you can compose these
functions together and that result is is
shared it's nice to know you know it's
cool that there's this pragmatic benefit
of doing this point free thing which can
sometimes feel like a bit of a chore for
questionable benefit right so now I I do
think haskell is very nice for it you
know this sharing being inherent and I
definitely think you know looking behind
the scenes was really cool kind of
seeing core a little bit and and seeing
that everything is a lambda ya know at
the bottom of the end of the day for the
most part obviously some values as well
things can change but it's just
interesting to see that that's what's
underneath yeah it's cool that Haskell
it's such a large language it has so
many features so many little knobs you
can turn and all of it comes down to
core and so that's really all there is
to understand behind the scenes I wonder
if if Haskell has a six pack you know
maybe one day but ya know I think it was
a really good article I'm gonna
definitely like I said before encourage
our listeners just go to go check it out
yeah go check it out
also go check out Haskell weekly there's
lots of other good stuff in this week's
issue in every issue yeah we did have a
kind of a challenge today and we kept
trying to pick something to talk about
so 168 go check it out yeah this morning
so it's out now like you're right
man that browser yeah something like
that all right
Internet their thing I think that all
about rapid us wrap it up for us thanks
for being on the show with me today cam
of course thanks for having me I had a
good old time me too and thank you dear
listener for listening to the Haskell
weekly podcast if you liked what you
heard you
find out more at our website haskell
weekly news also please go rate and
review us in itunes it helps a lot
haskell weekly is brought to you by IT
pro TV the tech skills development
platform for IT professionals and also
our employer yep that to send your sis
at man's and network admins to WWI t pro
TV for all their learning needs thanks
again for listening we'll see you next
week