hello and welcome to the Haskell weekly
podcast as you might have guessed this
show is about Haskell which is a purely
functional programming language
I'm your host Taylor Foss ak I'm the
lead engineer at IT Pro TV thanks for
joining me today Cody what are we gonna
be talking about we are going to be
following a blog post called inventing
mana it's talking through it cool I feel
like I've been programming high school
for a while so I'm familiar with my nads
but this is more of a beginner's
perspective right right he tries to
actually go through and start using or
he uses JavaScript throughout all of his
examples to make it a little more
approachable since that's kind of the
lingua franca yeah for sure
javascript you know use just a little
bit more than Haskell in industry and
it's nice to see that the concept of
mods can be applied in other languages
it's not something that is specific to a
school right so you mentioned that he he
does this in JavaScript so how does he
start off because I know that Haskell
and JavaScript represent things a lot
differently so it's kind of weird to see
that as a starting point right he just
starts with a normal kind of JavaScript
block of a function of how you would get
a middle name you have a function and
two constants in it a function call and
two constants in it mm-hmm
then he does a sort of pointless looking
transformation where he introduces an
apply function and he uses that apply
function to get the middle name and then
he calls the get user function on that
and then the apply above that as well
then finally calling get ID with all of
those things and the except supplies on
it gotcha
so he has this kind of straightforward
JavaScript function and he transforms it
throwing a seemingly unnecessary amount
of abstraction in there but I have to
assume it'll come in handy later right
he calls it a dense representation it
totally looks pointless and it's like oh
god why would you do this
yeah well hopefully he'll tell us and
it's interesting here that JavaScript
and Haskell again are such different
languages but he manages to make a
function call syntax that ends up
looking pretty close to Haskell so if
you kind of squint your eyes a little
bit you could imagine this javascript is
actually Haskell which is nice for me
yeah great so now that we've thrown all
this extra syntax and boilerplate in
front of ourselves what do we actually
get out of it what's the first thing
that he does with this stuff well the
first thing is he poses the question you
know what if ID
middle name user if any of those things
could be null which super coming right
right right you know anything fails
you'll you'll get a null is especially
in JavaScript mm-hm
he gives a code snippet where the get ID
and get user functions are now checking
for null same forget middle name right
so I'm showing you kind of the more
typical JavaScript way of approaching
this problem right correct and showing
how all of them have to handle the null
values and their possibility returning
it right every single place and then e
pivots and says what if we check for it
automatically right and and how do we
how can we do that automatically does it
use that apply function we had earlier
right so the secret to all of this is in
that you change how these functions are
interpreted instead of changing those
functions themselves that's pretty cool
so earlier you said that apply you know
it takes to re-take so an argument in a
function and then it applies that
function to that argument exactly like
you might expect but what is it doing
now that null has entered the picture
that's actually where it gets to
updating the apply function where if X
is equal to null so give an apply X F if
X is equal to note you just search on
null otherwise you apply F to X that's
pretty cool I like to think of that as
short-circuiting where once you
encounter a null everything stops
happening and you just get null from
that point out
and I see that a lot in JavaScript
functions where you say right at the top
of some handler you say if some
condition is met then return null or
error or whatever it is and that carry
on so this is pretty similar to that in
my mind yeah there's just a lot of times
where within a function you'd have to do
a lot of nested-if checks or something
where you could have used
short-circuiting mm-hmm yeah it cleans
things up a lot I think so now that he's
got this new apply implementation that
supports null checking what does he do
with it he uses it to show how he can
write the middle name function exactly
the same way as he did in the previous
iteration and that's pretty cool right
that the same code can behave
differently depending on if you need to
handle nulls or not right it's starting
to look a little bit like something but
I don't know we don't want to give it a
name yet I don't want to scare anybody
off so after he shows this example of
dealing with null
he kind of pivots and walks back to the
original example and then adds another
I'll call it an effect but another thing
so instead of checking for null he does
something else which is kind of logging
things as they happen right so that if
you were needing to debug this function
because you unexpectedly got a middle
name of you know popcorn and that's that
doesn't make sense then you want to
figure out how you got there so these
this logging would help you figure that
out right right not being able to log in
functions like this if we told people
coming to Haskell like yeah you can't
log that's not gonna work
you you need to be practical you got a
debug stuff and so how do they approach
logging given that they're trying to
implement these things as quote unquote
pure functions so the first thing you do
is functional languages avoid global
variables to keep track of all those
messages mmm so the first pass that that
is modifying utility functions to handle
erase and when you say arrays what do
you mean what's in those arrays the
result as well as the blog message
right so you get back an array where the
first thing in is the answer and
everything else is kind of stuff that
happened along the way that you might be
interested in you might throw away right
the trouble is that then your functions
have to know how to handle that yeah
every single function you call would
need to like D structure or lookup or
whatever but fortunately we have a
function that we've thrown in our own
way here right that we can change yet
again to do what need here right that
that pointless seeming function from at
first apply which made things look all
horrible now like oh we can just go back
and modify this now 2d structure that
and and show us what the logs the
results up
yeah previously we were using the supply
function to check for null but now we're
saying grab that first thing out of it
and append all you know can cat together
all the other stuff so we're
accumulating these log messages as we go
through but still producing the result
that we wanted in the first place yeah
and that's that's really cool to be able
to just modify that apply again to
handle all our needs
exactly pretty nice again you end up
with the same shape at the top level it
still looks exactly the same but
underneath the covers the implementing
the implementation details are kind of
switched out from underneath you so
instead of handling Knolls now we're
doing logging and that's that does
that's why this blog post does a really
good job of motivating why the word
we're not saying as useful maybe at this
point we can start talking about it is
in the title after all so oh yeah so far
these have been two examples of
Manette's and this is showing you that
yeah they are useful for real-life
situations that you're gonna come across
as you're writing programs it's not just
you know advanced math ivory tower stuff
for sure there's a lot of it a lot of
real-world advantages that you get from
on ads and these were good examples
already mm-hm and they go on to give a
few more so so let's kind of get through
those they talk about global environment
which when I read that makes me shudder
a little bit because I don't like global
environments I like things to be as
local as possible but I think they don't
really mean global they mean some
else don't they it's kind of like scoped
to the function or something like that
right they mean for a given function you
can provide an environment that can be
modified within that scope right so the
way that I like to think about this and
I think this actually came up in our
code base recently here at work where we
had a series of functions that all
needed some config and we were passing
that config from functionary to function
B B to C C to D and that's a lot of
boilerplate because you have to thread
that thing all the way through and I
think we we came out of that not having
to thread it through can you tell us how
we got there right so we started using a
mana transformer which the important
thing is that it had a reader mana in it
mm-hmm
Damona is what that just means that you
can simply use a function called ask and
whatever you initiated that reader
bonad with whatever value it was
initiated with you'll get that back in
our case it was convicted yeah so our we
had all these functions that were
operating in this maaan ad and instead
of passing an argument through to
everything in the single place where we
needed it all we had to do was ask for
it and it was suddenly available right
actually at one point we we had both the
new mana and we were still passing it
thick-headed twice you know just to make
sure get it from one place get her from
the other make sure they're the same and
then move on right so in in this blog
post he shows this global environment
example and kind of walks you through
the the reader mine ad is what it would
be an asshole and you know does it
provides motivation for this example
that we just ran into passing all these
arguments is annoying and if you can put
it in your context and then escort when
you need it
it's pretty nice and once again as you
might be able to guess you change apply
and your actual business logic ends up
looking the same and all the stuff
underneath the covers kind of changes
out from underneath you which sounds
scary but promise
as long as you follow a few rules
exactly so they're important rules say
that we call them laws but I don't think
you get arrested if you don't follow
them it's just very a very frowned upon
so now that we've gone through dealing
with nulls accumulating a bunch of state
in this case logs as we go through stuff
and having a kind of read-only
environment that's available to our
functions we land on the final example
which is state which is something that
gets passed to every function but also
can be updated along the way can you
tell us a little more about this example
and kind of how it differs from the
previous ones it's really similar like
you're saying I think to the reader mana
the only difference is that that initial
state that was passed in you can update
it then you can you can get it again do
whatever you want with it
mm-hm and I think the example they use
as kind of motivation has to deal with
random numbers because if you want to
generate a bunch of random numbers in a
pure fashion without reading from like
/dev view random or something like that
typically you're going to need a random
number of seed and those are
deterministic so if you give something
the same seed you get back the same
answer which works fine if you only need
one random number you could throw that
in your reader context and pull out the
seed and generate your random number but
if you want to generate two you would
generate the same number both times
because you couldn't change that reader
context so you need something like the
state where you can ask for it or get it
and then do whatever operation you want
with and then put something back into
the state change it
I actually remember I remember having a
bug with random numbers before where I
might have been using a reader monitor
just threading that same seed through
and after I figured it out it just
reminded me at the xkcd comic it's like
turn 42 yeah
guaranteed random number we rolled some
dice and figured out this is a very
random number we're just gonna keep
giving it to you yeah so we don't want
to implement random number generators
like that and you don't have to
the Mount add abstraction is powerful
enough to give you this ability to
consistently take something in into your
environment and use it and modify it and
then return that back out along with
your answer so once again we end up with
changing the apply function and using
the same business logic over and over
and over again so that gets us through
all of the motivating examples that this
guy gave for Mon ads and he managed to
make it through this post without using
my nads we didn't quite you know I think
we made it halfway through but this is
something that happens a lot in the
Haskell community right
beginners kind of finally grokking Mon
ads have you seen this come up before
oh yeah a ton I personally spread right
maskel just by making functions with you
know five ten arguments yeah to pass the
state through and then I finally got I
know I didn't up I was like I'm gonna
learn what bonnets are about I came
across a billion tutorials monitor
burritos what else are they oh there are
all kinds of things
I see singing there straws but I think
that's lenses are straws monitor
burritos they're boxes they're thinners
I don't know any number of things that's
why I really like tutorials like this
which focus on some real examples
because you're not gonna you're not
gonna get very far with metaphors as
much as you will with using these things
and seeing why those laws that are
seemingly pointless why the supply of
functions there seemed pointless help
you yeah I agree I much prefer seeing a
motivating example rather than here's
the type signature and here's the laws
and it's important and good luck walking
through stuff like this really helps me
or would have helped me when I was
learning Haskell see why do I care about
this what do I get out of it you know
exactly and like you I've seen so many
of these tutorials through the years
that it feels a little bit like a rite
of passage for new Haskell there's like
yeah you got to learn what my nads are
and then you got to write the blog post
that says you look
they are and that's exactly what's
happened yeah somehow I think neither
you nor I have written this blog post
but maybe that just means we haven't
truly understood my Nancy yet well I
hope we're making a podcast about yeah
does this count as a blog post probably
anyway I think that about wraps it up
for us today thanks for being with me on
the show today Cody
it was a lot of fun it's always good and
you have good having you on here and
thank you for listening to the haskell
weekly podcast if you liked what you
heard please find out more at our
website haskell weekly dot news and if
you did like our show again please go
rate and review us on iTunes it helps a
lot
Haskell weekly is brought to you every
week by IT pro TV the tech skills
development platform for IT
professionals who also happens to be our
employer so please send your sis admins
and network admins 2ww IT pro TV for all
their learning needs and they can let
you know what they think of the people
who develop it which is us so thanks
again Cody and we'll see y'all next week
you