[MUSIC]
Hi, welcome to the Haskell weekly podcast.
This show is about Haskell,
a purely functional programming language.
I'm your host, Cameron Gera, and
with me today we have our wizard expert
here at ITProTV for Haskell,
Taylor How are you doing Taylor?
>> I'm doing well Cam.
How are you?
I'm doing pretty good.
I'm pretty excited about today.
>> Me too.
I would be more excited if I knew,
what are we talking about?
>> Well,
I was just gonna let you figure that out.
>> [LAUGH]
>> But I will bring it up because
I think a very important subject in
the Haskell world is stack vs ball.
So I just wanna talk about kind
of stack a little bit more, and
maybe some of the build tools and
how that's helpful for us.
I was reading an article about kind of
how stack can give you this project
structure out of the box, and
how that's helpful for keeping all
Haskell projects in the same format.
>> We use Stack here at ITProTV
to manage our Haskell projects.
We only have one big project, and
it's got a lot of smaller
projects tucked inside of it.
And Stack does a great job of
keeping those things all in sync,
along with all
the dependencies that we use.
Cabal is kind of the other
contender in this area and
we don't have any experience as
a team here using Cabal directly.
But Zach uses Cabal for a lot of things
behind the scenes and in a lot of ways you
could think of it as a smooth veneer on
top of the foundation that Cabal provides.
>> So
it's like a shiny little outer coating.
>> [LAUGH] Exactly.
>> Underneath is the real meat of it,
which is Cabal.
>> Yeah, I don't know why you have
a shiny coating on top of your meat,
but whatever floats your boat.
>> [LAUGH]
>> I was gonna go with like a piece of
candy.
Kinda like the M&M,
like the shiny green outer and
then Cabal is like the chocolate center.
>> That's delicious.
>> The chocolate center of
Haskell project development.
[LAUGH]
>> Yeah, well, I've heard a lot of things,
being relatively new to Haskell.
Stack made it kind of easy to understand,
this is how I make something new.
I've worked with Stack, trying to make
a Hakyll blog and other stuff like that.
And it seems to be fairly useful, when I'm
trying to figure out what I need to use,
what dependencies I have,
I just kinda tell it hey, install this.
Then it's there.
There's no jumping through any hoops.
And why is that?
I know we have this thing called Stackage.
Kinda how does that help us?
So Stackage is a set of Haskell packages
that are known to all work together.
So you mentioned Hakyll.
Hakyll as part of its, one of Hakyll's
dependencies is Pan Doc which is a thing
that lets you convert document
formats from one to the other.
So if you have a markdown file and
you want to produce HTML,
which is extremely common
when writing a blog.
Pan Doc is a tool that will let you do
that and about a thousand other things.
Pan Doc requires a lot of dependencies and
it can be hard to find versions of all
of those things that work well together.
So if you want to start a blog and
you want to use Hakyll to produce it,
it can be challenging to find all
the dependencies you need and
all the versions of those
dependencies that all work togethe.
Stackage has done all that work for you.
So when you tell stack hey install
Hakyll stack already knows,
yeah, I can install these dependencies
together and they're just going to work.
That's in comparison to something like
Cabal, at least older versions of Cabal.
I don't know how things
have changed recently.
But Cabal works by resolving dependencies.
So each dependency has a version
constraint that says I work with
this broad range of packages.
And Cabal tries to pick a specific
version of each one that
the package claims it will work with.
This is basically working
on the honor system.
So there's no guarantee that package
A will actually work with package B even
though it says it will.
With Stackage that work
is done ahead of time and
the maintainers are notified when
something doesn't actually work.
But with Cabal, it's possible to get into
a situation where you try to install
something that says it should work and
it doesn't.
And you're left trying to
figure out what went wrong.
And this is kind of historically,
in the Haskell community,
called Cabal hell and this is
something that stack helps you avoid.
>> I see, yeah, so
having a background in JavaScript
to a little extent,
we use some forms of NPM.
There was kind of this hell of you have
this one package you're specifying but
it's installed a newer version
of this other package.
And you have all this issue they've got
package lock now on a lot of stuff.
And I haven't necessarily spent enough
time in JavaScript lately to really
understand or appreciate that stuff,
because we've been working in Haskell.
In Haskell, I've had stack, so
I haven't had to experience Cabal hell,
but I have heard fun stories.
And that's nothing against, well,
it's just part of how they do things.
And I appreciate that stack
allowed us to kind of not
have to worry about that kind of coming
into Haskell and being a beginner, right.
Like stack I feel like makes
the beginner's life a lot simpler.
>> I definitely agree with that.
It's one less thing to worry about when
you're getting started with Haskell.
You don't have to wonder will
these packages build together.
You know that they will.
It's also nice, you mentioned NPM.
One of the things that NPM does that
Haskell can't really do is that if you
have two packages that depend on
different versions of some sub package,
they can just install both
versions of that sub package.
And say sure, whatever,
package A will get this one version,
package B will get this other version.
In Haskell you can't do that because
all of your packages have to
agree with each other about every
dependency that they're using.
So you can't say Hackyll gonna use
version one of text and pan doc is going
to use version two and won't work
because the types won't line up.
It's also worth mentioning
that another thing Stack does,
that NPM also does,
is that it kinda quarantines
your local project's dependencies
from your global installation.
So anyone who's worked with
a JavaScript project is familiar with
the node modules folder.
>> Ouch.
>> Which is a giant folder with
hundreds of folders in there, one for
each dependency.
Do we have an ouch noise.
So known models is a giant folder with
hundreds of dependencies in there and
it's separate from your kind
of global installation.
And a lot of times, people will
install things globally like Bower, or
ESLint, some kind of tool that's just
convenient to have on the command line.
In the old days with Cabal, it installed
most of your Haskell packages globally.
So if you were working on two projects and
they needed different versions
of a dependency, too bad,
you can't really do that.
Eventually they introduced
this concept of a sand box,
which is a lot like the node
modules thing, the folder.
But the sand box augmented
your global packages,
it was in addition to
all of the global stuff.
So if you accidentally
installed some global package
that wasn't the one you wanted in
your project, again, you're stuck.
You have to go remove
that global package and
install it locally instead
>> That thing is rough,
because then that could cause mismatches
in people's local environments to
what's happening in production, too.
I feel like that's super dangerous.
>> Very dangerous and annoying.
>> Right, and
I feel like we've kinda circumvented
that because we dockerize things.
So in our development locally,
we dockerize everything.
So all of our packages,
if they were installed globally even
would be books on our container
that we're working in.
So we hopefully would be able
to avoid that said issue.
>> Exactly, I don't think we would have
run into this particular problem, even if
we were using Cabal instead of Stack,
because we're inside a Docker container.
Like you said, a global package inside
a Docker container is still kind of local
to that Docker container.
>> Right.
>> Newer versions of Cabal have added this
new way of building stuff, where it
completely ignores your global package
database, and only uses one
that's sandboxed for the project.
They call this NYX-style local builds.
Which is taking a page out of the NYX
handbook, which does everything for
your entire system like this.
Cabal focuses just on Haskell packages.
>> Interesting, yeah, our co-worker Cody,
he told me that I should make a Nix joke,
so I'm glad you brought
that into the picture.
>> Can we nix that NYX joke?
>> No, I can't nix it now.
I have to, well,
let's just move on, anyways.
>> [LAUGH]
>> I tried,
I'm not as funny as some of our
fellow peers here at ITProTV.
But I do what I can,
to try and stay with it.
Stack in Cabal kind of heard,
kind of the underlying side of Cabal,
which has been nice to kind of understand
more of like, what happened and
why global dependencies and stuff like
that were kind of causing issues.
If you're going to give advice to
anyone kinda starting in Haskell,
whether they have programming
experience or not.
What would be the best thing about
Stack for them to look into?
I dropped a bomb on you, now-
>> It's hard for me to pick one thing.
I feel like there are at least two and
the first one is that stack is going to
manage your compiler installation
along with all of your dependencies.
So Cabal doesn't install GHC for you.
You have to do that yourself and
then you can point Cabal at
the GHC that you want to use.
>> What's the nicety?
This is really cool that
Stack did this for me.
>> Right, it's something that's gonna be
invisible in that you're not going to
end up in a situation where you're stuck
because some dependencies don't work out.
And that's a hard thing to sell too hard
on because it's the lack of a problem.
But the problem itself is really
annoying and very difficult for
a beginner to solve.
Because they don't
really have the tools or
the expertise to figure out what happened,
and how to fix it.
And Stack, for the most part,
just sidesteps the whole thing.
Occasionally, you get into a situation
where you want a package that isn't on
Stackage.
And that's when things get complicated,
from the Stack side.
With Cabal, pretty much any package,
well really any package is gonna be
installable with Cabal eventually.
Maybe you need to work out
some dependencies but-
>> Anything on hackage pretty much you
could find use.
>> Exactly, mm hm.
And that's also true with Stack,
but if something isn't on Stackage,
then you don't get that nicety of
it just working automatically.
It may work really well without any extra
work, but it might not work at all.
And then you have to figure that out and
that can be hard for a beginner to do.
>> Got you, so we have a little
bit of that in our code base
based on our latest resolver that we have.
We don't have some of our dependencies,
so we had to bring in-
>> Yeah, like Happstack.
>> Happstack, right.
And so that was kind of a,
it kinda uses these extra dependencies and
text kinda thing in the stack.yaml.
And for a beginner, what would be
just something to be aware of
when trying to figure out,
what do I do with this extra dependency,
what does that look like?
>> I think that Stack's documentation
does a good job of explaining
what these extra dependencies are,
why you might need them, and
how to put them into your stack.yaml file.
Also, when you make a new project with
Stack, it includes a Stack.yaml file that
has a bunch of comments in it that say,
if you need to include an extra depth,
this is what it would look like,
and this is why you might need it.
There's also a lot of good
blog posts on this topic.
This is something that a lot of people
have run into where they're working with
Stack and they're enjoying it and then
they run into a package that they need to
install that's not on Stackage and
they tell you how to do that.
So I would say turn to Google.
>> Good ol Google, that's an engineer and
developer's best friend.
>> Sure is.
>> Stack Overflow,
any blog posting platform is great.
They do a really good job.
I know for me that's been something
that's really really been helpful.
It's a big topic.
Volver stack in the Haskell world.
We want everyone to know we love both.
We just use Stack so
we're more familiar with it.
Why do you think necessarily
this is such a hot topic?
>> Me personally I don't feel too
strongly one way or the other and we've
been posing this as a Cabal versus Stack-
>> Discussion.
>> Flame war,
discussion that we're hinting at here,
but really there are other
entrants in this battle.
There's NYX which we've
mentioned because Cabal kind of
borrowed this concept of
NYX style local builds.
But you could use NYX to build Haskell
packages and a lot of people do.
You can also use some more Niche tools,
I know that there's one called Mafia.
You could also use GHC directly,
which works great.
If you don't have a lot
of dependencies GHC has
a -- make flag that makes it behave
more like a build tool than a compiler.
And I'm sure there are many other
build tools that I'm not aware of,
or that I'm failing to mention right now.
That being said, Stack and
Cabal are kinda the big players.
And I think Stack has done a great
job of making Haskell development
accessible to a wider audience,
which was its goal from the get go.
In a previous job I was very
gung ho about using Haskell, but
I worked on a team that
primarily worked with Ruby code.
And I didn't feel comfortable
suggesting to them that we use Cabal
as our build tool.
Because I ran into so many of its
sharp edges with failing to install
a dependency, or polluting the global
package database, any of those things.
When Stack came out I thought,
you know what,
I would be okay subjecting
the rest of the team to this tool.
>> Right.
>> Cuz it generally works pretty well.
As to why it's such a contentious
topic in the community,
I think that a lot of people have
invested time into learning Cabal and
its quirks and mastering i.
And when there's a new tool that doesn't
require all of that expertise, it can
make you feel like you either you've
wasted some of your time or that people
need to learn the same things that you
learned in order to get onto your level.
And so this kind of undercutting their
expertise However, I'm not a psychologist.
I couldn't tell you.
I'm sure there are many more reasons why.
>> Well, I appreciate your time, too.
I appreciate you being able to take the
time to just talk to us about Atack and
about Cabal and hear some of
the quirks of both even and how we can,
use that in our day to day even
before expert or we are beginning.
Because there's some niceties with Stack
and if you use Cabal that's great and
there's nothing no hard feelings.
>> Yeah.
>> All right, thanks for
being with us Taylor and thank you all for
listening to the Haskell weekly podcasts.
This has been episode five and
I've been your host Cameron Gera.
If you liked our show find out more
at our website haskellweekly.news.
Thanks again for listening and
see you next week.
[MUSIC]