>> Hello and welcome to the Haskell Weekly
podcast.
I'm your host Taylor Fausak. I'm the
lead engineer at ITProTV. And with me
today is Cameron Gera,
one of the engineers on my team. Thanks
for joining me, Cam!
>> Thanks for having me,
Taylor! It's been a little bit.
>> Yeah it's been
a little bit. We're happy to have you
back on the podcast.
>> Appreciate that.
>> So
today we are going to be talking about
Haskell of course, but more specifically
refactoring and types. What's the
article we're gonna be covering, Cam?
>> Yeah
so it's it's an article by Tom Ellis.
It's called "Good Design and Type Safety
in Yahtzee" which is
actually an article looking at another
article, improving some code, and doing
some refactoring, which is really,
really informational. So I'm really
excited about today.
>> Me too! Because this
like you mentioned is kind of a response
article to another one where somebody
had some code that they'd written and
they slapped some types on it and we're
complaining that it kind of made things
harder to read and didn't give them too
much type safety.
>> Right yeah. The words
they used were "unreadable" and
"unmaintainable",
which I get. Looking at the code, it
was pretty hard to read. And I was
like, there has to be a better way.
You know there's all kinds of stuff and
I think we're going to talk about the
various steps that Tom took to kind of
say hey like type type safety isn't
something you just throw on it's
something that you design with you
know when you have good design you know
type safety is just there and it allows
you to really feel confident about the
code you're writing
>> exactly so instead
of taking some piece of code and
throwing types on it you kind of develop
the types and the design in lockstep one
influences the other okay
>> which i
think was cool yeah because yeah there's
a quote he said he you know I don't
think I'm gonna quote it exactly but you
know he talks about building type safety
struck type safe structures and
combinators relevant to the domain and
then that's what we use with the
implementation
>> right yeah so this is
going to be a little interesting to talk
about because obviously we're talking
about a piece of code and it's really
hard to communicate code over voice
>> right but you know
think about the game of Yahtzee that's
what we're talking about so the game of
Yahtzee you have five dice you roll them
you have it believe tends to be three
rolls and you can you know it's a dice
so it's one to six
and yeah so what we're doing I
gotta do is understand what the roles
are I guess that's that's the name of it
it's called all roles as the function
we're gonna kind of be evaluating
>> yeah
so the the original function by Mark
Dominus the blog post he wrote about it
it has some role presumably from a game
of Yahtzee and it is given some choices
like reroll that die keep that one and
then figure out what the next results
gonna be
so that's the that's the game plan here
and as Cam mentioned this kind of starts
off as something that the the
quote-unquote not type safe version is
kind of understandable but a little
dense and then the quote-unquote type
safe version is just completely
impenetrable because there's so many
like wrapping unwrapping things going on
>> right yeah I mean the type safety
doesn't you know doesn't just get
slapped on like we said earlier so I'm
really excited to kind of dive dive in
>> so let's do that let's dive right in and
get started here so we start with the
original implementation just kind of
repeated in full
and from a high level what we're doing
is applying a bunch of very small
refactorings to this piece of code
>> an
iterative basis
>> yeah iteratively so at
each step we don't need to know too much
if anything about what the original code
is doing we're just saying I recognize
this pattern as something that could use
a little more type safety so let's
measure it in that direction
>> Right and
and as somebody who's been in Haskell
for a year now like some of these
suggestions that we're going to talk
about are now relevant but starting out
I would have been very like wait what
you can do that um so you know if you're
a beginner like this is something you
kind of learn with time and you know
this article could be a good help for
you to understand and see you know not
understood what the code is doing but
the patterns and which its implementing
and being able to pull it out
you know the common you know best
practices of Haskell
>> Right um yeah it's
kind of like a quick tour of some kind
of design patterns that you might use in
Haskell for refactoring and I've also
heard people describe this as a
intermediate level Haskell post where
there's a lot of the kind of beginner
stuff of like here's a monad here's how
to do addition you know real rudimentary
things right and then there's all the
super advanced you know type level
shenanigans stuff and this one's right
in the middle of like actual work a day
just how do you make software better
>> right yeah which I'm a fan of because
you know as a day-to-day engineer this
is stuff you use yeah like we're not
designing this giant you know data
parser that needs to be perfect but
we're also not you know just making a
simple API they say hey I'm here you
know like there's nothing so we're in
the middle and this is what kind of you
plays into it so I think we should jump
right in
you know the first thing he notices and
this is something we do more in
intermediate steps but is the use of
undefined so that means there's a case
that we aren't accounting for there's
something like that's the case we don't
expect to get to because you hit that
undefined and runtime and you're blowing
up
>> Right now and you're blowing up with
a really useless error message message
that just says undefined happened
somewhere good luck figuring it out
peace yeah so how do they improve the
situation
>> Right so he says you know all
right we we have this undefined that's a
red flag let's throw a useful air that's
what he does first he says all right
we're gonna you know call the air
function with a string that says you hit
this location and there you know choices
has to be the same length as the Val's
or values that you're working in it's
>> alright
so after this change if you do run into
that case if something went wrong you
now have a breadcrumb to go look for and
say okay well I can track things down a
little bit
>> Yeah and the other thing he
does is you know to kind of set himself
up well for successes he avoids you know
catch-all patterns right like because I
catch all you know there's a chance
you're missing something there's some
invariant that you don't know about
because you're like anything happens
here you know we're gonna fail
>> yes so if your pattern matching on like
the empty list and then your padding
matching pattern matching on the list
having exactly one element and then like
a catch-all you could think oh well the
catch-all is for when there's three or
more elements but really you're missing
the case where there's exactly two and
it's you know ghe is not gonna warn you
about that because you're explicitly
handling quote-unquote every case with
that catch-all but it may not be working
the way you expect
>> Right so you know he
he kind of you know that's not the next
step after you know throwing the areas
oh hey like let's not use catch all the
uses catch-all internally but he D
structures that wasn't working right and
you know with the warn all which or warned
everything or all the high school you
know compiler warnings he kind of turns
on he's able to find that there's
another invariant in there
>> Yeah so he
keeps strengthening the invariant or
finding more right where he's like okay
previously we just had one case here but
really there were two cases kind of
hiding behind this thing mm-hmm
>> yeah and I've everything down the road
that's something for like for me like as
a intermediate you know mid-level high
school developer is like understanding
that catch-all aren't always the best
solution and to maybe try to put out
every case and see if there's something
that you know you can bubble up to the
type system that would have value not to
have to even care about these invariant
cases right which is kind of what he's
doing here which is really really for me
informational and I would recommend
anybody to read this article because I
felt like I was like oh okay I I don't
have to just use a catch-all because
it's you know what I know to do mm-hm I
can write out each case and understand
and see where the logic air or the
invariant could live and maybe bubble
that up to the type system like I said
>> yeah and even though we're talking about
kind of removing catch-all cases here as
a refactoring step sometimes it can be
useful to still use them and especially
if you have a bunch of them and you
write them all out all excuse me you
write all of them out explicitly mm-hmm
you may see like oh these I have twenty
cases here and nineteen of them are the
same I'll go
replace those with a catch all right
that's done that legwork to say well I
looked at all the cases
>> Right you're
understanding the code and what you're
writing and that's you know part of
refactoring like yes there's things you
can do in high school that you don't
have to fully understand what the code
is doing to refactor but if you want to
understand the code you want to make it
a useful refactor it tends to be better
to take the extra step yeah which i
think is really cool
and I think you know we can all kind of
glean that and you know some information
from that process
>> So moving on from the
catch-all patterns
this next refactoring I feel like is a
really big one and mm-hmm the key thing
that it does here that I see is that
they recognize a function is doing two
things and they pull them out into two
functions
>> Yeah I don't think you know a
function doing multiple things is always
the clearest choice mm-hmm
>> Especially
for pure functions you know it's very
common for some effectual function to do
a lot of stuff like write you know it's
stitching a bunch of other things to get
>> right right right but pure functions
yeah there's no reason to do that mm-hmm
>> and as we'll see later on it can often
really clarify things to have two very
tiny functions that do separate things
and then you combine them into one top
level function that does everything
>> right yeah definitely makes refactoring
easy
so yeah this function he pulls out is
great because it kind of checks for the
unvarying it says I want to pull that
logic out and you know if I find this
invariant I'll throw my air mm-hmm if
not then I'll just return the values
that you know the function the function
I extracted from expects
right and then it also clears up the the
main function that we were using yeah oh
hey we just have a you know in this case
it's a maybe you know okay we just have
a case that says is you know is it just
or is it nothing and the air is handled
within the separate function
>> Yeah it
kind of quarantine those invariant
checks into one function so that outside
of there you can generally just say okay
I'm assuming those have been handled
which is really nice and as you
mentioned it also cleans up reading that
top level function that calls the other
one because you don't have to when
you're reading it you don't have
worried about the logic there you can
say okay that other function handles it
I can read that if I'm interested but
when I'm here I just have to pattern
match on that maybe
>> Right yeah image
yeah I think that's something we as an
engineering team have gotten better at
is understanding like okay like we don't
have to do everything in this one pure
function we should break it out make
make it smaller make it easier to
understand right and kind of keep keep
bite size pieces rather than a whole sub
or something
>> You know yeah it's almost
never a bad idea sometimes you can go
crazy and have way too many small
functions right but I think it's usually
pretty obvious when that when that
happens especially when you're trying to
read through one function you have to
keep bouncing around other definitions
makes our I don't you come out
>> Cool well
we're gonna move on go to the next one
the next one is a little bit trickier
because you have to think through the
design process and kind of have a better
understanding of what your code is doing
so this is you know kind of that next
step
and it's you know kind of finding that a
value is unused so when you're looking
at a function especially a recursive
function and you see a value that
doesn't end up being in the final result
that kind of stir your stomach and kind
of feel like something's wrong and for
us I'm sure there's lots of pause spots
in our code where we're like yeah we
don't need this but you know having
senior engineers like you and Cody
allows us to think through those things
and see them and identify them faster so
with time you get better at that but you
know Tom here is like hey like there's
this value we're kind of using and at
the end of the day we don't ever display
it or return it it's just to keep track
of something in a recursive function
mm-hmm
and so he does a lot he'll he kind of
says hey let's take some time and think
about why we're returning this value and
he kind of puts in like a test like hey
if we hit this value this what we expect
to be here then we should throw an error
because we actually don't expect to be
here like it's not a final value
>> Right
and in a way this is another type of
invariant and the invariant is we're not
using this value but I think it's also
to point out here that we're talking
about refactoring and using type systems
but really in this case you're relying
on the test suite because he's saying I
looked at this value and I don't think
it's used so I'm gonna plug in an error
there and then rerun my tests and see
that that error doesn't get thrown so
yeah that values not used right so a lot
of people think that you have to kind of
use types or use tests but really you
use both right both help
>> Right and
that's kind of his whole scheme yeah
point in this article was like it's not
one or the other it's together right
it's a symbiotic relationship which i
think is cool and so he kind of
indicates okay this is unused and then
he kind of takes it you know a step to
say oh wait like we're kind of having
these different types that are you know
they don't need to be bound together
they're not you know something that
relies on one another so he as a tuple
here that he's like I don't feel like
this types actually used so he kind of
gets rid of the type alias and says okay
like let's just name it and let's see
and take some steps and see if we can
get these to be independent right
they're you know independent arguments
and then if those arguments don't get
used we can factor them out a little bit
better
>> Right because it's a lot easier
to get rid of one argument than it is to
get rid of half of a tuple right mmm
half a tuple One Bowl oh one pool okay
just parens mm-hmm
>> So yeah he kind of
takes a couple steps to rearrange some
stuff
>> Yeah and I think it's interesting
the way that he does this because he
recognizes that these two values that
are in a tuple together probably
shouldn't be together but he doesn't
immediately delete one of them
he kind of prized them apart and then
makes it easier for himself to delete
that single argument later on and I
really like that because he identifies
the refactoring that he wants to do of
getting rid of this member of the tuple
and then he does like a intermediate
refactoring that makes that thing he
wants to do later a lot easier so that
instead of getting rid of one thing out
of a tuple he can get rid of an ax
an argument to a function which as we
said is a little easier to manage
>> Mm-hmm
yep
and I feel like yeah I think like error
message is associated with that
substance easier to rather than like oh
wait we have a to poot yeah yeah I just
think it's all around a better choice
you know and if if there are two
arguments that are very closely tied
like yeah a tuple is understandable he
kind of gets back to that at some point
yeah but he says like hey like let's
let's figure out where the real
connection is here
>> Right he's not saying
that the tuple is the wrong data
structure he's saying it doesn't look
right right now right here
so let's pry it apart
>> Right so I think
that's good and I think you know for you
know mark and as he wrote that you'll
deal role dimension yeah the original
authors like you know he's still
learning he's kind of figuring it out
he's you know saying hey like this tuple
seems like the right moving and that is
as software engineers that's art that's
what happens that's our job we say oh
this works we get it functional we make
it work we'll make it you know do what
we expect it to and then you know we can
come back and refactor so I think this
is very information was like you know it
worked it's a good it's an okay solution
but you can kind of look at it and say
oh let's let's bring it do something
better
>> Yeah and in case in point the
refactoring here isn't let's slap some
types on it on the arguments after the
fact it's okay let's take that function
and really break it down step by step
and find the better ways to do those
things
>> Yeah so I think that's cool
and as he rearranges arguments he
actually put something back into a tuple
mm-hmm that he's passing to this that
helper function we created earlier that
pure invariant function right and he's
you know he made it a tuple and then he
realized oh we passed that tuple to this
function we deconstruct it but we don't
really need to deconstruct it yeah
because we're just passing it to a
function and that function returns a
value that we can you know deconstruct
individually rather than having you know
this confusing decoupling in the type
that it's not that direction but yeah
the function declaration
>> So instead of
matching on this tuple and grabbing the
left and the right value out of it and
then later on building that exact same
tuple again you can not do structure it
and pass that original tuple straight
through
>> Mm-hmm yeah which is a nice nice
add you know there's nothing wrong with
D structuring the tuple
>> But it makes it
harder to read like you said it can be
hard because you when you read that you
think okay I'm gonna be using each piece
of this individually but really you're
not you're just building that thing
again later
>> Right now if you later
you're trying to use that value one of
those values for me that makes sense
yeah but if it's only being passed to
another function there's no reason to do
that the next one
>> i think is the big one
>> is the Big Kahuna if you know what I
mean
and this one is something that you know
you you probably need to know and
understand what the code is doing yeah
to do effectively
>> yeah and I back it up a little bit all
the things we've talked about so far you
don't really need to understand what the
code is doing you can just look at it
and say oh I recognize that's kind of a
weird pattern let's do it this other way
instead
>> Mm-hmm yeah and I mean Italy the
big idea here and he kind of says in a
summary is like you know these factor
house is gonna hold your hand through it
you know like you can do this kind of
refactor in any language
it doesn't like there's always a way to
refactor the nice thing about high
school is it's gonna hold your hand
through
>> Yeah it helps you along the way
right
>> So this next big one is this idea
of like that unused value that we kind
of talked about earlier that's not
really needed in the core of the
function is we're getting rid of this
we're making a structural change and
design decision that allows like the
confidence that the type is doing what
we you know or the function and types
are doing what we expected yeah
>> We added
that invariant that said we're not using
this argument mm-hmm and now we're
finally getting rid of that argument so
we're like taking this information that
we had only in our head and pushing it
into the type signature of this function
so that it doesn't need that argument
anymore
>> Right you know and pushing out
some of the you know doing the doing the
making it pure and pushing out like the
core logic into a separate function and
allowing the original function just to
say hey I know I keep track of this
integer
because I need to know where I am
recursively mm-hmm but it doesn't
require that you know you know if I have
an empty list of choices that okay
I do nothing and if you know we have
something then okay let's we don't
really care about what that value is
we just need to do an action right so I
think that's really cool
>> Yeah so that's
one of the big refactorings and I feel
like we're maybe not doing it justice
over audio but they then follow up with
another really huge one which I think is
the the main kind of rallying cry of
type systems which is making legal
states unrepresentable so they say like
okay we've done all these little
refactorings to kind of clean it up and
make it easier to understand but now
let's do one that actually eliminates
some of these invariants that we have
and pushes them into the type system
>> mm-hmm oh yeah the big kahuna
>> Yep
the other big kahuna there's two of them
yeah
>> Yeah which I mean that's kind of
what he's saying is like hey there's
little things you can do but there's
also bigger things you can do so I think
it's very informational and yeah I think
you know kind of this is the moment
where you say okay these two things are
so closely tied together that they
shouldn't be separated and there should
be a you know the way to make the type
system make the legal states they
represent not representable yeah I don't
words are hard anyhow you know we're
kind of talking here but no we're trying
Travis
>> And this step actually reminds me
of a blog post awhile ago by Matt
Parsons called type safety back and
forth where he mentions that you can
have functions that you know return and
maybe a return in either or something
like that or you can have a function
where the input to that function
represents that invariant that you're
that you were enforcing by the output so
I feel like that's what's kind of
happening here we had a function that
returned to maybe because it was kind of
like connecting these two lists together
mm-hm and what we did instead was pushed
that connection out of the function and
said okay I take a tuple where the
things have already been connected and
then I don't have to return it maybe
anymore
I can always return something right so
in this particular instance they pushed
it out to a zip
at the top level that says okay combine
these two things
>> Right and you know it
it it didn't fully get rid of our maybe
but he got us closer it got us closer
right it allowed us to see what she can
talk to on Nexus you know okay we can
use on cons which Jack's very step after
that is don't use unconscious
pattern-matching but that's the thing is
you take baby steps exactly okay this I
see this as on console okay well okay
don't quite need uncon see here I can
just pattern match yeah it's just steps
>> you don't need to go 0 to 100 in one
step nope this is another upshot of
doing really small functions like we
talked about earlier is that sometimes
you'll have one of those small functions
and you'll see oh this is just some
other functions that I already knew but
I didn't realize it when I was using it
in the first place because often
especially in Haskell with really
polymorphic types you can have something
that's really concrete and then when you
actually write it out you say oh this is
just Traverse or map M or something like
that
>> Right which you'll see later
yeah he's foreshadowing in case alright
so the next one for me is something
that's beyond helpful and it's the unit
using dude notation mm-hmm
you know we have the bind operator in
Haskell and that's great and if you can
make the bind operator look
understandable that's awesome
yeah I'm a fan but the fact that 95% of
the time in my opinion do notation is
much clearer yeah and yeah I know it
these sugars to the bind operator
underneath the covers but it visually
and understandability was it doesn't
help and so that maybe that's part of
the reason why you know mark said oh
this is unattainable and unreadable like
this bind operator right here is not
helpful
>> Right yeah it's got to bind
right in the middle of like the core
business logic know that this thing is
doing so you have to understand not only
all of the Yahtzee rules but also this
weird Haskell operator and how it works
>> right which direction is it going what's
you know obviously the type system gonna
help you with that but
>> Yeah and I'm with
you 100% I feel like if you can use do
notation you probably should even if it
feels a little silly if you're only like
pulling one value out or something
it just it's so much more familiar to a
lot of programmers
>> Right because it's a
step-by-step process like okay do this
this value now I can use that value here
>> and even in cases like this where we're
using do notation with list datatype so
we can think of it kind of sequentially
like grab this value then grab this
value but really the list data type is
representing choice for us so it's
saying well choose a value here and then
choose another value and then combine
them in some way so you know that's the
that's the value add of mana adds is
that you can choose a different
representation and this one we're using
lists to represent doing different stuff
but we still use do notation right nice
>> good old list monad
cool well the next step is something
that I think as this refactor happened
it became apparently clear is we are
taking you know the head of a list
modifying that value and then sticking
it back onto the list right you know and
in him anybody's mind who's been around
Haskell cultural programming you know
even in NOLA no matter what the language
is
oh I'm just mapping over a list and
doing some operation on each value
>> mm-hmm that's a map
>> And so he's like hey
and you know we're in the list monad so
let's use math in
>> Right because the
action we're taking for each element is
monadic but yeah this is this is a great
example of these really small steps
paying off because you're looking at
this new saying you know what this is
just a map let's call it a map and that
way whoever reads it next doesn't have
to understand like the manual recursion
that's going on or whatever it is
they're like oh map I know how that
works
>> mm-hmm yeah no and I think that was a
big a big boost I mean it literally took
it from five you know seven lines to to
>> write it really crunches it down
>> Right
and and it's not any less clear right
>> I'd argue it's more clear right even
though it's shorter right
>> Because you
don't have to worry about oh this case
what's going on like it's all kind of
taken care of yeah which I think it's
really cool
>> and then finally we get to the last
factor
>> Which is one we've done an entire
podcast on exactly go check it out but
avoiding boolean blindness mm-hmm I
think last week when our teammates had
like this question like oh you just use
a boolean here and we're like we're all
like wait let's think about this like is
this a value we rely on or is it just a
value of returning and you know if
you're just returning the boolean okay
that's fine yeah but if you're trying to
use that in an operation it's yeah it's
not clear
>> Right so in this particular
example we have a tuple with a boolean
in it and some integer and if I just
describe that to you you don't actually
know what that means
but what we refactor it into is a data
type that says reroll this died or keep
this role that we already have had and
its value was this integer
now obviously the data type constructors
are much shorter than what I've just
said right but they communicate that
intent much better than a tuple with
these two things in it
>> Right
yeah it's like oh what am I doing with
this boolean yeah oh I'm either rolling
or I'm keeping it you know because it's
a state of type and you know you can
create a simple function that turns that
data type into the boolean result you
want
>> Right or you can pattern match on
it right so then it reads a lot better
when you're reading through the code you
don't have to say if you know this
boolean part of this tuple is true then
do this blah blah blah you can say oh if
we're reroll in
do this or if we're keeping it do that
>> right boolean blindness
>> So much nicer
being a blind
>> Yeah I love seeing yeah I
know I know we've talked about this
internally as a team is you know using
lambda case mm-hmm like it's cool I was
like I guess he you know he uses lambda
case which is cool and I think it's nice
I just also the normal case statement in
my mind is
>> It's not that much worse
>> right I'm not so yeah and there you can
you know you were uncontroversial
>> Yeah I
mean it's a pretty common language
extension mm-hmm but I do feel like it
kind of undercuts his argument here
where you know Haskell has a reputation
of needing all of these language
extensions to do
anything and I'm happy that he shows one
here because it does make it look nicer
but I feel like he could have just as
easily written out the lamda explicitly
and said well this is kind of you know
maybe not super nice and if you want to
avoid it use lamda case but really every
other programming language is pretty
comfortable using lambdas you know
JavaScript Ruby Python whatever you
would just write the lamda and nobody
would think twice about it
mm-hm so yeah and now we've arrived at
the end we have this perfect refactored
all roles function and we can now play
Yahtzee in Haskell
>> oh yeah and we can understand what we
wrote yes helpful yeah no go come back
later yeah we know what this is doing
rather than there's something going on
here I'm not sure so I mean I would
definitely agree with with marks like
feelings of it being on his original
work being unreadable and I'm
maintainable but I think you know Tom
says hey like I you I get that and
Haskell can be unreadable unattainable
but if you focus on not just type safety
but good design and type safety right
you can create a beautiful work of art
and you know
>> Yeah and and we now have
those two things complementing each
other where you use the types to
influence your design and your design
influences your types as well that's the
sweet spot to be in
>> Oh so sweet yeah I
mean I think this is a great article by
Tom I would definitely encourage all of
our listeners to go check it out it's a
little hefty but it's a good
intermediate post
>> Yeah and it really
teaches you or shows you rather these
refactoring strategies you can use in a
school or really as he mentions any
language but the reason that he focuses
on Haskell here is a because he knows it
I imagine but be it really pushes you in
the right direction with a lot of these
decisions it makes them easy
>> Right yeah
it definitely nudges it away so I think
that's pretty awesome but uh yeah I
appreciate being on the show today
>> thanks for being on the show with me cam
it's always great having you and thank
you for listening to the Haskell weekly
podcast this has been episode 22
we hope you enjoyed and if you did
please go rate and review us on iTunes
and tune in next week where we'll be
talking about Haskell once again who
knows what though
>> Yeah and you know
obviously this is sponsored by IT Pro TV
so any of your sis admin's or you know
networking geeks need any training
please have them check out itpro.tv
we'd love to get you on board and help
you out with all of our engaging content
by various IT platform so we're quite
excited and we're definitely gonna miss
you guys but we'll be back next week
>> See
you then