Hello and
welcome to the Haskell weekly podcast.
As you might have guessed
this show is about Haskell,
which is a purely functional
programming language.
I'm your host Taylor Fausak.
I'm the lead engineer at ITPro.TV.
>> I'm Cody Goodman.
I'm a senior engineer at ITProTV.
>> Thanks for joining me today, Cody.
What are we going to be talking about?
>> We are going to be following a blog
post called inventing monad and
talking through it cool.
>> I feel like I've been
programming Haskell for a while.
So I'm familiar with monads, but this is
more of a beginner's perspective, right?
>> Right, it tries to actually
go through and start using or
uses JavaScript throughout all
of those examples to make it
a little more approachable since
that's kind of the lingua Franca.
>> Yeah, for sure.
JavaScript use just a little bit
more than Haskell in industry, and
it's nice to see that the concept of my
monads can be applied in other languages.
It's not something that
is specific to Haskell.
>> Right.
>> So you mentioned that
he does this in JavaScript.
So how does he start off,
because I know that Haskell and
JavaScript represent
things a lot differently.
So it's kind of weird to see
that as a starting point.
>> Right, he just starts with
a normal kind of JavaScript block of
a function of how you
would get a middle name.
You have a function and
two constants in it.
A function call and two constants in it.
Then he does this sort
of pointless looking
transformation where he
introduces an apply function and
he uses that apply function
to get the middle name, and
then he calls the get user
function on that, and
then the apply above that as well.
And finally, calling get ID
with all of those things and
the subsequent plies on it.
>> Got you, so he has this kind of
straightforward JavaScript function and
he transforms it.
Throwing a seemingly unnecessary
amount of abstraction in there, but
I have to assume it'll
come in handy later.
>> [LAUGH]
>> Right,
he calls it a dense representation.
It totally looks pointless and
it's like God, why would you do this?
[LAUGH] Yeah, well,
hopefully he'll tell us.
And it's interesting
here that JavaScript and
Haskell again are such different
languages, but he manages to make
a function called syntax that ends
up looking pretty close to Haskell.
So if you kind of squint
your eyes a little bit,
you could imagine this JavaScript is
actually Haskell which is nice for me.
>> Yeah, great.
>> So now that we've thrown
all this extra syntax and
boilerplate in front of ourselves,
what do we actually get out of it?
What's the first thing that
he does with this stuff?
Well, the first thing is
he poses the question.
What if I ID, middle name,
user if any of those things could be null?
>> Which is super common, right?
>> Right, right, anything fails, you'll
get a null, especially in JavaScript.
He gives a code snippet
where the get ID and
get user functions are now checking for
null, same for get middle name.
>> Right, so I showing you kind of the
more typical JavaScript way of approaching
this problem, right?
>> Correct and showing how all of them
have to handle the null values and
the possibility of returning it.
>> Right, every single place.
>> And then he pivots and says,
what if we check for it automatically?
>> Right and how do we how
can we do that automatically?
Does it use that apply
function we had earlier.
>> Right, so the secret to all of this is
in that you change how these functions
are interpreted instead of changing
those functions themselves.
>> That's pretty cool.
So earlier, you said that apply,
it takes an argument in a function and
then it applies that function to that
argument exactly like you might expect,
but what does it do now that
null has entered the picture?
>> That's actually where he
gets to updating the applied
function where if x is equal to null,
so given apply xf.
If x is equal to null,
you just return null.
Otherwise, you apply f2x.
>> That's pretty cool.
I like to think of that as short
circuiting where once you encounter
a null, everything stops happening and
you just get null from that point out.
And I see that happening a lot in
JavaScript functions where you say,
right at the top of some handler,
you say, if some condition is met,
then return null or error or
whatever it is and then carry on.
So this is pretty similar
to that in my mind.
>> Yeah, there's just a lot of times we're
within a function, you'd have to do a lot
of nested if checks or something where
you could have used short circuiting.
>> Yeah, it cleans things up a lot,
I think.
So now that he's got this new apply
implementation that supports null
checking, what does he do with it?
>> He uses it to show how he can
get the middle name function
exactly the same way as he did
in the previous iterations.
>> And that's pretty cool, right,
that the same code can behave differently,
depending on if you need
to handle nulls or not.
>> Right.
>> It's starting to look a little bit
like something, but I don't know.
We don't wanna give it a name yet.
I don't wanna scare anybody off.
>> [LAUGH]
>> So after he shows this example
of dealing with null, he kind of pivots
and walks back to the original example and
then adds another, I'll call it an effect,
but another thing.
So instead of checking for null,
he does something else which is kind of
logging things as they happen, right?
So that if you were needing
to debug this function,
cuz you unexpectedly got
a middle name of popcorn and
that doesn't make sense and
you wanna figure out how you got there.
So these this logging would help
you figure that out, right?
>> Right, not being able to log and
functions like this if
we tell people coming to Haskell
like yeah, you can't log.
That's not going to work
right kind of eased.
>> You you need to be practical,
you got to debug stuff.
And so how do they approach logging, given
that they're trying to implement these
things as quote, unquote, pure functions?
>> So the first thing you do is in
functional languages avoid global
variables to keep track
of all those messages.
So the first pass that, that is modifying
utility functions to handle arrays.
>> And when you say arrays,
what do you mean?
What's in those arrays?
>> The result, as well as the log message.
>> Right, so you get back an array where
the first thing in it is the answer and
everything else is kind of stuff that
happened along the way that you might
be interested in and you might throw away.
>> Right,
the the trouble is that then your
functions have to know how to handle that.
>> Yeah, every single function you
call would need to like d structure or
lookup or whatever.
But fortunately, we have functions that
we've thrown in our own way here, right,
that we can change yet
again to do what we need here.
>> Right, that pointless seeming function
from it first apply which made things
look all horrible.
>> [LAUGH]
>> Now it's like we can just go back and
modify this now to distructure that and
show us what the logs, the results of.
>> Yeah, previously, we were using
the supply function to check for null.
But now we're saying,
grab that first thing out of it and
append all can cat together
all the other stuff.
So we're accumulating these log
messages as we go through, but
still producing the result that
we wanted in the first place.
>> Yeah and that's that's
really cool to be able to just
modify that apply again
to handle all our needs.
>> Exactly, pretty nice.
Again, you end up with the same
shape at the top level.
It still looks exactly the same.
But underneath the covers,
the implement, excuse me,
the implementation details are kind
of switched out from underneath you.
So instead of handling nulls,
now we're doing logging.
>> And that's why this blog
post does a really good job of
motivating why word we're
not saying is useful.
>> [LAUGH] Maybe at this point we can
start talking about it is in the title
after.
So-
>> Yeah.
So far, these have been two examples of
monads and this is showing you that yeah,
they are useful for
real life situations that you're gonna
come across as you're writing programs.
It's not just advanced
math Ivory Tower stuff.
>> For sure, there's a lot of it a lot
of real world advantages that you get
from monads and
he's worse good examples already.
>> And they're going to give a few more,
so let's kind of get through those.
They talk about global environment which
when I read that makes me shudder a little
bit, because I don't
like global environments.
I like things to be as local as possible,
but I think they don't really mean global.
They mean something else, don't they?
It's kind of like scoped to
the function or something like that.
>> Right, they mean for a given function,
you can provide an environment that
can be modified within that scope.
>> Right, so the way that I
like to think about this and
I think this actually came up in
our code base recently here at work
where we had a series of functions
that all needed some config and
we were passing that config from
function A to function B, B2 C, C to D.
And that's a lot of boilerplate, cuz you
have to thread that thing all the way
through and I think we came out of
that not having to thread it through.
Can you tell us how we got there?
>> Right, so
we started using a monad transformer which
the important thing is that
it had a reader monad in it.
>> And that reader monad is what?
>> That just means that you can
simply use a function called ask and
whatever you initiated that reader on Ed
with whatever value it was initiated with,
you'll get that back.
In our case, it was convicted.
Got you, so we had all these functions
that were operating in this monad.
And instead of passing an argument
through to everything in the single place
where we needed it, all we had to do was
ask for it and it was suddenly available.
>> Right and actually at one point,
we had both the new monad and
we were still passing in fig.
>> [LAUGH]
>> It headed twice just to make sure get
it from one place,
get it from the other and
make sure they're the same and
then move on.
>> [LAUGH]
>> Right.
>> So in this blog posts, he shows
this global environment example and
kind of walked you through the reader
monad is what it would be in Haskell and
provides motivation for
this example that we just ran into.
Passing all these arguments is annoying.
And if you can put it in your context and
then ask for it when you need it,
it's pretty nice.
And once again, as you might be
able to guess, you change apply and
your actual business logic ends up
looking the same and all the stuff
underneath the covers kind of changes out
from underneath which sounds scary, but
promise isn't as long as you
follow a few rules exactly.
They're important rules
as we call them laws, but
I don't think you get arrested
if you don't follow them.
It's just very, very frowned upon.
So now that we've gone through dealing
with nulls accumulating a bunch of state
in this case logs as we
go through stuff and
having a kind of read-only environment
that's available to our functions.
We land on the final example which is
state which is something that gets passed
to every function, but
also can be updated along the way.
Can you tell us a little
more about this example and
kind of how it differs
from the previous ones?
>> It's really similar like you're saying,
I think to the reader mpnad.
The only difference is that that
initial state that was passed in.
You can update it and you can you can get
it again do whatever you want with it.
>> And I think the example they use as
kind of innovation has to deal with
random numbers.
Because if you wanna generate a bunch of
random numbers in a pure fashion without
reading from like slash dev random or
something like that.
Typically, you're gonna need a random
number seed and those are deterministic.
So if you give something the same seed,
you get back the same answer which works
fine if you only need one random number.
You could throw that in your reader
context and pull out the seed,
and generate a random number.
But if you wanna generate to, you would
generate the same number both times,
because you couldn't change
that reader context.
So you need something like the state
where you can ask for to get it and
then do whatever operation you want with,
and
then put something back
into the state change it.
I actually remember I remember having
a bug with random numbers before where I
might have been using a reader monads
just threading that same seed through.
And after I figured it out,
it just reminded me of the xkcd comic,
it's like turn 42.
>> Yeah, guaranteed random.
We rolled some dice and
figured out this is a very random number.
We're just gonna keep giving it to you.
[LAUGH] Yeah, so
we don't want to implement
random number generators like that and
you don't have to.
The monad abstraction is powerful enough
to give you this ability to consistently
take something in into your environment
and use it, and modify it, and
then return that back out
along with your answer.
So once again, we end up with
changing the apply function and
using the same business logic over and
over and over again.
So that gets us through all of the
motivating examples that this guy gave for
monads and he managed to make it through
this post without using monads we didn't
quite think we made it halfway through.
>> [LAUGH]
>> But this is something that happens
a lot in the Haskell community, right,
beginners kind of finally grokking monads.
Have you seen this come up before?
>> Yeah a ton.
I personally started writing
Haskell just by making
functions of the five
ten fifteen arguments.
Yeah, to pass the state through and
then I finally got annoyed and I was like
I'm going to learn what monads are about
and I came across a billion tutorials.
>> [LAUGH]
>> Monads are burritos.
What else are they?
>> They're all kinds of things.
I keep thinking the straws, but
I think that's lenses are straws.
Monads are burritos.
Their boxes, their containers.
I don't know, any number of things.
>> That's why I really like tutorials like
this which focus on some real examples,
because you're not gonna get very far with
metaphors as much as you will with using
these things and seeing why those
laws that are seemingly pointless.
Why there is applied functions
through seemingly pointless help you.
>> Yeah, I agree.
I much prefer seeing a motivating example
rather than here's the type signature and
here's the laws and
it's important and good luck.
>> [LAUGH]
>> Walking through stuff like this really
helps me or
would have helped me when I was learning
Haskell see why do I care about this?
What do I get out of it?
>> Exactly.
>> And like you, I've seen so many of
these tutorials through the years that
it's feels a little bit like a rite
of passage for new Haskellers.
Like yeah,
you got to learn what mountains are and
then you got to write blog posts
that says you what they are.
>> And that's exactly what's happened.
Yeah, [LAUGH] somehow I think neither you,
nor I have written this blog post,
but maybe that just means we haven't
truly understood monads yet.
>> [LAUGH]
>> Well, I hope we do.
We're making a podcast about them.
>> Yeah, it does this count
as a blog post probably.
Anyway, I think that about wraps it up for
us today.
Thanks for
being with me on the show today, Cody.
>> Thanks for having me, Taylor.
It was a lot of fun.
>> It was a lot of fun.
It's always good and
good having you on here, and thank you for
listening to the Haskell weekly podcast.
If you like what you heard,
please find out more at our website,
haskellweekly.news.
And if you did like our show, again,
please go rate and review us on iTunes.
It helps a lot.
Haskell weekly is brought to you every
week by ITPro.TV, the tech skills
development platform for IT professionals
who also happens to be our employer.
So please send your sysadmins and
network admins to www.itpro.tv for
other learning needs and
they can let you know what they think of
the people who develop it which is us.
So thanks again, Cody and
we'll see you all next week.
[MUSIC]