hello and welcome to the Haskell weekly
podcast as you might have guessed this
show is about Haskell which is a purely
functional programming language
I'm your host Cameron Guerra and I'm an
engineer here at IT Pro TV and I'm
Andres Royce I'm also an engineering an
IT for a TV it's really excited to have
you on the show today man how you doing
think it I've been here 2/10 now and
it's pretty good to be here yeah it's
pretty fun huh get to hang out talk
about high school be nerds it's always a
good time yeah well guys today we're
actually gonna be talking about a
article called practical Pro functor
lenses and optics in pure script and yes
we know this is pure script but we just
thought the the topic was good and this
article is also written by Thomas
Honeyman and it can be found an issue
172 of Haskell weekly so if you want go
check that out because it's a pretty
good article
all right on just well we're talking
about you know lenses and optics in your
experience what is that so I've been
here for about three months now and
that's pretty much how long I've been
doing Haskell and my question is exactly
what do we use lenses for and why do we
need them yeah so that's like that's a
great question
and in my professional experience which
isn't much more than yours maybe you
know another year so the the experience
I've had with it is you know getting
into two nested objects and seeing
really what nested data structures have
in store and then actually being able to
mutate them which and my most experience
being in JavaScript you know I have this
like fear of mutation is evil but
Haskell has lenses which allow mutation
within you know and the other optics as
well which is prisms Trevor traversals
and ISOs which they're all kind of cool
and I definitely think you know this
article talks a lot about all of them
but I definitely want us to stick to
lenses so we've useless is a lot here at
IG Pro for XML mostly huh there's
another library we use that helps us
with our AWS integration coding
amazonica that also uses lenses
but yeah we use that because the data
structures can be pretty hairy things
are pretty hard to get into the nested
objects of XML you know so what what's
your experience with dealing with XML
and other languages so coming from an
imperative background and JavaScript and
Java and specifically Android XML is
something that is it's a red herring
things that every single programming
languages have tried to solve and it
seems like for every single
implementation that I've seen a parsing
does it is super complicated especially
so on languages like Android where when
I first started didn't have it at all
and the the internal implementations for
XML were not allowed to be used in the
Android library so it became this thing
that would be really difficult to use so
it was very interesting to come to
Haskell and start to see how we handled
XML especially as a you know back-end
server side language for Haskell and it
seems like it's complicated but it also
seems like it's doable it's not a thing
that is almost impossible or you'll have
to write your own parsing and you know
have to deal with everything that comes
with parsing so with to me lenses have
been interesting because it's a
complicated solution to a complicated
problem yeah
and it does add you know another level
of mental complexity to learning high
school right it's just not the syntax
it's not you know it's another level of
you know oh this is a possibility high
school the other thing is it is possible
to parse XML and things like that with
out lenses and we've done it here at IG
pro TV and it's needless to say rough
you know trying to filter out exactly
what you need out of every element and
all the nodes and children elements that
kind of things whereas XML or sorry
excuse me using lenses in you know to
parse the XML allows us to get out
specific values without having to know
what else is in the XML
which is helpful because we don't have
to filter out things we don't need or
filter things we do need so Linds has
allowed us to get you know the deeper
nested objects which is great you know
and without all the boilerplate have you
kind of experience anywhere where you're
dealing with nested objects that you
felt like when's this could have maybe
helped with producing boilerplate so
that's actually the point that we were
discussing way before we even came into
this article which was why even use
lenses we have all of these solutions
available to us why use lenses so coming
back to the the parsing of JSON one
thing that came to mind was we use the
Ehsan library to parse JSON just because
that's what I was told to use and it
seems like it was it is a very good way
to parse JSON there is one and only one
downside that I've seen so far and it's
been sort of nagging at me and that is
the fact that it's got a lot of
boilerplate to be able to parse all of
this JSON that is coming into your
server and one of the worst offenders of
it are very nested objects to be able to
use JSON in a manner that isn't required
to do any kind of fancy parsing you'll
need to set up a data structure with an
instance for every single level of your
JSON object not a hundred percent sure
but I think with lenses if you didn't
care for this structure that was already
there so let's say that you're hitting a
third-party library and you just cared
about one thing and inside a nested
object I could see lenses being useful
in removing a lot of that boilerplate
code my question is is it worth it is
the complexity trade-off versus the
boilerplate trade-off worth it and with
Haskell from what I've seen so far high
school is very concise it's the language
that allows you to write things in a
very concise manner lenses is just
another extension of this right that's a
little a little more complex but you
know it's yes definitely the question of
when do use lenses first
- first for the complexity aspect and I
think something we talked about earlier
was you said we don't use lenses for
JSON but we do for XML and I think with
JSON there's there's a little more types
there right there's a little you know
inherently it's a little easier to
understand you could take a JSON file
and look at it and understand what is
what where do you pull out an XML file
and you're like wait a second what's
going on here and I'm sorry I think the
reason that complexity lives for XML is
because it is a confusing data structure
as it is it's great it does
you know it's effective but it's a it's
confusing and hard to read from a visual
you know a visual perspective and you
know the it kind of reflects in the code
right that's kind of crazy huh
definitely and if you think about it XML
specifically it doesn't have any kind of
data structure e things that people are
normally used to seeing in code because
of the fact that in and of itself is a
sort of you know Dom language so it's a
it's got a document and it's got about a
whole bunch of different tags and values
and they don't necessarily need to mean
anything they are just there and you
know hTML is XML it's just a different
it's a different subset of it so if you
look into XML XML isn't a data structure
that is easily possible by anything with
JSON from what I've you know discovered
it was meant to be a or it is a
replacement for XML to be more towards
transferring of information simpler
mm-hm and I think that's why going back
to the whole complexity issue we have a
complicated problem very complicated
step I'm sorry we have a complicated
solution for a complicated problem
mm-hm and that is my experience with
this right and and we were talking to
more about you know some of the
fundamental aspects of lenses right and
we touched on it a lot earlier about the
mutability and with xml you know we want
to be able to reach into an object and
if we're gonna change it you not have to
parse everything else around
but just change that one aspect right
because it could get complicated
where's Java you know JSON sorry we're
gonna be wanting to we could just make a
whole new object and deal with it you
know because it's it's easy to kind of
just create and I think Haskell
definitely no I think most programming
languages are much more friendly to JSON
than they ever will be to XML so daggone
complicated problem luckily we have the
complicated solution but I wanted to
kind of talk a little bit about lenses
and get back more to the focus not the
JSON for his XML thing because that's
you know this is kind of our context in
which we view it and we understand
lenses can be you know using many
aspects and we're just kind of speaking
for a personal experience here but yeah
like the ability you know lenses
specifically have to you know they can
view something though there's like three
functions that are pretty critical to
you know lenses and are really the only
ones that can be used our view set and
over so view is a get function right
let's get it out set is the function
that's able to mutate it which is
setting the value and we also have over
which is kind of like a map so it's
saying you know we're gonna modify this
value in this lens with a function and
here's the function that takes you know
takes that value gives you back the same
value modified which is you know helpful
that lenses has that built in which yeah
you would think it definitely should
considering we're in Haskell one and so
that was something that was you know
interesting for me to see and understand
and get a comprehension on is you know
what are the access to functions what do
I do with lenses how do I make a lens
that that even the Constructors I don't
super haven't spent a ton of time
dealing with because you know the
libraries we have have easy ways to
construct the new lens or you know
whatever and so yeah I just thought that
you know these functions at the core are
pretty easy to understand but I think
people can also get a little bit
confused about how they're operating
right
because we're operating within this
optic this lens which I think for some
people is a little more confusing where
JavaScript you're just like yeah hey
here's this value I found it I have
access to it
okay just change it to this Haskell
still kinda says hey hold on we're gonna
make it a little more difficult for you
to mute a something but here's what you
can do
uh-huh which i think is you know it's
it's nice because Haskell says okay you
know obviously this article we're
reading it's in pure skip so I'm just
pulling it over to Haskell because we're
talking about it's a hassle podcast so
like I think it's very much it's like a
yeah because it's just a necessary means
to solve this really deep nested object
issue I totally agree with the whole
lens aspect of these things this is just
an optic this is not a mutation now what
I mean by that is a school's entire
paradigm is please don't mutate my
things so lenses give you an option to
go in there and mutate it in such a way
that makes sense to Haskell which you
know when you start thinking about what
a mutation is it makes sense that really
you Haskell is mutating and it's
probably mutating a lot of stuff in the
background
I don't know much like I said just
started three months ago but I'm
assuming that Haskell's functional
paradigm is on the front side but it
obviously will have to have some kind of
state in the background and lenses will
give you a view into this mutations I'm
not entirely sure that's where the name
comes from probably not but that's how I
see it and leading into this I have the
question that has been a little nagging
and lenses aren't just for these types
of data structures that come from like
JSON or XML or any kind of server thing
the lenses are used for a raise for
lists for maps any kind of data
structure that you can think of can be
used through a lens and my question to
you is would you use lenses in that
scenario yeah that's a great question
and I think it would boil down to you
know do
I wanna like if I'm gonna modify
something is it worth it to make a new
one or just modify that single their
value in most the time you know we
choose make a new one right brand new
yeah
the old one goodbye see you later but if
we have a huge data structure that we
don't want to continually load into
memory or be passing around maybe it is
easier to say hey let's just use a lens
and modify those values along the way
and keep the same thing so I definitely
say high school the community of high
school also we lean a lot more towards
make a new one rather than modify a
value but yet lenses give you that
option and I think that goes in line to
what my thought process was which is if
you don't think you need it or even if
you think you might need it don't use
lenses until you're sure that lens has
become a necessity right like I would
definitely not lean towards yeah if you
want to go go ahead and make your whole
architecture if you're using lenses
because you know it will work and it
would be fine
but it's just gonna add a lot of
complexity in areas you may not always
need that complexity and angry yeah and
one thing to note here just a little
side note I was just looking at this one
little thing we had highlighted here you
know a key difference with the lens
specific optic is the value has to be
known or like has to be known to exist I
should say whereas you know prisms or
traversals or ISOs that's not true
you know prisms are you know you kind of
can't think of it as maybe or the either
monads and you know dealing with the
maybe neither monads and you know
traversals thinking more like lists and
arrays and you know maps things like
that and so that's something to be to
note is you know you want to make sure
if you're gonna use a lens you know
these are values you want to make sure
they're if not you probably want to look
more into like a prism and say hey does
this thing exist before I try to go get
it in you know that would like you know
prisms allow have something called
preview which is okay go see if this is
there if not
let's let's bail um so that you know
that's another thing to think about if
you're using lenses is you know the
value has to be there and exist or else
you could probably get some some gnarly
runtime errors yeah and I think my
takeaway from this talk is lenses are
complicated I will probably only reach
for them for problems that are
complicated not for simple problems
mm-hmm and that is something that in the
last three months it's exactly what I've
seen so far is the only time we've ever
used lenses in our environment is just
solve a complicated problem much more
specifically to us XML and I that is my
takeaway from this I am open to finding
out that lenses are a lot more powerful
and a lot more structured way of doing
something it's just I haven't come
across it yet mm-hmm yeah and that's
totally fair and you know if you're you
know beginning high school I would
definitely out there over-the-head say
hey slow down on lenses like they
they're not a core component necessarily
you know you'll run into libraries you
use that may have lenses you know for us
we have Amazon which is our AWS library
and then we have text XML dot lenses is
also a big thing so core components do
have lenses and you can use and solve
problems with lenses but I would
definitely say that's not you know just
because that added complexity could you
know just kind of demotivate you home
from solving the problem because high
school you know that's one thing I love
about high school is there's a ton of
ways to solve a problem you know yeah
the more complicated problems there's
less options for beginners out there
don't be don't be afraid of lenses but I
wouldn't go chasing them you know don't
go chasing waterfalls stick to the
rivers and lakes that you're used to you
know we've got record syntax with that
you know instances we have type classes
things like that they can kind of bypass
the old need for lenses so definitely
feel better about that so are just you
have anything else you want to kind of
touch on in regards to specific lenses
no I think we've covered everything I
enjoyed our little talk about lenses
yeah I think it was good and you know I
think there's definitely more out there
so definitely check out the article
because it's super you know it was
pretty informative because I hadn't
really spent time looking at lenses
lenses in depth or prisms or traversals
or Isis so it's definitely pretty
informative to me I definitely encourage
our readers to go out there and check it
out but thanks for being on the show
with me today Andris thank you for
having me cam and thank you for
listening the haskell weekly podcast be
like what you heard find out more on our
website haskell weekly dot news also
please rate us and review us on iTunes
it helps a lot haskell weekly is brought
to you by IT Pro TV the tech skills
development platform for IT
professionals and also our employers
yeah that to send ursus admins and
network admins WWI T Pro TV for all your
training needs and then they can tell
you what they think of the people who
develop it yeah thanks again for being
on the show we'll see you again next
week see ya
you