>> Hello and welcome to the Haskell Weekly
podcast. As you might have guessed, this
show is about Haskell, a purely
functional programming language.
I'm your host Cameron Gera. I'm an
engineer here at ITProTV, and with me
today we have ...
>> Jose Silvestri. I'm
an intern at ITProTV.
>> Woo! We got our
intern in here. He's pretty witty,
pretty cool. We're excited to have you on
the show today, man.
>> Thank you man, appreciate it.
>> Jose, what are we
talking about today?
>> So we're talking about our Haskell
survey.
>> Well it's not OUR Haskell survey,
it's THE Haskell survey.
>> THE Haskell survey.
>> It's big --
it's big time guys, it's big time. But no,
Taylor, our -- he was also on this
podcast a lot. He kind of put together
this Haskell survey that he does.
He's done this for two years now, well
this will be his third year. So kind of
putting, you know, a survey out to kind of
get the temperature of, you know, Haskell.
What the community wants,
what the community commonly uses, what
kind of trends and stuff like
that, you know. What does the Haskell
-- you know, what did the Haskell
survey kind of glean for you, as you did
it?
>> Yeah
I really thought -- there's a section
on it of what would I like to see more
of content-wise about Haskell, and that
was a really useful thing to me because
I feel like there's certain areas of,
sort of, the Haskell info sphere that
are very lacking, and I think surveys
like this are very useful on that
end, just for people to see what
the community wants, what's missing, what
type of content needs to be made and so
on.
>> Right, yeah. I think, you know, for me
taking the survey for the second year,
you know, looking at it this year, it's
very, you know, there was, you know, a section
on community. How do you feel like you
fit into the community, do you feel like
it's welcoming, do you feel like you can
communicate with people. And I think
that's one thing, you know,
as I looked at those questions
was like, I probably haven't plugged in to
the Haskell community as much as I want to,
you know. But you kind of use
all these things that are out there but
it was kind of a good introspective to
look at like, oh we should probably be
in the community a little bit more.
>> For
sure. And also it's a good place
I guess see what avenues of
communication there are. It's also a really
nice list just to see what's out there.
>> Yeah Taylor did a very thorough
job of making sure you know all the
stuff's out there. But I'm also you know
we want you to know: these surveys,
these are -- there's more surveys like this
out there, you know. I know Stack Overflow
does, you know, development for the year
and kind of, you know, you can see the
temperature of who's using what
programming languages, what tools they're
using, stuff like that. And so I think
this was really nice to kind of dive in.
This one specifically to dive into Haskell
you know being a mostly Haskell
programmer now. It was
cool to kind of put in my input.
>> Yeah for
sure. I think getting the temperature of
the Haskell community is particularly
important for our community.
>> Right right right.
We want to -- the Haskell community as
a whole is kind of, you know, it's there,
but it's been under the, you know --
underneath and, you know, there's not
really a lot of: "Oh, Haskell! Using Haskell, that's
awesome!" People like: "You're using Haskell,
what's that?" So getting a
survey out like this can, you know, kind
of get, you know -- cause there's I mean
looking at the survey results from the
previous years, which will link to in the
show notes here, but you know there's
trends you see of like, there's people
who fill out the survey who have never
touched Haskell, but they found it.
And like that's exposure you know. So
surveys like this kind of open up,
you know, opportunities for people to
learn about programming languages. In our
case, Haskell.
>> Yeah for sure.
It's really good to get some feedback on
the accessibility of our community, not
only in terms of the people in it, but
also, we are sort of in a community where
we have very specific -- a very specific
language for talking about things, and
let me be off-putting to a lot of people.
I feel like maybe getting people's
feedback on that, that are not part --
already part of the community, and how
they sort of internalize this
language when they first hear it.
>> It's very interesting.
>> Yeah, no and I
think that's ...
Haskell seems like this
big bad scary thing, and I think a lot of
people carry that. And you know this
survey allows us to kind of get the
temperature. Is that really the case or
is that just something we're saying?
So I'm really excited about this year's
survey. And you know, because now we'll
have three years of data, I know we'll
kind of be analyzing some trends a
little bit more. I know we want to get
this data out to the community and out
to the development community as a whole,
but also the, you know, more particularly
the Haskell community, to kind of
see: "Oh, like ..." You know, "Oh Jose, you use
Visual Studio, like, oh there's another
thousand people who also use Visual
Studio. Maybe I should give it a try and
see what extensions there are, and you
know packages that will help me be a
more effective, you know, developer.
>> You know, when it comes to
dealing with Haskell." So you know there's
a lot of different cool things in there.
I would definitely recommend all of our
listeners here to go check it out.
It takes like, what -- five, ten minutes?
>> Yeah I literally filled that out while I
was waiting for my food to come out.
>> During lunch today he took the survey,
which is good, you know. We wanted
to be prepared for this podcast, so we
both took it today. But yeah I would
definitely recommend everyone to go
check it out. It is open until November
14th 2019, so be sure to fill that out
quick. The time is running out.
We have seven days left, so by the time --
it's just now the 7th, by the time
you guys get this in your hands, it may
be close to the deadline. So please,
please, please go check it out. But
yeah, you got any other, like -- what has
been your feedback and experience with
other surveys. Like how does the Haskell
survey compare?
>> I don't take
that many surveys, honestly. But this one
was, like -- I took it not only because I
know Taylor, but also because I do care
about this language and community, and I
think it's a very quick and very
effective way to help out our community.
And hopefully sort of be a little nudge
in the right direction.
>> Right yeah yeah. I
don't take a lot of surveys either so it
really was a loaded question, I'm sorry. But
you know it's one of the things
that
nobody has really a lot of time to take
surveys, but I definitely encourage all
of you to check it out. But I think we're
gonna keep this episode short. Was there
anything else you want to touch on?
>> Not really but, yeah. We just wanted to
get the word out about the survey, and
encourage you guys to, if you're
listening, to go ahead and fill that out.
>> Check it out, what what!
>> Check it out bro!
>> Awesome. Well
guys, thank you for joining us.
Jose, thank you for being on the show
today man.
>> Thank you for having me, Cam.
>> The
Haskell Weekly Podcast. If you like what
you heard find out more at our website
HaskellWeekly.News. And please
rate us and review us on iTunes. It helps
a lot. Haskell Weekly is brought to you by
ITProTV, the tech skills development
platform for IT professionals.
>> And also
our employer.
>> Yeah, that too. So send your
sys admins and network admins to www.itpro.tv
for all their learning needs. And
give them this promo code which will give
them 30 percent off: it is HaskellWeekly30. So
HaskellWeekly30 will give them 30
percent off an annual or monthly
subscription, so please please please
send them our way.
>> And then they can tell
you what they think about the people who
developed it.
>> That's true. Thanks for
listening. we'll see you next week.
Bye!