hello and welcome to the Haskell weekly
podcast as you might have guessed this
show is about Haskell which is a purely
functional programming language
I'm your host Dustin seekers and I'm an
engineer here at IT Pro TV hi I'm Cody
Goodman I'm a senior engineer here at
IPTV where were you talking about today
desam we're talking about game
development in Haskell I thought it
would be cool to kind of bring together
my love of game development in games
video games in general and Haskell which
is what I use daily here at Ida Pro TV I
was gonna actually have a few questions
for you and I figured it would be cool
to kind of just look into the Haskell
game dev community in space and see what
all was out there yeah I think a lot of
people are in your position you know if
you browse the Haskell subreddit you'll
see occasionally questions about people
wanting to make games and people
frustrated trying to make games so if if
you don't take the right path that can
be pretty frustrating
one recommendation I've seen over the
years and tried a little myself is to
start out with a 2d library called gloss
Ketchum have you ever heard of it yeah
actually our lead engineer I think he
did a few just very basic games using
gloss I heard it was super intuitive and
quick to get something up on the screen
right right yeah that's that's one of
the reasons I recommend it and I think a
lot of other people recommend it is you
can you can draw a window and draw a
circle and a single line and it's all
and you know plain English words that
you might be able to guess yourself nice
you know glosses really aimed at
simplicity there's a ton of tutorials
available not just like basic tutorials
but tutorials of you know how do you
make pong oh yeah right
it's more of an end-to-end thing which
has schools sorely lacking in other
areas but when you're just getting
started and it's a new paradigm a new
language you you need you know a little
bit hand-holding to just get all the way
from point A to point B at least exactly
at least once mm-hmm so that's it
so gloss seems really attractive to me
in that as
fact mainly because I'm not super
proficient in Haskell I've only been
doing it for a little while
but I do enjoy it and I think I have
more experience in game development
mainly as a hobby right versus you know
programming in Haskell so I would like
to merge both of them and Glaus seems
like a pretty good pretty good way to do
that
yes and for people trying to merge their
game development experience or interest
in their love Haskell he'll probably run
into a functional reactive programming
which you know if you are really in
proficient in high school it can be a
bit of a mind bender to wrap your head
around that can't you yeah I actually
just doing a little bit of research
before this podcast we stumbled upon FRP
functional reactive programming and then
also just your classic main iterating
over your main game loop and do you have
any like I guess a concise way if you
could explain functional reactive
programming to those who don't know I
didn't come up with the best answer
myself but I I looked around and hope I
see the name right here T cons Elvis as
they a talk on answering that that
question you know you have to have a
whole talk to answer it yeah he says if
I had to summarize it in one sentence I
would say that functional reactive
programming is programming with time
varying values now that's not the most
satisfying answer for someone who might
already be overwhelmed yeah yeah but
basically that's for lack of anything
better to use at this moment it's state
right like represent state yeah it's a
lot like state the so it still encodes
the information that state would encode
the difference would be that the way
that these things compose together are
different we won't get too deep into
that and that's one of the reasons we
recommend gloss to start
with yeah so you can just you know gloss
over
FRP yeah let's see what you did there
okay cool so do we have any like games
that may have used FRP and examples of
that or up top your head yeah any
packages that might implement or use
this yeah a recent recent really cool
game with a an interesting premise that
we might recognize the roots of is
people Mon yes I did see that I believe
is by Alex Stewart correct right right
and so the premise is that you you catch
people and in battle with them and style
of Pokemon and I got you that's pretty
funny yeah I did I got a chance to at
least watch the little trailer for it
and go to the site but I have not yet
played it I planned to play it mmm-hmm
here it's it's pretty short but looks
pretty entertaining at the very least oh
and I recommend at least check out their
homepage pretty hilarious images on the
gadget let's see so people Mon what was
it based on it was Yampa I think okay
which is an FRP library you'll notice
that the more complex examples of high
school games use FRP I think we had an
exception which used your classic game
loop which we'll talk about in a second
but just to answer why these libraries
might prefer FRP as as complexity scales
up FRP
seems to have some advantages over the
classic game loop much in the way that
Haskell has advantages over imperative
languages oh yeah that actually reminds
me Cody we will be linking the package
Yampa as well as people maan and other
things mentioned in this podcast on our
Haskell weekly podcast page so if you're
you know interested in you know finding
these not really having to Google
even though you totally can we'll have
those links available at the Haskell
weekly podcast page but the mention of
people Mon and then also Pokemon which
is a mainstream game I will found out
just a little while ago that there was
actually a Haskell game that was
greenlit on Steam now they've retired
the whole greenlight thing on Steam but
so this is a little bit older but it was
still pretty cool to see that I think it
was even back in 2012 right people were
using Haskell to create games and yeah
they actually you know we're we're
getting somewhere with it
trailblazers for sure that was Nikki in
the robots and I remember watching on
excitedly in their development blog and
tracking their progress trying to get
everything building myself it was
exciting and then to see that they got
on Steam greenlight it was like wow so
in 2012 it's possible to write a high
school game if you put in enough effort
and get it greenlit on Steam it's
actually really cool yeah I noticed that
um I went to their page and I did a
little a little snooping around and I
saw their tech stack consisted of
Hipmunk which is the physics engine
right yeah it's a Haskell take on
chipmunk mm-hmm which is pretty cool
it looks like the package is now
deprecated so it might be a little old
but it was still nice and cool to see
that you know the community is out there
and they're doing things with it
yeah you know I rewatched Nicki in the
robots video after after looking around
for some examples and it just made me
think you know what would it take to
revive Nicki and the robots and make it
something compiling something that
people for instance in this podcast you
heard about this could go and download
the source code and try it out
you know much work is it to update that
there was an older FPS game made in
highschool I can't recall the name of it
but somebody did the work to like bring
it current oh well is it really cool
nice
maybe somebody maybe me maybe you or
someone hearing this can try to revive
Nick
the robot right and it's also just it
would be good to I guess have something
else to do to emergencies I guess these
hobbies and this love of a Haskell
together and which would help progress
you know my skill in Haskell as well so
I guess that's like another right
another bonus doing this on the topic of
that there is also Dino rush which you
know if you're wanting to merge your
hobbies of high school and game
development but you're kind of new you
might want to use like a classic game
loop and Dino rush actually went that
route and they used a class a game loop
so highly recommend anyone who wants to
do that
to check out their blog post that I
think you're probably going to put the
resources to yes download the source
code get it building poke around in
there nice yeah I'm definitely gonna do
that actually went to the page earlier
and checked it out and it's it's pretty
cool I like the the pixel art for the
game it looks pretty right and in for
context the game diner rush it's you
know when you lose internet connection
on Google Chrome yes jump over stuff I
think we have a high scoreboard
something around in the office those
examples are pretty inspiring Cody but
if I get lost how could I get support
right you know we were talking about
Nikki and the robots and their
trailblazers there wasn't there weren't
really a lot of people trying to do high
school game dev back then so they had to
figure out all those things herself but
then at some point past that they
started a or someone started a subreddit
called our slash Haskell game dev and
they made a wiki of how to get started
now they're getting started I think is
more fitted to complex games and I would
still recommend using gloss to get
started since it'll won't get you up and
running the fastest but some really good
resources there they also have
a Haskell game dev channel on freenode
if you're familiar with IRC chat and you
can usually get pretty quick help in the
Haskell chat room I'm guessing the
Haskell game dev is similar then there's
always Stack Overflow I've noticed quite
a few game to have questions and asked
will get answered on Stack Overflow
gotcha nice yeah I'll definitely give
those a shot and just to clarify
somebody coming from let's say unity3d
developing there there's nothing like
that currently for the Haskell community
right like it's basically c-sharp for
the most part in Wright unity right yeah
nothing is complete as unity there is a
game engine that I think attempted to be
something like unity called helm that
you might want to take a look at I think
it still compiles the latest GHC and is
is working couldn't find any good game
examples of it though gotcha okay cool
thanks for being on the show with me
today Cody no problem that's been a lot
of fun and thank you for listening to
the Haskell weekly podcast if you liked
what you heard find out more at our
website haskell weekly dot news also
please rate and review us on itunes it
helps a lot a school weekly is brought
to you by IT pro TV the tech skills
development platform for IT
professionals and also our employer yeah
that's you so send your sis ID mins and
network admins 2ww IT pro TV for all of
their learning needs thanks again for
listening we'll see you again next week