Hello and
welcome to the Haskell weekly podcast.
This is a podcast about Haskell a purely
functional programming language.
I'm your host Taylor Fausak,
I'm the lead engineer here at ITProTV.
And with me today is Sara Lichtenstein,
one of the engineers on my team.
Thanks for joining me, Sara.
>> Thanks for having me, Taylor.
>> It's good to have you here and
today we're gonna be talking
about profiling in Haskell.
And in particular,
this article by Jake Zimmerman,
where he talks about speeding up
one of his programs by ten times.
So pretty pretty significant improvement.
>> Yeah definitely, I think anything
ten times improvement is pretty great.
>> Yeah, its hard to argue with that,
can't beat ten times better.
So Jake explains the problem he was
trying to solve in this article and
we will kinda recap for
our listeners here.
He was at a carnival and playing this
carnival game where he had a six by six
grid of shapes or symbols and
you turned over some pieces and
tried to see if you got a bingo like if
you lined up a whole column or a row or
a diagonal or something like that.
And he was interested in finding out if or
rather what their probability was of
winning this carnivore of a game.
So how good should he feel when he wins?
Is it like you win 50% of the time or
1% of the time?
And he figured that he could write some
type of combinatorics solution to get
the exact answer like you're gonna
win exactly 123 out of 767 times.
But he thought it would be more fun to
write one that just generated these boards
and shuffled all the pieces together and
then solve at one or not.
>> If a task takes more than five minutes,
why not program it?
>> Exactly, yeah.
Why sit there all day making bingo
boards if you could write a Haskell
program to do that for you.
So he wrote this program and
it seemed to work.
He didn't really talk too much about if
he got the implementation right or not.
So we're assuming he got
the implementation right, but
his first time around was way too slow for
him.
And his threshold for too slow is
apparently very different than mine
because his first attempt took
the order of like one second.
And this I think was to generate and
solve like 100,000 boards.
So for me that seems fast enough for
this problem, but
I definitely understand wanting
to really dig in to something and
find out how fast can it be and
he definitely went on that red hole.
So he talks about some of the changes
he made to his attempts and
the first one was to use like a single
large integer as the whole game board.
Because with,
I think yeah with 36 slots on the board,
you could represent that
in one large integer
rather than having some data structure
with a bunch of different fields in it.
>> Right.
>> And his assumption was that if you can
use one integer then it will probably
be faster cuz you're not gonna have as
many things floating around in memory.
But it's also I think,
somewhat of a strange choice.
So Sara for the pro or for the programs
that we right here at work, we don't do
a lot of this really cramming, getting the
most performance possible out of stuff.
So I was wondering, did this look weird
to you or you're like okay, yeah,
I kind of get what's going on here.
>> The idea in general
just using one inter just
seems very odd
>> Yeah
>> To represent this whole thing.
But he did make a point about how
simple this was to implement for
him.So I guess you know if it's easy
to implement and it works why not.
>> That's a great point.
Yeah, why make things more
complicated just in looking for
Purity or something like that.
>> Exactly.
>> But yeah, he said he was able to pretty
quickly knock out this Fisher Yates
Shuffle to generate the random boards and.
This used a random number generator, the
one kind of from the standard library in
Haskell for doing this stuff which
is of course just called random.
And so he kind of-
>> What else was he called?
>> Why I come up with a more
imaginative name, random works fine.
But as we'll discover,
there's kind of a problem with that.
And what he did was he passed in
this random number generator and
did one step of the shuffle and gave back
the slightly shuffled board and they
are like next random number generators.
So just keeps getting passed
along to successive calls.
Which is of interesting
the way they do things and
makes sense for Haskell because it's pure.
So you have to have something that's
sort of implements that randomness,
but it's still kind of strange even
to me after programming it for
a while to see that explicitly
passed in as an argument.
So then he gets into kind of
the performance characteristics, and
this is where he talks
about how slow it is.
And again, it's crazy to me that's under a
second, and he's like it's just too slow.
>> Yeah, I found that very hilarious,
because I started reading it and
he was like, yeah 738 milliseconds and
Im like, what in the world?
How is that slow, [LAUGH]?
>> Yeah, I would think,
okay we're done here you know?
[LAUGH]
>> Yeah, absolutely.
>> Fast enough, but I am guessing based
on later in this article he talks
about porting some C code over to Haskell,
maybe he is a C programmer or
RASP programmer or
something like where he has kind
of different definition of what it
means to be performant and fast enough.
>> That would make sense.
>> Yeah, I'm just guessing, I don't know.
Hopefully Jake can can tell us or we could
probably read and find out who knows.
>> [LAUGH]
>> So
then it gets into really the meat
of what we're doing here.
And I guess Sara, do you wanna kinda
explain the process that he goes through
to profile this code and
figure out what's going on with it.
>> So profiling and Haskell is actually
extremely simple because you can
literally just run stack build dash
dash profile to build it with that and
then add a dash p to exec And
that's it, it prints you
you out this like really nice profile,
tells you everything you need to know.
It's got all your time allocations,
all that good stuff.
So it's super useful.
It doesn't really take any overhead
to implement or anything like that.
So, definitely great tool.
>> Yeah, it is surprisingly easy to use,
I don't know what to think there if it's
stack, doing a bunch of lifting for you.
Or somewhere deeper in the stack
like COBOL or GHC or something else.
But yeah, you just throw this dash dash
profile option onto your build and
then pass another option to
the program when you run it.
And boom, you get this output that
tells you yeah, your program spent,
in this guy's case 70, no more than
that 85% of your time, coming up with
random integer values, which is crazy,
>> Right.
>> And it's it's also really useful to
look at this in terms of percentage time
because already I've lost track of
the fact that we're only taking a second.
I see 85% and that's way too high,
we gotta make that number lower.
>> [LAUGH]
>> [LAUGH] So yeah,
I mentioned earlier that the de facto
standard random number library in
Haskel being called random is a bit of a
problem because it has, it's really slow.
Which is what this guy figures out in
his relatively small program where
he's generating all these boards and
checking to see if they're valid.
None of that business logic is the slow
part, it's the random number generation.
>> Right, which seems crazy.
>> Yeah.
>> You always think that the logic would
take more time.
>> Right.
>> Which is
kind of what he explains is that his like
assumption is, it's got to be the logic.
And then once he starts using profiling,
he's like, it's not the logic at all.
>> Yeah which is one of the huge upsides
of profiling is you write your program and
don't care about what part is fast.
And then if it's too slow,
which isn't even a given,
sometimes you can write just atrociously,
it's really slow looking code, but
then it runs fast enough to because
your inputs not big enough or whatever.
And as soon as you run into a performance
problem throw the profiler out and
you might be surprised at what you find.
>> Exactly.
>> Cuz I wouldn't have guessed at
the beginning of this article that
the random number generation
would be the slow part.
I can flip coins pretty fast,
I can roll dice pretty fast,
that's not gonna be the slow part.
>> Yeah, exactly and
I think as programmers we might
be a little predisposed to think,
my logic must be wrong, rather than
the library being the slow thing.
>> Right, because so often,
especially in the type of code that we do,
the library is almost never at fault.
And the language-
>> Exactly.
>> Is never at fault.
It's always us, but that's more so for
bugs than performance.
And we rarely have reason
to look at performance.
Generally, things are fast enough for
us with Haskell.
But when you do,
it can be surprising to find, because
I know as a library author and this
probably applies to many library authors,
I don't run benchmarks
against my library code.
I just kind of assume that it's
fast enough and if I'm using it for
a particular problem, I'll definitely
make sure it's fast enough for that.
But I may not have envisioned usage
like this if I wrote this library in
the first place.
>> Right.
>> So the fact that it can be used
in all these different contexts and
that authors aren't typically focused on
that means that yeah library code can be
the slow part and profiling is the thing
to tell you that as fast as possible.
So then he gets into talking
about how he after he identified
this random number generation as the slow
part of his program, how he fixed it.
And we don't wanna get too far
off into the weeds of that, but
it's impressive, to me at least, that he
imported this C program into Haskell.
It's been a long time since I've
had reason to look at C code and
I think that's true for
you too right Sara?
>> Yes, absolutely.
Not since I think maybe
junior year of college.
>> Yeah, so it's been a while.
I don't think I'd do as well as him,
[LAUGH]
but it looks like it paid off.
I mean, he speed his program up
by like six times by ditching
the standard library and using his own.
>> Right, which is already
a very impressive speed up.
>> And then he goes on to ask, I think
a very important question when you're
looking at performance improvements.
Because well, what he asks is
what did we have to give up
in order to get this
performance improvement?
And I feel like that's
an important question because
sometimes when you're focusing
on sort of a sub problem,
in this case performance,
you can lose sight of the bigger picture.
And so you can make something
that's really, really fast, but
then it's a huge pain in the butt to use.
>> Right and that would kinda just
defeat the purpose of having it at all.
If it's not simple to use then why use it?
>> Right, yeah, ideally,
we could keep the same interface and
swap out the internals and make it faster.
That's the best case scenario.
So I don't think he quite
achieved that here.
But it is surprising how
little he had to change.
If you look at the, obviously our
listeners can't actually look at the code,
but the original code that he
wrote with the slow one and
the new code that he
wrote with the fast one.
And they're almost the same,
like if you squint they look the same.
>> [LAUGH] Definitely.
>> Which I think is a great metric to have
in mind when you're profiling code in
Haskell or really in any language is keep
the call site looking almost the same and
try to update the internals
without break in the API.
>> Right, if one of our listeners
wanted to look at this code,
is this article found in Haskell Weekly?
>> It is, as per usual.
It will also be in the show notes for
this episode, we'll have a link to it.
>> Perfect.
>> And so moving on, this guy, Jake,
he again runs into this problem
that I would not run into of
saying that 126 milliseconds,
the new run time is just too slow.
He can't abide by that,
>> [LAUGH] 126 how slow?
>> [LAUGH] I mean, if it was 126 seconds,
maybe I'd agree but milliseconds,
>> Yeah.
>> I'm gonna hit the return key and
it'll be done almost instantaneously.
But yeah, he talks about how he
went on to improve it and again,
the actual mechanics of what he did to
speed it up aren't super interesting.
It's that he continued to use profiling
to identify the hot spots in his program.
So instead of saying, well, I've swapped
out the random number generator so
I can stop worrying about that part and
move on to something else
that I think is the problem.
He ran the profiler again and
discovered, no,
the random number generation
is still the slow part.
Even though it's been sped up so much,
it still takes a big chunk of the time.
Which again, is really surprising,
you mentioned before about
how libraries aren't often the problem
with bugs, but can be with performance.
And with bugs,
when you fix them, they're gone.
>> Right.
>> But with performance,
it can't really be fixed.
It can just get faster, or I guess it
could get slower if you did something bad.
>> [LAUGH]
>> But, isn't it interesting that you
can spend a bunch of effort, he wrote
a whole new random number generator and-
>> And it's still slow.
>> And it's still the slow part, [LAUGH]
>> Right.
>> So yeah, that to me is just the huge
positive benefit that profiling has versus
kind of staring at code and hoping you can
identify which part will probably be slow.
As it will tell you, no,
even though you've already put a ton of
work into that it's still the slow part.
>> Yeah, absolutely,
I mean, I definitely think it's helpful
to have that kind of information.
Especially if you don't have to
do a ton of set-up or anything.
It's such a useful tool.
There's no reason really not to use it,
but I think it's also good to keep in mind
like we had brought up the kinda
of exchange that goes on
with making something more performing
versus what you're using for the program.
>> Right, you don't wanna loose
track of that bigger picture.
>> Exactly.
>> Yeah, and you mentioned that it's
really easy to do this which it is,
and it's still interesting
though cuz even here at work,
I don't think we've ever
profiled our code base.
Actually you said we did that once
actually when I wasn't here, right?
>> Right, when the boss is
away the mice will play but-
>> Boss isn't here quick profile
of the code.
>> [LAUGH] Cody and
I were working on a problem and
the code base is just like
a bug that we had found.
And he suggested using profiling and
I'd never used that before,
I was like what kind of profile
are you trying to make here.
What does that even mean.
And so he kind of explained it to me and
we tried to use it and
while we didn't use it for very long, it
was still a very interesting experience to
have something tell us what was going on.
>> Yeah, and I think you mentioned that
you didn't end up using this profiling
report to actually solve the problem.
So something else popped up, but the
profiling at the very least told you that
there wasn't one thing that's taking
in this case like 85% of the time.
>> Right
>> It was a bunch of little things.
Which can be a lot less satisfying.
If you run the profiler and it says, well,
you spent at most 5% of your time
in any given part of your program.
You might have to do some harder thinking
to figure out how to speed that up.
>> Right, we were hoping for
more of a straightforward answer, but
I guess it's also good to know that
nothing we're using is overtly wrong.
>> Yeah, that's very encouraging.
That's a good way to look at it.
>> Yeah.
>> So yeah, that kinda covers this
blog post talking about profiling
Haskell programs to speed them up in
maybe the best case by ten times but
in the, typical case,
probably quite a bit.
Is there anything else you wanted to
mention about profiling in Haskell?
>> I think we pretty
much covered it honestly.
>> Yeah, I think the only thing I had to
add was that I profiled some programs.
In my high school career,
none of them have been as
great a success story as this.
So it's not like,
throw profiling at your problem and
it'll magically get ten times faster.
But right as we discussed,
it can still be validating to see that
there isn't one huge hot spot where
it's slowing everything else down and
you weren't even thinking about it.
>> Right?
>> And
I just feel the need to reiterate again,
this is such a good way to think
about performance problems and
to me that means don't think about them
at all until it becomes a problem.
And then when they do, throw it to at it
that tells you exactly where the problem
is rather than trying to guess.
>> I think that's the best way to honestly
look at performance problems because you
should mostly optimize just making
the code as the best as it can be, and
then after that if it becomes an issue-
>> Yeah.
>> To try and solve it.
>> Yeah, and
we touched on this already, but
if you're writing the code without
an itoid performance, and you
were focusing on making a nice expressive
API or something that's easy to use.
Then when you have the need to
make it more performant, and
you maintain that API,
you're meeting both goals.
Versus if you right out of the gate start
jumping through some hoops just to right
code that you think will be faster,
you might end up with a much worse API for
almost no benefit.
>> Right?
>> So I agree.
Write the nice API and
then if you needed to be faster,
just go ahead and make it faster.
>> Then maybe not like less
than a second is too short.
>> [LAUGH] Yeah,
that's still where we disagree.
Maybe if this guys was at Google Scale or
writing some web service that needed to
turn these requests around real fast,
people really wanted to solve this
carnival game, I could see it.
But it's definitely a good practice and
that's something I've noticed in my
personal programming with Haskell is that,
you get the ability to sort of look
into things that may not be worth
your while to do at your day job,
but are still fun and interesting.
And then put another tool in your toolbox,
that you can use later on.
>> Yeah, definitely.
>> So I bet, you mentioned Cody doing or
using profiling for
a problem here at work.
And I bet that's not
the first time he used it.
So he was hacking away at something at
home, and found that profiling was a neat
tool, and figured out how to use it and
then boom, applied it at worked.
>> Cowboy Cody, I would guess that wasn't
the first time you used it, [LAUGH]
>> Good old Cowboy Cody.
Yeah, and I guess the final thing I wanted
to mention here about profiling in Haskell
performance is that it's very possible to
write Haskell that is really, really fast.
This guy ended up with a program that
simulated 100,000 board states and
checked them to see if they were winners
or losers, and did it in 70 milliseconds?
>> Right.
>> And when you look at the performance of
other languages that are as expressive as
Haskell, it's hard to find one
that can get to be that quick.
So the fact that Haskell gives us the best
of both worlds when we need it is awesome,
I love that about it.
>> Is there anything you don't love
about Haskell though, [LAUGH]?
>> [LAUGH] Good question, no,
[LAUGH] Haskell is the perfect language.
All right, well, thanks for
joining me today Sara to talk
about profiling and Haskell.
It's nice to have you on the show again.
>> Absolutely, it was nice to be here.
>> And thank you for
listening to the Haskell Weekly podcast.
If you liked what you heard here
today please go find out more at
haskellweekly.news.
This has been episode 11, and please
be sure to join in next week, see you.
[MUSIC]