hello and welcome to the Haskell weekly
podcast as you might have guessed this
show is about Haskell which is a purely
functional programming language
I'm your host Sarah Lichtenstein I'm an
engineer here at IT / TV with me today
is Andre Schmoyer the engineers thanks
for joining me today Andres thank you
for having me Sarah I'm excited to be
here I think today we're going to be
talking about the hassle face book which
is one of the Haskell weekly topics and
since I'm just starting out here I
thought it would be a pretty good
experience to talk about next to you I'm
the next newest so we have the two most
most junior Haskell learners here yep
I'm actually very excited to continue my
learning experience as well as maybe
even potentially get to a point where I
can start teaching things about Haskell
since it's very interesting topic for me
absolutely and I'm really excited to
hear more in depth about your learning
experience so why don't you tell me a
little bit about what you did to first
learn the language the first thing that
I started doing was reading a book that
would probably everyone has heard of
which is learning you learn you Haskell
for a greater good it's something that
kind of put me a little bit uneasy about
the whole learning experience with
Haskell because while it's a great
learning resource and you know it's free
available online and all the great
things that come with all that there is
one downside to it and it was a little
daunting at first and you know that's
the same thing with every language out
there but one thing that first came to
mind was there's a lot of syntax here
that I am gonna have to learn which is
going to be extremely difficult yeah
absolutely I think I had that same
experience when I first came into shadow
before I started working here when they
had Haskell up on the screens and I she
was just so unlike anything I'd seen
before so it can be really scary at
first yeah yeah definitely
one thing that was brought up to us this
week was into you know Haskell weekly
was the Haskell Facebook and it caught
my attention because
a similar resource to learn you know
Haskell for great good but it's a lot
more quick and succinct and I do say
similar in that they're both beginner
pieces not that you know they match
one-to-one and what they actually teach
right absolutely
is there any takeaways from the frieze
book that you particularly liked or that
you didn't like one thing I really
really liked about reading through that
was how quick and simple each example
was and you know it starts you off slow
with the hello world just like every
other resource out there and yeah I very
much liked that it was quick succinct
and from the last three months that I've
been doing this high school learning
experience most of the topics that were
touched upon there I have been needing
to use absolutely I really like that
they introduced UHC ID almost
immediately because I don't think we
started using that until a little bit
after Taylor got here and it's such a
useful tool I mean we use it every day
yeah definitely so when talking about
the phrase book we can't help but
highlight a couple really important
sections so one of the ones that I
wanted to talk about was continual
checking because they use GHC ID almost
immediately it's the second section in
the phrase book and it's such a useful
tool and I don't think we started using
it until Taylor our lead engineer got
hired here and it's great to see it
represented so early because we use this
every day
yeah definitely ght ID was kind of weird
to me at first when I when I got started
because that we already had a
compilation tool that was already doing
everything for us and then my co-workers
started saying hey you know we also used
GHC ID if we want a much faster
experience with the compilation and all
these things and I was surprised at
first that the compilation side and the
gh tid side was so decoupled from each
other it was really nice to see all of
these errors instantly happen not having
to wait for the compiler to pick up the
changes and be a little slow about it so
I very much liked that GHC ID was
instantly brought it
yeah the instant feedback loop that it
provides is so invaluable it's amazing
definitely are there any sections that
you particularly thought were
interesting or would be useful to
somebody trying to switch for to high
school from let's say an imperative
language the one thing that came to mind
when I first read through this phrase
book was the fact that at the end of it
they brought up mutable variables and
threading that's not something that you
see often in beginner guidebooks and
under like the learning Haskell for
great good did not touch upon meaningful
variables did not do threading maybe
mentioned it I can't really remember out
the top of my head but definitely wasn't
anything that stuck out with me yeah
those are definitely more complex
subjects so for it to be in a beginners
book is really interesting yeah and I
think this is more a beginner Haskell
that rather than a beginner programming
phrase book now it could be seen either
way regardless because you can just pick
this up and start coding in hands go and
be perfectly fine but one thing that I
have from my background of coming from
an imperative language my background
comes from Java Android on the front end
and then had done some pretty extensive
node frame working and all of that in
the backend so I come mostly from
imperative and I've been doing it for
quite a while now so seeing all this
here is a good thing to see because if I
would have started off with this I would
have been like okay well I'm thinking
and imperative and I'm gonna switch over
to Haskell but I'm gonna leave the
functional things a little bit behind
and to like start getting used to the
syntax and although the other weird
things that come with it right I
definitely could understand that what
was the hardest part for you from
switching from an imperative language to
something so functional like Haskell the
hardest part was the syntax weirdly
enough I took a very long time to
realize some of the different things
that Haskell does to the syntax like
not needing to say which monitor you're
in explicitly so you could just regular
just use it as if it was already there a
lot of the the small syntax things
really took me out of my comfort zone
and so once I get through that learning
all of the different things Haskell does
and functional and all that wasn't as
difficult especially because JavaScript
and all of those languages could
technically be used in a functional
manner they're usually not because they
have a bunch of state saving and all
that that you can do but I very much
enjoyed once I get through the syntax I
enjoyed being able to just apply all the
knowledge I had into this great
functional language that doesn't usually
allow state saving absolutely that
definitely makes sense are there any
other parts of the phrase book that
you'd like to highlight or talk about
here well I
you mentioned saying coming from an
imperative language what other things
stood up to me the if then and for loops
from an imperative language they're used
pretty extensively a assume you agree as
well yes for the experience I had in
imperative languages we definitely did a
lot of those loops
yeah and one thing that I've learned
over the past three months working on a
Haskell server-side coding is that if
statements and for loops have been used
very sparingly I think for loops I have
not seen one yet which is a crazy thing
to think about and if statements we use
very rarely because most of our coding
is parsing different types and making
sure everything is type safe and our
responses and if statements don't really
come into any of that so it's
interesting to see that once coming back
after three months and reading through
this face book that if statements are a
thing in the programming world I mean
obviously but it is nice to be able to
come from an imperative language and
have the same syntax that were used to
but then once you start actually working
purely in a has
Manor you stop using the things that
you're used to from imperative languages
yeah definitely hilariously enough up
until I read this Facebook I didn't even
know that Haskell had four loops yeah
that's actually a pretty good point I
mean you've been doing this for a year
and a half how was your first three
months of your learning experience my
beginning learning experience I like to
call my brain melt because every day I
would come to work and I would pair with
the other engineers and I would feel
like my brain was melting out of my ears
because it was just so much new
information and it was just so vastly
different from anything else that I had
ever learned
but as affectionately as I called it the
brain melt I like to say that are also
reformed into a bigger better brain so
yeah it was definitely a challenge for
me I agree completely there I I'm going
through that brain melt now and you know
going through the first few weeks was
difficult to say the least it it wasn't
more that I couldn't understand what was
happening it was more that trying to get
your thoughts into a functional manner
became a lot more difficult when at the
same time I had to learn the syntax for
Haskell so I could totally see that
brain melt being a thing for Haskell
learning because you're learning so many
things at once
not unlike learning programming for the
first time so maybe yeah maybe it was
like that when I first started I did
start at a slightly young age so I had a
lot more time available in my handset it
could be that a slower pace into Haskell
is much less demanding but you and me we
both sort of jumped in there and I had
to learn it as quick as possible and I
think it's a pretty cool skill to have
to be able to just jump in and brain
brain melt for a week or two and just
keep on learning so yeah hopefully one
day in that what year-and-a-half I'll
I'll look back and think the same thing
that you're saying absolutely
what really I think kind of helps me
solidify my knowledge is being able to
like work with our co-workers and some
of our new newer co-workers like I've
distinctly remember pairing with you on
one of your first days and explaining
some concept and being like wow I know
stuff now so I'm sure you're gonna have
a similar experience with our new intern
which will be fun for you yep yep
definitely I've already started seeing
that happen and I it's a good feeling to
be able to explain something after you
very recently just learned it totally
agree there okay well is there anything
else maybe about the freeze book or
about learning Haskell any tips or
tricks well one thing that I thought of
when I first started learning Haskell
was learning a Haskell for great good is
a great resource and when I first
started reading it I it was a daunting
thing it was too much at once and I
think it kind of gave me a false sense
of this is going to be extremely
difficult and possibly not possible so
well it's a great resource I think it
shouldn't be the first thing you read I
think the first thing you read could be
this phrase book I mean it's kind of
hard to say at the moment but just
thinking back after these three months I
think the phrase book is a lot more
easier thing to start with then learning
a great high school for a great good now
that's not to say that learning has go
for a great good is not something you
shouldn't read I think it's a great read
and I think it will solidify a lot of
the things that you've been slowly
learning while doing test programs and
things like that so I enjoyed reading
both and I will probably read them again
after a month or so after you know
getting a little more stable with my
high school writing and reading and
certain things like that absolutely I
definitely think that this phrase book
would be a good first introduction
before the learn you a Haskell book just
because it's so succinct and so clear
and it does make a lot of good bridges
from imperative to functional angry
thanks for being on the show with me
today Andres
thank you for having me I enjoyed
talking about my first experience as a
pastor absolutely me too and thank you
for listening to the Haskell weekly
podcast if you like what you heard find
out more at our website haskell weekly
news also please rate and review us on
iTunes it helps a lot half the weekly is
brought to you by IT Pro TV the tech
skills development platform for IT
professionals Nelson our employer yes
that too then anyone who needs their IT
needs to WWI T Pro TV for all of their
learning needs thanks again for
listening we'll see you next week