Oh
[Music]
hello and welcome to the Haskell weekly
podcast
I'm your host Taylor fossick I'm the
lead engineer at IT Pro TV with me today
is Cameron Guerra one of the engineers
on my team thanks for joining me today
cam thanks for having me Taylor it's
good to have you on the show and on this
show we talk about Haskell no surprise
there it's a purely functional
programming language but what
specifically are we gonna be talking
about today cam gonna be talking about
why Haskell why Haskell what do you mean
by that
well there was a blog post by the
Symantec team at github called why high
school and why they chose Haskell for
that project kind of led by Timothy Klem
so okay so github is using Haskell in
production that's awesome
yeah the big secret we're not the only
company out there with with Haskell code
in problem there's some big time but
before we kind of get into their article
what are we gonna start with what is
Symantec and why maybe this has a little
good for them yeah so Symantec is a I
guess package or program by the github
team and it's what they use to analyze
and compare source code on their servers
so like when you submit a pull request
to github you may notice that in
addition to like being able to break it
down by file you know jump to this file
in the diff you can also jump to
specific functions and say show me the
changes on this function alone and
Symantec is a tool on their back-end
that allows that to happen so they can
parse the source code of JavaScript or
Python or whatever and figure out oh
this is a function and something within
that function changed no that's awesome
why was this announcement big news this
is a big deal because github obviously
is a giant force in the development
community mm-hmm a lot of people use
github to manage their source code and
they're just a huge company so they've
got lots of people working for them and
this is a big deal because haskell is a
pretty small community especially in
relation to all of github you know right
there aren't too many companies out
there using haskell a couple of the big
ones that I can think of off the top my
head are facebook and Nike mm-hm and us
of course but you know ITT
yeah we're coming we're coming for your
Facebook ID Pro TV the next Facebook the
IT world but yeah this is this is just a
big deal cuz github is a big company and
Haskell's a small language and it is
really interesting to a lot of people
yeah it's good to see the community
growing you know and yeah bigger
organizations picking up this language
allows for the community to to obviously
grow I mean there's so many employees at
github and you know obviously just the
semantics team right now it's using high
school but I'm sure it's spreading
through their organization and kind of
its gonna allow our community to
continue to grow and have you know more
experts in the field you know absolutely
it's really cool even if you're at a
smaller company and you're interested in
using haskell this can be really useful
because you can point to github and say
look they're using it and it's working
for them it can work for us too right
and a lot of the articles out there
about why people choose haskell are are
pretty normal like they're pretty
standard like this this and this but why
do you think you know github kind of
chose this different path there's
different paths to using haskell right
yeah so for a lot of the blog posts that
I've read in the past about why
companies have chose haskell it you sort
of see the same reasons trotted out you
know haskell is a pure language so you
don't have to worry about side effects
and weird parts of your code or as lazy
evaluation so you don't have to worry
about things being evaluated even if you
don't end up using them or it you know
lets you express complicated ideas in a
small amount of code and the first time
you see that set of arguments it might
be compelling but the fifth or tenth or
under the time you see them you're like
okay i get it
I know Haskell has those things what
else can I do mm-hmm that's awesome yeah
and I think it's really cool that they
kind of broke it down they had some
different reasons for choosing high
schools so do you kind of want to kick
off you know what reasons they chosen
and why they chose high school sure as I
mentioned there's kind of the bog
standard reasons for why people
typically choose Haskell but one thing
that I like about this article is they
didn't dwell on that too much they said
yeah these are all characteristics of
Haskell these are reasons why you might
want to choose
but they ended up focusing more on what
come or things that are only possible
because of those kind of fundamental
characteristics but more compelling
reasons for their particular business
case and I think the one that they start
with is control flow right correct yep
and so by control flow what they mean is
that in a typical programming language
something like Java or C sharp or go the
control flow is built into the language
itself so like if a statement is above
another one you know that it's going to
get executed first so you need top to
bottom left to right basically and in
Haskell that's not necessarily the case
you can write code that looks the same
but one version of it might be
synchronous and another version of it
might be asynchronous so you know this
comes up in JavaScript all the time
where the synchronous function is really
easy to write but you block the main
thread for a long time and if you're
doing something with a web UI then your
UI
stalls wow that synchronous thing is
happening so you want to write stuff in
this async fashion but then you have to
do like nested callback so you do the
async await or something like that right
so the syntax you have to change the way
that you write your code in order to
change how the control flow works mm-hmm
but with Haskell you the code that you
write looks the same but you can change
how it's implemented or not implemented
but executed right right so pretty much
higher up in in the program is where
kind of the deciding factor of oh is a
sinker this asynchronous or synchronous
like exactly and the further you get
into the code it just looks the same and
it's not you don't have to like be
worried of Oh am i writing this the
right way mm-hmm because in the end I
want this result like the code you write
is can be executed however you want it
to be executed you just tell that you
know once you start to write the
executable and make that code come true
yeah and that's especially useful for
the semantics team because what they're
doing is parsing and analyzing source
code so they want to be able to parse
let's say a Python file and analyze it
as if it was executing but not actually
execute it mm-hmm and so it becomes
really powerful to have you know the
to lascal provides to be able to manage
the control flow in the same way that
you manage regular data in other
languages right so the other thing they
kind of talked about and the reason they
chose it was runtime correctness and you
know they gave a lot of really great you
know things we've kind of experienced
but what were some of the things you
took away from you know that that aspect
of the article I really liked that
aspect of the article and I'm glad that
they brought it up because when you read
about let's say Elm another language
that's in the same vein they bring that
front and center all the time it's like
on their homepage you know they say you
can write programs with confidence and
not have to worry about runtime errors
and I wish Haskell marketed more in that
direction because it is really powerful
to not have to worry about those runtime
errors and trust that when you write the
program and it compiles it will almost
want or what you intended for it to do
right and you don't have to worry oh
crap well I forgot that this value could
be null so then you get a
nullpointerexception in production or
you forgot I changed the name of that
method last week and I forgot to update
it here at this call site so now I'm
getting a method not found error right
it saves you from those really tedious
kind of rote problems and so that you
can focus on developing new features and
shipping those out to your users rather
than fixing some bug that popped up in
your issue tracker for the hundredth
time yeah one thing I wish Haskell was
magical and it can be we just aren't
necessarily using it right now at ITP
OTV is the kind of a way to get away
from accidentally like miss aligning
like a value for a JSON or something
like that because we've kind of you know
some of our parsing for our JSON parsing
we use the applicative stuff and that
kind of enters that like hey this could
end up being different because you miss
a line you know the keys or whatever so
I I think as a group of developers I
would like for us to kind of lead lean
more into okay let's not you duplicative
just so we can make sure we keep our
sanity because I mean a few months ago I
was
just banging my head against the wall
trying to figure out like wait a second
what's happening here and sure enough it
was just a Miss a flip flopped key
mm-hmm that brings up a good point that
just because Haskell gets rid of a large
portion of runtime errors doesn't mean
that it gets rid of all of them and in
fact it's not even desirable to get rid
of all of them because you'd have to pay
so much upfront in order to do that but
there are some things like you mentioned
with the applicative syntax where they
allow you to sort of accidentally
introduce problems that are very hard to
detect and there are easy ways around
that in our case doing those
excuse me writing those parsers in a
more monadic style makes it clearer
which things are going where so you can
look at a line and say oh no we're
pulling this field that's named price
but we're pulling it from a you know
object where the key we're looking for
is named and that obviously doesn't line
up right yeah so I mean I do I do think
a lot of the things that Haskell
provides for runtime correct misses are
great so I'm really glad that they kind
of echoed that because like you said Elm
that's something they boast all about
yeah but Haskell you don't really hear
about that until you're in and you're
like oh this isn't gonna let me like
change a function name over here without
updating all the callers like that's not
possible
yep um because that compiler will not
will not be happy with you that's
awesome
the other they make I'm a touchstone was
kind of the research so academia is kind
of leaning more towards high school as a
language that you know these new
research methods are kind of written in
these algorithms and all this various
stuff you know what is what is that
useful for for github you touched on it
a little already in that a lot of
computer science papers are written
using Haskell or a language that's very
close to Haskell but you know that kind
of typical computer science paper that
you read with the the font that
everybody knows and the like you column
layout and the all that stuff the code
that you look at in those papers is a
usually Haskell and if you can take that
code from an established research paper
and more or less copy pasted into your
library and start using it right away
that's a huge win versus if you were
using basically any other language you
would have to think okay how can I port
this behavior that I want that they're
talking about in this paper into the
language that I have and you have to
change the semantics you have to change
the you know actual shape of the code
itself you have to make sure everything
works the way you expected so it's just
it's just more difficult to do that now
that's not a common problem for you know
workaday programmers like us you know
we're writing web apps we're not looking
into research papers to figure out well
how do we parse JSON it's it's kind of a
solved problem at this point right which
is nice but it is also helpful if you're
you know trying to be on the cutting
edge of technology and the growth in
technology mm-hmm research papers have
high school that's where those papers
are still coming out programming
language theory not a solved field and
the semantics team at github is on the
cutting edge of this you know they are
analyzing source code for millions of
software projects across many different
programming languages and they want to
do it quickly effectively safely and the
research is kind of showing them how to
do that and they're able to crib from it
effectively no and I think that's really
awesome so I definitely applaud them for
oh yeah me too this article also kind of
talked about you know the things they
didn't like which is a helpful thing
when you're analyzing okay do I jump in
and go with Haskell or do I you know
lean towards you know the Java or C
sharp or something you know a little
more mainstream yeah I always like it
when I see an article like this and they
include the stuff they didn't like
mm-hmm otherwise it's really easy to
look at it and discount it offhand and
think well they just really like this
and it's their pet language and they
want it to succeed so they're not going
to say anything bad about it is it their
cat language cat or dog people do you
think maybe fish fish people lizard
people I think that's you know it does
add credibility to to this not document
yeah this article very I'm very official
artist
a good term I should use that more often
but they they talk about kind of the
weak tooling aspect this is something
we've come to come to deal with yeah
it's a problem we've definitely run into
right and so you want kind of explain
what we do to kind of counteract this
and sure acknowledge it first just kind
of for a statement of terms I think that
when they talk about tooling they're
talking about like an IDE integration
something like IntelliJ or Visual Studio
where when you're working on code you
can mouse over a certain part and it'll
show you
perhaps the documentation for that thing
or what parameters it expects or where
and your code base that's used you know
mmm stuff that isn't
earth-shattering on its own but a bunch
of small niceties that add up to a
really positive experience and they're
right to say that Haskell is kind of
weak in this regard there are certainly
tools that help the one that we use most
often is GHC ID another one I wish -
another one that I was just thinking
about offhand sided catch off on this
but in Tarot
yeah and Tarot offers like so awesome
IDE experience but it like takes over
people's machines and like crashes them
like yeah and we run into problems with
Haskell IDE engine where the promise of
it is excellent but when you run it for
more than a couple hours it starts
eating up all the RAM it can find mm-hmm
so I think the Haskell is moving in the
right direction and they seem to have
landed on the same solution as us which
is you have your editor up on maybe the
left-hand side of your screen and your
compiler output up on the right-hand
side
and you kind of stitch things together
yourself mm-hmm
obviously not ideal but definitely
workable yeah and just to kind of color
that a bit from my point of view I think
this comes down mostly to lack of
resources because developing all of that
tooling just takes a lot of work and for
these other languages like Java or
JavaScript you have millions of people
working in these languages and that's
not true for Haskell so I'm excited to
see github talk about this because if
they get people interested and excited
about Haskell and working in it then the
tooling is naturally going to improve as
more people get it
with the community no I think that's a
very good point so where to go get hub
awesome well they also kind of talk
about no dependent types why do you
think this is an issue for them so we
already talked a little how they kind of
borrow from current programming language
research and apply it to their problem
domain so they're already in a kind of
unusual situation as far as that goes
and I think that's why they feel this
pain from the lack of dependent typing
because they're pushing
Haskell's type system to its limits and
haskell while it's well revered for
having a strong useful type system it
does not have dependent types and
there's lots of things you can do to try
to pretend like you have them or give
you some of the same benefits of
dependent types but at the end of the
day it doesn't happen and I can't speak
personally to this because I haven't run
into this particular limitation in the
type of development that we do and I
think that most developers would not run
into this problem you know they wouldn't
think oh well I wish I had dependent
types here it doesn't it doesn't come up
that often hmm
but for them it does I don't want to
discount their experience here obviously
they wish they had this and they don't
so the you know the only languages that
do have this they're they're few and far
between stuff like Agda and idris they
have this but they're they're a little
less production-ready than haskell is
they're not used quite as widely right
yeah I don't think we've really thought
of dependent types has never really been
a thing mm-hmm I think that you know
it's a great idea and I'm really
interested in it but day to day there's
not too much where I'm like ah this
would be so much easier if I had
dependent types and yeah
awesome well they also kind of talk
about kind of the lack of info
yeah I like that terminology used in for
a glue it sounds like a something you'd
buy from a TV channel or something right
here here's your info group can talk but
yeah so they've mentioned that for the
actual meat and potatoes of their
program Haskell does a great job but for
the stuff where they have to worry about
like deploying or making containers or
stuff like that it's a little more
difficult and that's mostly because it's
similar to the tooling problem we're
just
not as many people have been using it so
there's not a can solution for like oh I
want to deploy this to AWS or I want to
make a container out of this you can
definitely do those things but you're
probably gonna have to do them yourself
rather than just picking something off
the shelf that says okay yeah I'll
deploy this Python program to Heroku or
whatever it's a little more boilerplate
yeah and and again not a showstopper and
not terribly difficult to get around but
just annoying that it's not there yeah
but then one of the more interesting
ones that I feel like we've encountered
a lot is the kind of the performance
issues with lazy evaluation I think for
us we've had various scripts and you
know things as you know our code is
trying to figure out what it's gonna do
until it actually needs to execute
something it just builds up this giant
funk that you know hangs out all over
the place really everything slows down
you're like what's going on mm-hmm
and then you put one exclamation point
in one place and everything works again
yeah and you know we've thinkin I talked
about the language extension strict data
strict data and so that's how they kind
of I guess kind of acted it but why do
you think for them that's a big issue I
think that lazy evaluation is a
double-edged sword in Haskell for sure
and the main reason for that is that
Haskell is pretty much the only
programming language that I can think of
off the top my head that is lazy by
default every other programming language
is strict by default mm-hmm so as
programmers we're not used to
identifying and solving problems that
stem from laziness because we rarely
encounter them in other languages you
have to explicitly opt in so like in
Python you can make a generator or in
JavaScript you do all the async stuff to
pretend like you have laziness
whereas in Haskell it's everywhere so
people just aren't used to looking for
those types of problems and so they're
bound to crop up every now and then that
being said they're usually not terribly
hard to diagnose and fix once you have a
couple tricks in your bag but the first
time that you run into them they can be
completely mystifying because you can
look at code and it looks totally
reasonable but for whatever reason the
way that you wrote it either you know
generates too much too many thunks like
you mentioned and you don't evaluate
them at the right time or just something
like that and it can be really difficult
to figure out what's going on and again
this comes back to the lack of tooling
if there was better tooling to analyze
the laziness of your program this would
be an easier problem to solve so maybe
booth time maybe with time all right the
last one this one hits home for us is
they kind of said you know it's got a
notorious reputation of being too hard
to learn as you know a bunch of junior
developers for the most part - you and
Cody Learning High School in within the
last two years you know it's had it's
like a little bit of growing pain in the
beginning but once you understand like
the concept and the paradigm of
functional programming it becomes a lot
more attainable yeah to really conquer
the language and you know have a good
understanding of it without you maybe
not the deepest understanding but gonna
have a general idea of what's going on
so that what do they have to say about
that I think they say something very
similar to what we think and I hope have
said but if we haven't yet we'll say now
that
Haskell's does have this reputation of
being difficult to learn but it's not
that difficult and it's especially not
that difficult to get to a working
knowledge where maybe you don't have a
super deep understanding of everything
that's going on but you can get work
done and you can feel effective and be
effective without knowing you don't you
don't have to learn category theory or
really like understand what is a man add
in order to program in haskell day to
day and they say especially with some
type of you know mentor or tutor on the
team you can get people up to speed
really quickly and we've seen that we
hired somebody a month ago and they got
up to speed basically within the first
week now granted they obviously don't
understand all of haskell everything i
mean it's a huge language there's a lot
to know right but they know enough to be
effective and write code that works and
submit it for PR and get it you know
into production within a week or two of
being hired right it's not
insurmountable yeah then I think another
attribute for us attribute to like the
ability to learn high school has been
like the idea of promiscuous pairing
which for those of those of you
listeners yes check it out there's a
cool paper on it so we've been doing it
for a little while now and we find it
very effective and it allows us
knowledge transfer it really well so you
know I did a shameless plug for Jason
yeah he's all about it and it really
ties in to what get this semantics team
at github said of you know having a
tutor somebody who knows the ropes to
show the new person promiscuous pairing
just forces that every time around
teaching I'm whispering and whispering
into a microphone that's kind of rude
alright and obviously this program is
pretty large semantic like as far as
like yeah the depth of what it can do
but it's only 20,000 lines of code
mmm-hmm yeah and that's amazing because
as they point out several times in their
article if they had written this in
let's say Java they may have written
20,000 lines of just boilerplate whereas
the entire Haskell program would fit
into that same space so yeah it's
phenomenal they can get so much done
with so little code yeah I think it's
just incredible so I I do think this is
a really great article and I would
definitely encourage all of our
listeners to check it out for sure but
you have anything else you'd like to add
on it I don't think so
just want to reiterate that it's great
to see another big company like github
using haskell in production and
generally coming away with a positive
experience obviously they had some
things that they didn't like too much
but overall they were really positive
about it and it seems like if they had
to choose it again they would yeah we'll
see the octocat soon with some sweet
high school tattoos yeah the purely
functional octocat yeah well awesome
we'll tailor it's been really really fun
talking it's been great talking with you
cam thanks for being on the show with me
of course always anytime and thank you
for listening to the haskell weekly
podcast this has been episode number 13
if you liked what you heard find out
more at our website haskell weekly dot
news also please take a minute to rate
and review us
I Tunes it helps us out a lot I think
right now Cameron and I are the only
people that have reviewed us Cecil yeah
reviewed this episode like all of the
other ones we've done so far was
actually recorded in our own office the
IT Pro TV studios so I just want to give
a shout out to IT Pro for recording this
whole thing woohoo
and I - Pro what we do is provide IT
training that's both effective and
entertaining so that sounds interesting
to you please go find out more at IT Pro
TV thanks again for listening and we'll
see you next week bye adios