[MUSIC]
Hello and
welcome to the Haskell weekly podcast.
I'm your host Cody Goodman.
I'm a senior engineer at ITProTV.
With me today is Andres one
of the engineers on my team.
Thanks for joining me today, Andres.
>> Yeah, thanks for having me, Cody.
I'm excited to talk about
some fun stuff with you.
>> Cool, this shows about Haskell,
a purely function program language.
Today we're gonna be talking
about Refined which is a way
of moving a lot of runtime
errors into the types system.
There is an interesting blog post recently
in Haskell Weekly that explored using
Refined to solve a few common
cases of runtime errors,
such as division by zero, or
making sure a string is uppercase.
Things that you'd usually
have to worry about runtime.
Andres, what were your thoughts on it?
>> The first thing that came to
mind was it's very interesting
to think of type checking
at the runtime level.
And one of the things that first
stood out to me was what is the use?
High level seems very useful.
After diving into it a little bit,
seems like maybe some of these
features should be implemented more
directly into the compiler level, or
even just as part of
the actual Haskell language.
But we can talk more about that in a bit.
>> Great.
Definitely want to talk
more about that in a bit.
Haskell is actually moving towards
supporting dependent typing I hear
in the next year, so we'll probably have
something pretty useful and workable.
In terms of Refined specifically though,
and things that we can use today,
what do you think are the trade-offs
in deciding to use something like that?
Is there a lot of ceremony involved
with using something like Refined?
So runtime errors are expensive but
is it more expensive to implement
something with Refined?
>> I think the major point
that came to me first is
how much extra coding work do I need
to actually do to be able to use this?
And I think that's probably the major
downside to using something like Refined.
We've gotten to a point where we
are trying to fix, or not really fix but
more solve a problem that isn't already
solved by using type checking and
runtime checking and all of these things.
And the first thing that sticks out is
lots of different conversion functions.
So there's a lot of extra boilerplate
required around using Refined and
using it in such a way that
is helpful to the code.
And that's my first takeaway,
and there's some extra stuff in
there as well that is very nice.
It's just that my first question is,
how much extra coding do I have to do?
And it's actually a little bit
more than I'm comfortable with.
>> Okay.
And like you mentioned, part of the reason
for that is because it's an external
library and not something
integrated with a compiler, so
it's exciting to see if that helps
reduce that ceremony and boilerplate.
>> Yeah, definitely something that
I think would be better benefited
to be directly inside
the language than as a library.
But it would be nice to know, or
at least to be able to use it in practice,
to be able to see if is it
actually a lot of work?
Or if it's just something that
I get from the representation
of it in the blog post and
the documentation.
>> Right.
>> What did you think,
as a first glance, what did you
first think that this was gonna do?
>> I think that Refined
is really interesting.
I know there's a lot of ceremony
with setting up things at first.
I do wonder, though, if you go from the
approach of wrecked by construction, and
you eventually build up a lot
of these refined helpers.
If it pretty much gets rid of the
ceremony, once you've integrated into your
normal workflow of programming and
start thinking in terms of runtime errors.
If you think in terms of using Refined,
and does this value Refined,
before I pass it to the next function?
If you start thinking that way and
just implementing those things
as a lever you could reuse,
I think it could be a lot more convenient.
It's harder to make that argument though
without having a flushed out example.
>> Yeah, I agree.
I think once this is actually in use,
and we're able to see more of how it
is used, then we can make that call.
It's just one of my major downsides
that I can see just off the bat.
If the extra work required to
wrapping it and unwrapping it,
better than just doing that
type checking by hand.
Or, is that actually worth it?
>> Right, and I think that when you look
at some of the examples, by nature they're
trying to teach something, so
they're gonna be a little contrived.
You have to simplify things to teach the
concept first, but it would be good if we
had somewhere to go from there, layers on
the different things that we've learned.
Maybe having Refined
check at compile time,
that a string is uppercase is invaluable.
But if you're verifying
social security numbers,
maybe verifying that they are again eight,
nine digits, then that's
something that could be useful.
>> Yeah, I agree.
However, I do see verification is
usually user input variables and
they're not available at build time.
So I can see that being a major issue, so
let's say that you have a Refined
type of positive number.
What, how will the compiler know that
a user is gonna input two minus one
if you don't actually go through
the entire refining it and
unrefining it in the process?
Which, when you refine the two minus
one it's gonna throw an error,
or however you decide to
actually implement it, and
that is the same as if you just
did an If statement for example.
So I'm a bit hard to see the difference of
actually type checking in code, and
type checking in the types itself.
>> Right, that's a great point.
I think the special sauce,
so to speak, lies in that.
It's really not about
verifying that value.
It is in the exhaustiveness checking
that we get by defining that and
how it forces programmers.
If you are throwing an error
on exhaustiveness checks,
it forces the programmers to
handle that case upfront.
Whereas you could have missed
that case at a dynamic language.
>> Yeah, I agree.
And that's obviously where we see
the benefits of this library.
The question I had was, is it worth it?
Do we want to add all
this extra complexity?
Just to be more safe for
the developer to write this code.
And the upsides I think are still
not better than the downsides.
>> Okay.
What do you think about the possibility of
senior engineers using Refined
to write out the types and
stub out implementations?
And then having the rest of the engineers
implementing the functionality for
those things?
>> If most of these types are gonna
be used in a compilation manner,
so we are mainly using Haskell
in a in a web environment.
So most of our types that need type
checking are gonna be user input, and
I think that's where it falls short.
If it is going to be used in
such a way that this type
checking is gonna help in the code
writing, then I think that's a good thing.
So Refined is a great library
to make sure that your types
that are more dynamic than other types,
such as numbers, lists, things like that.
Stay inside the range
they're supposed to be,
then Refined is a great library for that.
Regardless whether it's a senior
engineer doing the structuring or
it's a junior one,
I don't see a difference in that scenario.
>> Okay.
Did you see if it was possible in
the docs, I'm scrolling through them now,
to add Refined values to have
composite Refined values?
>> You mean doing, for example,
one plus one on a Refined value?
>> Sort of.
I mean saying that to
refine this value needs to
both be uppercase and
both be a length of ten.
>> I'm actually not sure exactly how
it's used and that's the idea behind
looking into this library
was to see what my
first thoughts are in just
as a skimming sort of view.
So, is it going to appeal enough for me
to actually sit down and start using it?
I could go in there and start writing
it and see if it feels natural.
If it just feels very unnatural, or
just completely different
than what we're used to.
And I can't actually answer
the question that you're asking there.
>> Right.
>> If it were the case that you can
do that then that's an extra plus.
>> Right, and actually that's
a little bit of a warning sign to me,
and something I see too commonly
in Haskell libraries is
if you can't communicate the really
valuable pieces like that.
So if you can't show how to move past
the trivial examples to something more
complicated but also more useful,
that's a marketing problem as well.
>> Yeah, I agree.
I had the same thought, I said I'm
probably gonna have a different mindset,
when I actually go in there and
play around with it.
But I thought it was more
valuable to have that
viewpoint where I actually
haven't used the code.
I'm just going by what the author
has told me about it, and
so far I'm not 100% agreed on it.
>> Mm-hm.
>> And I think having a little more
examples that could help you understand
what the library is meant to fix and
how it fixes it would
benefit the adoption of it.
>> Right, and I think it's really
valuable for you to look at this from
the mindset of somebody who's just
thinking about looking at Haskell,
thinking about adopting Haskell for
some of these benefits they heard about.
Or maybe is a Haskell user who's
thinking about putting more
type safety into their code base.
That's pretty similar to
the mindset they're going to be in.
And I think you found a valuable
opportunity for anyone who's writing blog
posts about Refined or any documentation,
and that is to give more examples.
And this is true through Haskell
documentation in general, but
especially in here you wanna motivate
not only the simple cases but
the intermediately advanced.
>> Yes, and I actually have
a comment on that one as well.
The last part of the blog post where
they show the examples of using
Refined inside of a JSON type.
As a used case to use Refined to
make sure that your JSON parsing
matches want you want it to be,
that seems like what Refined was
meant to do, at least in my eyesight.
As a server developer for Haskell,
JSON parsing is pretty much a lot of what
we do so we wanna make sure that the input
that comes in is what we want it to be.
And I think Refined
attempted to use liaison
library to help type these
JSON values a little better.
>> Right.
>> However, that seemed to me like
it was an afterthought, it was okay.
We also did this.
They never went into what you can do
with it or what the code can do what?
When you're writing it, if it can make
the parsing less verbose or maybe more
concise, things like that, is what I want
to see when I'm reading a blog post.
It is a fine line though, right?
>> Mm-hm, so what they left is
a footnote about JSON there.
You would have maybe like to
see them leave with that and
then expound upon that example.
>> Yeah, I mean, everyone's thoughts
on what Refined is good for
is obviously different.
I just wanted to get a little
more information upfront about
all the different ways you can use
Refined, not just simple strings and
then by the way, we also do JSON.
>> So, look at their example for a second.
Looks like they find a type called the
alcohol user, who has a name and an age.
They have a Refined type to make sure that
there's at least one
character in the string.
Where would you have usually verified
something like that without Refined?
>> That is a good question.
That would probably depend on
how simple the parsing is.
Most likely I would write it either
directly inside the ASON instance,
or as a conversion of the type.
So if I had a type that
was an alcohol username,
I would have a string to alcohol
username that would type check there and
make sure you can only convert a string to
that type if it is at least one character.
Otherwise you fail.
>> So the difference that would get us
is kind of a more declarative way of
listing out how to parse and
validate that JSON.
>> Right, and if it would also remove
a little bit of the boilerplate code
required to do so.
>> Right, yeah for
building a [INAUDIBLE] syntax for
building the data and stuff like that.
>> Yeah.
>> Thanks for
being on the show with me today, Andres.
>> Yeah, thank you very much.
It was fun doing this.
And something that I actually forgot to
mention at the beginning, I have just
started doing Haskell a couple months ago,
so most of this stuff is brand new to me.
And it helps a lot to read about these
libraries that people want to implement,
just to understand what
people's thoughts are in terms
of Haskell's strict type system and
where it needs to be improved in.
>> Thanks for that very valuable input.
And thank you for
listening to the Haskell Weekly podcast.
If you liked what you heard, find out
more at our website HaskellWeekly.news.
Also, please rate and review us on iTunes.
It helps a lot.
Thanks again for listening.
We'll see you again next week.
[MUSIC]